<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:source="https://source.scripting.com/">
  <atom:link href="https://rsdoiel.github.io/pages.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <channel>
    <title>An Antenna Website</title>
    <description>
      This is the default websites created by the antenna init action.
    </description>
    <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/pages.xml</link>
    <lastBuildDate>27 Dec 25 14:32 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>antenna/0.0.20</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <title>Python Setup on Raspberry Pi OS 6</title>
      <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2025/12/19/python_setup_pi_os_6.html</link>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[A set of quick notes for wrangling Python to work nicely on Raspberry Pi OS 6]]>
      </description>
      <source:markdown># Python Setup on Raspberry Pi OS 6

By R. S. Doiel, 2025-12-19

I like the python programming language but I don&#39;t like to program in it as much as I used to. The trouble is the challenge of versions and packages. At work we&#39;re shifting to using [uv](https://docs.astral.sh/uv/getting-started/installation/) to manage the &#34;python environment&#34; (a symptom of how python has become less than fun). It works well on the machines and operating systems I use for work. My personal computing platform of choice these days is a Raspberry Pi 500 though. Raspberry Pi OS is based on Debian but when it comes to Python things can get persnickety pretty quick. The best way to install uv I&#39;ve found isn&#39;t via methods suggested at the beginning of the linked install pages. For me I have found installing via Rust&#39;s cargo command the most reliable.

```shell
cargo install --locked uv
```

Once installed you can update it with the following

```shell
uv self update
```

Since I don&#39;t setup a new Pi frequently I tend to forget the simplicity of this approach and waste an hour trying the other suggested ways. This post is just a note to myself so I remember that!</source:markdown>
      <enclosure url="https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2025/12/19/python_setup_pi_os_6.md" length="1494" type="text/markdown" />
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
