<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>R. S. Doiel</title>
        <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>Robert&#39;s ramblings and wonderigs</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>mkrss v0.2.5</generator>
        <item>
            <title>RetroFlag GPi Case Setup</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/12/24/gpi-case-setup.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Setting up a RetroFlag GPi Case&#xA;===============================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-12-24&#xA;&#xA;These are my notes for setting up a RetroFlag GPi case using Recalbox&#xA;distribution for retro gaming.&#xA;&#xA;+ RetroFlag GPi Case Kit (including a Raspberry Pi Zero W and blank SD Card)&#xA;+ A computer to setup the SD Card  and the Raspberry Pi Imager v1.5 ...</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/12/24/gpi-case-setup.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Dates &amp; Clock</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/27/Dates-and-Clock.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Dates and Clock&#xA;===============&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-11-27&#xA;&#xA;The [Oakwood](http://www.edm2.com/index.php/The_Oakwood_Guidelines_for_Oberon-2_Compiler_Developers#The_Oakwood_Guidelines)&#xA;guidelines specified a common set of modules for Oberon-2 for writing&#xA;programs outside of an Oberon System. A missing module from the Oakwood&#xA;guidelines is modules for working with dates and the system clock.&#xA;Fortunately the A2 Oberon System[^1] provides a template for that&#xA;functionality. In this article I am exploring implementing the&#xA;[Dates](Dates.Mod) and [Clock](Clock.Mod) modules for Oberon-7. I&#xA;also plan to go beyond the A2 implementations and provide additional&#xA;functionality such as parsing procedures and the ability to work with&#xA;either the date or time related attributes separately in the&#xA;`Dates.DateTime` record.&#xA;&#xA;[^1]: A2 information can be found in the [Oberon wikibook](https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Oberon#In_A2) ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/27/Dates-and-Clock.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/11/magnacarta.txt</link>
            <description>﻿The Project Gutenberg EBook of The Magna Carta, by Anonymous&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and most&#xD;&#xA;other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions&#xD;&#xA;whatsoever.  You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms of&#xD;&#xA;the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at&#xD;&#xA;www.gutenberg.org.  If you are not located in the United States, you&#39;ll have&#xD;&#xA;to check the laws of the country where you are located before using this ebook.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Title: The Magna Carta&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Author: Anonymous&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Posting Date: April 4, 2015 [EBook #10000]&#xD;&#xA;Release Date: February, 2006&#xD;&#xA;First Posted: October 26, 2003&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Language: English&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*** START OF THIS PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THE MAGNA CARTA ***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Produced by Michael Hart&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;A note from Michael Hart, preparer of the 0.1 version.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This file contains a number of versions of the Magna Carta,&#xD;&#xA;some of which were a little mangled in transit.  I am sure&#xD;&#xA;our volunteers will find and correct errors I didn&#39;t catch,&#xD;&#xA;and that version 0.2 - 1.0 will have significant improvements,&#xD;&#xA;as well as at least one more version in Latin.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Version 1.0 may contain a dozen different versions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Text of Magna Carta&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;JOHN, by the grace of God King of England, Lord of Ireland, Duke of&#xD;&#xA;Normandy and Aquitaine, and Count of Anjou, to his archbishops,&#xD;&#xA;bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, foresters, sheriffs,&#xD;&#xA;stewards, servants, and to all his officials and loyal subjects,&#xD;&#xA;Greeting.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;KNOW THAT BEFORE GOD, for the health of our soul and those of our&#xD;&#xA;ancestors and heirs, to the honour of God, the exaltation of the holy&#xD;&#xA;Church, and the better ordering of our kingdom, at the advice of our&#xD;&#xA;reverend fathers Stephen, archbishop of Canterbury, primate of all&#xD;&#xA;England, and cardinal of the holy Roman Church, Henry archbishop of&#xD;&#xA;Dublin, William bishop of London, Peter bishop of Winchester, Jocelin&#xD;&#xA;bishop of Bath and Glastonbury, Hugh bishop of Lincoln, Walter Bishop&#xD;&#xA;of Worcester, William bishop of Coventry, Benedict bishop of&#xD;&#xA;Rochester, Master Pandulf subdeacon and member of the papal household,&#xD;&#xA;Brother Aymeric master of the knighthood of the Temple in England,&#xD;&#xA;William Marshal earl of Pembroke, William earl of Salisbury, William&#xD;&#xA;earl of Warren, William earl of Arundel, Alan de Galloway constable of&#xD;&#xA;Scotland, Warin Fitz Gerald, Peter Fitz Herbert, Hubert de Burgh&#xD;&#xA;seneschal of Poitou, Hugh de Neville, Matthew Fitz Herbert, Thomas&#xD;&#xA;Basset, Alan Basset, Philip Daubeny, Robert de Roppeley, John Marshal,&#xD;&#xA;John Fitz Hugh, and other loyal subjects:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(1) FIRST, THAT WE HAVE GRANTED TO GOD, and by this present charter&#xD;&#xA;have confirmed for us and our heirs in perpetuity, that the English&#xD;&#xA;Church shall be free, and shall have its rights undiminished, and its&#xD;&#xA;liberties unimpaired. That we wish this so to be observed, appears&#xD;&#xA;from the fact that of our own free will, before the outbreak of the&#xD;&#xA;present dispute between us and our barons, we granted and confirmed by&#xD;&#xA;charter the freedom of the Church&#39;s elections - a right reckoned to be&#xD;&#xA;of the greatest necessity and importance to it - and caused this to be&#xD;&#xA;confirmed by Pope Innocent III. This freedom we shall observe ourselves,&#xD;&#xA;and desire to be observed in good faith by our heirs in perpetuity.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;TO ALL FREE MEN OF OUR KINGDOM we have also granted, for us and our&#xD;&#xA;heirs for ever, all the liberties written out below, to have and to&#xD;&#xA;keep for them and their heirs, of us and our heirs:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(2) If any earl, baron, or other person that holds lands directly of&#xD;&#xA;the Crown, for military service, shall die, and at his death his heir&#xD;&#xA;shall be of full age and owe a `relief&#39;, the heir shall have his&#xD;&#xA;inheritance on payment of the ancient scale of `relief&#39;. That is to&#xD;&#xA;say, the heir or heirs of an earl shall pay 100 for the entire earl&#39;s&#xD;&#xA;barony, the heir or heirs of a knight 100s. at most for the entire&#xD;&#xA;knight&#39;s `fee&#39;, and any man that owes less shall pay less, in&#xD;&#xA;accordance with the ancient usage of `fees&#39;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(3) But if the heir of such a person is under age and a ward, when he&#xD;&#xA;comes of age he shall have his inheritance without `relief&#39; or fine.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(4) The guardian of the land of an heir who is under age shall take&#xD;&#xA;from it only reasonable revenues, customary dues, and feudal services.&#xD;&#xA;He shall do this without destruction or damage to men or property. If&#xD;&#xA;we have given the guardianship of the land to a sheriff, or to any&#xD;&#xA;person answerable to us for the revenues, and he commits destruction&#xD;&#xA;or damage, we will exact compensation from him, and the land shall be&#xD;&#xA;entrusted to two worthy and prudent men of the same `fee&#39;, who shall&#xD;&#xA;be answerable to us for the revenues, or to the person to whom we have&#xD;&#xA;assigned them. If we have given or sold to anyone the guardianship of&#xD;&#xA;such land, and he causes destruction or damage, he shall lose the&#xD;&#xA;guardianship of it, and it shall be handed over to two worthy and&#xD;&#xA;prudent men of the same `fee&#39;, who shall be similarly answerable to&#xD;&#xA;us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(5) For so long as a guardian has guardianship of such land, he shall&#xD;&#xA;maintain the houses, parks, fish preserves, ponds, mills, and&#xD;&#xA;everything else pertaining to it, from the revenues of the land&#xD;&#xA;itself. When the heir comes of age, he shall restore the whole land to&#xD;&#xA;him, stocked with plough teams and such implements of husbandry as the&#xD;&#xA;season demands and the revenues from the land can reasonably bear.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(6) Heirs may be given in marriage, but not to someone of lower social&#xD;&#xA;standing. Before a marriage takes place, it shall be&#39; made known to&#xD;&#xA;the heir&#39;s next-of-kin.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(7) At her husband&#39;s death, a widow may have her marriage portion and&#xD;&#xA;inheritance at once and without trouble. She shall pay nothing for her&#xD;&#xA;dower, marriage portion, or any inheritance that she and her husband&#xD;&#xA;held jointly on the day of his death. She may remain in her husband&#39;s&#xD;&#xA;house for forty days after his death, and within this period her dower&#xD;&#xA;shall be assigned to her.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(8) No widow shall be compelled to marry, so long as she wishes to&#xD;&#xA;remain without a husband. But she must give security that she will not&#xD;&#xA;marry without royal consent, if she holds her lands of the Crown, or&#xD;&#xA;without the consent of whatever other lord she may hold them of.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(9) Neither we nor our officials will seize any land or rent in&#xD;&#xA;payment of a debt, so long as the debtor has movable goods sufficient&#xD;&#xA;to discharge the debt. A debtor&#39;s sureties shall not be distrained&#xD;&#xA;upon so long as the debtor himself can discharge his debt. If, for&#xD;&#xA;lack of means, the debtor is unable to discharge his debt, his&#xD;&#xA;sureties shall be answerable for it. If they so desire, they may have&#xD;&#xA;the debtor&#39;s lands and rents until they have received satisfaction for&#xD;&#xA;the debt that they paid for him, unless the debtor can show that he&#xD;&#xA;has settled his obligations to them.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(10) If anyone who has borrowed a sum of money from Jews dies before&#xD;&#xA;the debt has been repaid, his heir shall pay no interest on the debt&#xD;&#xA;for so long as he remains under age, irrespective of whom he holds his&#xD;&#xA;lands. If such a debt falls into the hands of the Crown, it will take&#xD;&#xA;nothing except the principal sum specified in the bond.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(11) If a man dies owing money to Jews, his wife may have her dower&#xD;&#xA;and pay nothing towards the debt from it. If he leaves children that&#xD;&#xA;are under age, their needs may also be provided for on a scale&#xD;&#xA;appropriate to the size of his holding of lands. The debt is to be&#xD;&#xA;paid out of the residue, reserving the service due to his feudal lords.&#xD;&#xA;Debts owed to persons other than Jews are to be dealt with similarly.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(12) No `scutage&#39; or `aid&#39; may be levied in our kingdom without its&#xD;&#xA;general consent, unless it is for the ransom of our person, to make&#xD;&#xA;our eldest son a knight, and (once) to marry our eldest daughter. For&#xD;&#xA;these purposes only a reasonable `aid&#39; may be levied. `Aids&#39; from the&#xD;&#xA;city of London are to be treated similarly.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(13) The city of London shall enjoy all its ancient liberties and&#xD;&#xA;free customs, both by land and by water. We also will and grant that&#xD;&#xA;all other cities, boroughs, towns, and ports shall enjoy all their&#xD;&#xA;liberties and free customs.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA; (14) To obtain the general consent of the realm for the assessment&#xD;&#xA;of an `aid&#39; - except in the three cases specified above - or a&#xD;&#xA;`scutage&#39;, we will cause the archbishops, bishops, abbots, earls, and&#xD;&#xA;greater barons to be summoned individually by letter. To those who&#xD;&#xA;hold lands directly of us we will cause a general summons to be&#xD;&#xA;issued, through the sheriffs and other officials, to come together on&#xD;&#xA;a fixed day (of which at least forty days notice shall be given) and&#xD;&#xA;at a fixed place. In all letters of summons, the cause of the summons&#xD;&#xA;will be stated. When a summons has been issued, the business appointed&#xD;&#xA;for the day shall go forward in accordance with the resolution of&#xD;&#xA;those present, even if not all those who were summoned have appeared.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(15) In future we will allow no one to levy an `aid&#39; from his free&#xD;&#xA;men, except to ransom his person, to make his eldest son a knight, and&#xD;&#xA;(once) to marry his eldest daughter. For these purposes only a&#xD;&#xA;reasonable `aid&#39; may be levied.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(16) No man shall be forced to perform more service for a knight&#39;s&#xD;&#xA;`fee&#39;, or other free holding of land, than is due from it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(17) Ordinary lawsuits shall not follow the royal court around, but&#xD;&#xA;shall be held in a fixed place.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(18) Inquests of novel disseisin, mort d&#39;ancestor, and darrein&#xD;&#xA;presentment shall be taken only in their proper county court. We&#xD;&#xA;ourselves, or in our absence abroad our chief justice, will send two&#xD;&#xA;justices to each county four times a year, and these justices, with&#xD;&#xA;four knights of the county elected by the county itself, shall hold&#xD;&#xA;the assizes in the county court, on the day and in the place where the&#xD;&#xA;court meets.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(19) If any assizes cannot be taken on the day of the county court, as&#xD;&#xA;many knights and freeholders shall afterwards remain behind, of those&#xD;&#xA;who have attended the court, as will suffice for the administration of&#xD;&#xA;justice, having regard to the volume of business to be done.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(20) For a trivial offence, a free man shall be fined only in&#xD;&#xA;proportion to the degree of his offence, and for a serious offence&#xD;&#xA;correspondingly, but not so heavily as to deprive him of his&#xD;&#xA;livelihood. In the same way, a merchant shall be spared his&#xD;&#xA;merchandise, and a husbandman the implements of his husbandry, if they&#xD;&#xA;fall upon the mercy of a royal court. None of these fines shall be&#xD;&#xA;imposed except by the assessment on oath of reputable men of the&#xD;&#xA;neighbourhood.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(21) Earls and barons shall be fined only by their equals, and in&#xD;&#xA;proportion to the gravity of their offence.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(22) A fine imposed upon the lay property of a clerk in holy orders&#xD;&#xA;shall be assessed upon the same principles, without reference to the&#xD;&#xA;value of his ecclesiastical benefice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(23) No town or person shall be forced to build bridges over rivers&#xD;&#xA;except those with an ancient obligation to do so.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(24) No sheriff, constable, coroners, or other royal officials are to&#xD;&#xA;hold lawsuits that should be held by the royal justices.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(25) Every county, hundred, wapentake, and tithing shall remain at&#xD;&#xA;its ancient rent, without increase, except the royal demesne manors.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(26) If at the death of a man who holds a lay `fee&#39; of the Crown, a&#xD;&#xA;sheriff or royal official produces royal letters patent of summons for&#xD;&#xA;a debt due to the Crown, it shall be lawful for them to seize and list&#xD;&#xA;movable goods found in the lay `fee&#39; of the dead man to the value of&#xD;&#xA;the debt, as assessed by worthy men. Nothing shall be removed until&#xD;&#xA;the whole debt is paid, when the residue shall be given over to the&#xD;&#xA;executors to carry out the dead man&#39;s will. If no debt is due to the&#xD;&#xA;Crown, all the movable goods shall be regarded as the property of the&#xD;&#xA;dead man, except the reasonable shares of his wife and children.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(27) If a free man dies intestate, his movable goods are to be&#xD;&#xA;distributed by his next-of-kin and friends, under the supervision of&#xD;&#xA;the Church. The rights of his debtors are to be preserved.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(28) No constable or other royal official shall take corn or other&#xD;&#xA;movable goods from any man without immediate payment, unless the&#xD;&#xA;seller voluntarily offers postponement of this.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(29) No constable may compel a knight to pay money for castle-guard if&#xD;&#xA;the knight is willing to undertake the guard in person, or with&#xD;&#xA;reasonable excuse to supply some other fit man to do it. A knight&#xD;&#xA;taken or sent on military service shall be excused from castle-guard&#xD;&#xA;for the period of this service.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(30) No sheriff, royal official, or other person shall take horses or&#xD;&#xA;carts for transport from any free man, without his consent.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(31) Neither we nor any royal official will take wood for our castle,&#xD;&#xA;or for any other purpose, without the consent of the owner.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(32) We will not keep the lands of people convicted of felony in our&#xD;&#xA;hand for longer than a year and a day, after which they shall be&#xD;&#xA;returned to the lords of the `fees&#39; concerned.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(33) All fish-weirs shall be removed from the Thames, the Medway, and&#xD;&#xA;throughout the whole of England, except on the sea coast.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(34) The writ called precipe shall not in future be issued to anyone&#xD;&#xA;in respect of any holding of land, if a free man could thereby be&#xD;&#xA;deprived of the right of trial in his own lord&#39;s court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(35) There shall be standard measures of wine, ale, and corn (the&#xD;&#xA;London quarter), throughout the kingdom. There shall also be a&#xD;&#xA;standard width of dyed cloth, russett, and haberject, namely two ells&#xD;&#xA;within the selvedges. Weights are to be standardised similarly.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(36) In future nothing shall be paid or accepted for the issue of a&#xD;&#xA;writ of inquisition of life or limbs. It shall be given gratis, and&#xD;&#xA;not refused.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(37) If a man holds land of the Crown by `fee-farm&#39;, `socage&#39;, or&#xD;&#xA;`burgage&#39;, and also holds land of someone else for knight&#39;s service,&#xD;&#xA;we will not have guardianship of his heir, nor of the land that&#xD;&#xA;belongs to the other person&#39;s `fee&#39;, by virtue of the `fee-farm&#39;,&#xD;&#xA;`socage&#39;, or `burgage&#39;, unless the `fee-farm&#39; owes knight&#39;s service.&#xD;&#xA;We will not have the guardianship of a man&#39;s heir, or of land that he&#xD;&#xA;holds of someone else, by reason of any small property that he may&#xD;&#xA;hold of the Crown for a service of knives, arrows, or the like.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(38) In future no official shall place a man on trial upon his own&#xD;&#xA;unsupported statement, without producing credible witnesses to the&#xD;&#xA;truth of it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(39) No free man shall be seized or imprisoned, or stripped of his&#xD;&#xA;rights or possessions, or outlawed or exiled, or deprived of his&#xD;&#xA;standing in any other way, nor will we proceed with force against him,&#xD;&#xA;or send others to do so, except by the lawful judgement of his equals&#xD;&#xA;or by the law of the land.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(40) To no one will we sell, to no one deny or delay right or justice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(41) All merchants may enter or leave England unharmed and without&#xD;&#xA;fear, and may stay or travel within it, by land or water, for purposes&#xD;&#xA;of trade, free from all illegal exactions, in accordance with ancient&#xD;&#xA;and lawful customs. This, however, does not apply in time of war to&#xD;&#xA;merchants from a country that is at war with us. Any such merchants&#xD;&#xA;found in our country at the outbreak of war shall be detained without&#xD;&#xA;injury to their persons or property, until we or our chief justice&#xD;&#xA;have discovered how our own merchants are being treated in the country&#xD;&#xA;at war with us. If our own merchants are safe they shall be safe too.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(42) In future it shall be lawful for any man to leave and return to&#xD;&#xA;our kingdom unharmed and without fear, by land or water, preserving&#xD;&#xA;his allegiance to us, except in time of war, for some short period,&#xD;&#xA;for the common benefit of the realm. People that have been imprisoned&#xD;&#xA;or outlawed in accordance with the law of the land, people from a&#xD;&#xA;country that is at war with us, and merchants - who shall be dealt&#xD;&#xA;with as stated above - are excepted from this provision.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(43) If a man holds lands of any `escheat&#39; such as the `honour&#39; of&#xD;&#xA;Wallingford, Nottingham, Boulogne, Lancaster, or of other `escheats&#39;&#xD;&#xA;in our hand that are baronies, at his death his heir shall give us&#xD;&#xA;only the `relief&#39; and service that he would have made to the baron,&#xD;&#xA;had the barony been in the baron&#39;s hand. We will hold the `escheat&#39; in&#xD;&#xA;the same manner as the baron held it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(44) People who live outside the forest need not in future appear&#xD;&#xA;before the royal justices of the forest in answer to general&#xD;&#xA;summonses, unless they are actually involved in proceedings or are&#xD;&#xA;sureties for someone who has been seized for a forest offence.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(45) We will appoint as justices, constables, sheriffs, or other&#xD;&#xA;officials, only men that know the law of the realm and are minded to&#xD;&#xA;keep it well.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(46) All barons who have founded abbeys, and have charters of English&#xD;&#xA;kings or ancient tenure as evidence of this, may have guardianship of&#xD;&#xA;them when there is no abbot, as is their due.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(47) All forests that have been created in our reign shall at once be&#xD;&#xA;disafforested. River-banks that have been enclosed in our reign shall&#xD;&#xA;be treated similarly.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(48) All evil customs relating to forests and warrens, foresters,&#xD;&#xA;warreners, sheriffs and their servants, or river-banks and their&#xD;&#xA;wardens, are at once to be investigated in every county by twelve&#xD;&#xA;sworn knights of the county, and within forty days of their enquiry&#xD;&#xA;the evil customs are to be abolished completely and irrevocably. But&#xD;&#xA;we, or our chief justice if we are not in England, are first to be&#xD;&#xA;informed.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(49) We will at once return all hostages and charters delivered up&#xD;&#xA;to us by Englishmen as security for peace or for loyal service.&#xD;&#xA;***here were some strange characters, not completely removed&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(50) We will remove completely from their offices the kinsmen of&#xD;&#xA;Gerard de Ath, Peter, Guy, and Andrew de Chanceaux, Guy de Cigogne, and in&#xD;&#xA;future they shall hold no offices in England. The&#xD;&#xA;people in question are Engelard de Cigogn, Geoffrey de Martigny and his&#xD;&#xA;brothers, Philip Marc and his brothers, with Geoffrey his nephew,&#xD;&#xA;and all their followers.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* As soon as peace is restored, we will remove from the kingdom all&#xD;&#xA;the foreign knights, bowmen, their attendants, and the mercenaries&#xD;&#xA;that have come to it, to its harm, with horses and arms.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* To any man whom we have deprived or dispossessed of lands,&#xD;&#xA;castles, liberties, or rights, without the lawful judgement of his&#xD;&#xA;equals, we will at once restore these. In cases of dispute the&#xD;&#xA;matter shall be resolved by the judgement of the twenty-five&#xD;&#xA;barons referred to below in the clause for securing the peace. In&#xD;&#xA;cases, however, where a man was deprived or dispossessed of&#xD;&#xA;something without the lawful judgement of his equals by our father&#xD;&#xA;King Henry or our brother King Richard, and it remains in our&#xD;&#xA;hands or is held by others under our warranty, we shall have&#xD;&#xA;respite for the period commonly allowed to Crusaders, unless a&#xD;&#xA;lawsuit had been begun, or an enquiry had been made at our order,&#xD;&#xA;before we took the Cross as a Crusader. On our return from the&#xD;&#xA;Crusade, or if we abandon it, we will at once render justice in&#xD;&#xA;full.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* We shall have similar respite in rendering justice in connexion&#xD;&#xA;with forests that are to be disafforested, or to remain forests,&#xD;&#xA;when these were first aforested by our father Henry or our brother&#xD;&#xA;Richard; with the guardianship of lands in another persons fee,&#xD;&#xA;when we have hitherto had this by virtue of a fee held of us for&#xD;&#xA;knights service by a third party; and with abbeys founded in&#xD;&#xA;another persons fee, in which the lord of the fee claims to own a&#xD;&#xA;right. On our return from the Crusade, or if we abandon it, we&#xD;&#xA;will at once do full justice to complaints about these matters.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* No one shall be arrested or imprisoned on the appeal of a woman&#xD;&#xA;for the death of any person except her husband.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* All fines that have been given to us unjustly and against the law&#xD;&#xA;of the land, and all fines that we have exacted unjustly, shall be&#xD;&#xA;entirely remitted or the matter decided by a majority judgement of&#xD;&#xA;the twenty-five barons referred to below in the clause for&#xD;&#xA;securing the peace together with Stephen, archbishop of&#xD;&#xA;Canterbury, if he can be present, and such others as he wishes to&#xD;&#xA;bring with him. If the archbishop cannot be present, proceedings&#xD;&#xA;shall continue without him, provided that if any of the&#xD;&#xA;twenty-five barons has been involved in a similar suit himself,&#xD;&#xA;his judgement shall be set aside, and someone else chosen and&#xD;&#xA;sworn in his place, as a substitute for the single occasion, by&#xD;&#xA;the rest of the twenty-five.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* If we have deprived or dispossessed any Welshmen of lands,&#xD;&#xA;liberties, or anything else in England or in Wales, without the&#xD;&#xA;lawful judgement of their equals, these are at once to be returned&#xD;&#xA;to them. A dispute on this point shall be determined in the&#xD;&#xA;Marches by the judgement of equals. English law shall apply to&#xD;&#xA;holdings of land in England, Welsh law to those in Wales, and the&#xD;&#xA;law of the Marches to those in the Marches. The Welsh shall treat&#xD;&#xA;us and ours in the same way.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* In cases where a Welshman was deprived or dispossessed of&#xD;&#xA;anything, without the lawful judgement of his equals, by our&#xD;&#xA;father King Henry or our brother King Richard, and it remains in&#xD;&#xA;our hands or is held by others under our warranty, we shall have&#xD;&#xA;respite for the period commonly allowed to Crusaders, unless a&#xD;&#xA;lawsuit had been begun, or an enquiry had been made at our order,&#xD;&#xA;before we took the Cross as a Crusader. But on our return from the&#xD;&#xA;Crusade, or if we abandon it, we will at once do full justice&#xD;&#xA;according to the laws of Wales and the said regions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* We will at once return the son of Llywelyn, all Welsh hostages,&#xD;&#xA;and the charters delivered to us as security for the peace.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* With regard to the return of the sisters and hostages of&#xD;&#xA;Alexander, king of Scotland, his liberties and his rights, we will&#xD;&#xA;treat him in the same way as our other barons of England, unless&#xD;&#xA;it appears from the charters that we hold from his father William,&#xD;&#xA;formerly king of Scotland, that he should be treated otherwise.&#xD;&#xA;This matter shall be resolved by the judgement of his equals in&#xD;&#xA;our court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* All these customs and liberties that we have granted shall be&#xD;&#xA;observed in our kingdom in so far as concerns our own relations&#xD;&#xA;with our subjects. Let all men of our kingdom, whether clergy or&#xD;&#xA;laymen, observe them similarly in their relations with their own&#xD;&#xA;men.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***Strange characters may have ended here.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;SINCE WE HAVE GRANTED ALL THESE THINGS for God, for the better&#xD;&#xA;ordering of our kingdom, and to allay the discord that has arisen&#xD;&#xA;between us and our barons, and since we desire that they shall be&#xD;&#xA;enjoyed in their entirety, with lasting strength, for ever, we give&#xD;&#xA;and grant to the barons the following security:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* The barons shall elect twenty-five of their number to keep, and&#xD;&#xA;cause to be observed with all their might, the peace and liberties&#xD;&#xA;granted and confirmed to them by this charter.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* If we, our chief justice, our officials, or any of our servants&#xD;&#xA;offend in any respect against any man, or transgress any of the&#xD;&#xA;articles of the peace or of this security, and the offence is made&#xD;&#xA;known to four of the said twenty-five barons, they shall come to&#xD;&#xA;us - or in our absence from the kingdom to the chief justice - to&#xD;&#xA;declare it and claim immediate redress. If we, or in our absence&#xD;&#xA;abroad the chief justice, make no redress within forty days,&#xD;&#xA;reckoning from the day on which the offence was declared to us or&#xD;&#xA;to him, the four barons shall refer the matter to the rest of the&#xD;&#xA;twenty-five barons, who may distrain upon and assail us in every&#xD;&#xA;way possible, with the support of the whole community of the land,&#xD;&#xA;by seizing our castles, lands, possessions, or anything else&#xD;&#xA;saving only our own person and those of the queen and our&#xD;&#xA;children, until they have secured such redress as they have&#xD;&#xA;determined upon. Having secured the redress, they may then resume&#xD;&#xA;their normal obedience to us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* Any man who so desires may take an oath to obey the commands of&#xD;&#xA;the twenty-five barons for the achievement of these ends, and to&#xD;&#xA;join with them in assailing us to the utmost of his power. We give&#xD;&#xA;public and free permission to take this oath to any man who so&#xD;&#xA;desires, and at no time will we prohibit any man from taking it.&#xD;&#xA;Indeed, we will compel any of our subjects who are unwilling to&#xD;&#xA;take it to swear it at our command.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* If one of the twenty-five barons dies or leaves the country, or is&#xD;&#xA;prevented in any other way from discharging his duties, the rest&#xD;&#xA;of them shall choose another baron in his place, at their&#xD;&#xA;discretion, who shall be duly sworn in as they were.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* In the event of disagreement among the twenty-five barons on any&#xD;&#xA;matter referred to them for decision, the verdict of the majority&#xD;&#xA;present shall have the same validity as a unanimous verdict of the&#xD;&#xA;whole twenty-five, whether these were all present or some of those&#xD;&#xA;summoned were unwilling or unable to appear.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* The twenty-five barons shall swear to obey all the above articles&#xD;&#xA;faithfully, and shall cause them to be obeyed by others to the&#xD;&#xA;best of their power.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* We will not seek to procure from anyone, either by our own efforts&#xD;&#xA;or those of a third party, anything by which any part of these&#xD;&#xA;concessions or liberties might be revoked or diminished. Should&#xD;&#xA;such a thing be procured, it shall be null and void and we will at&#xD;&#xA;no time make use of it, either ourselves or through a third party.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We have remitted and pardoned fully to all men any ill-will, hurt, or&#xD;&#xA;grudges that have arisen between us and our subjects, whether clergy&#xD;&#xA;or laymen, since the beginning of the dispute.&#xD;&#xA;We have in addition remitted fully, and for our own part have also&#xD;&#xA;pardoned, to all clergy and laymen any offences committed as a result&#xD;&#xA;of the said dispute between Easter 1215 AD and the restoration of&#xD;&#xA;peace.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In addition we have caused letters patent to be made for the barons,&#xD;&#xA;bearing witness to this security and to the concessions set out above,&#xD;&#xA;over the seals of Stephen archbishop of Canterbury, Henry archbishop&#xD;&#xA;of Dublin, the other bishops named above, and Master Pandulf.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;IT IS ACCORDINGLY OUR WISH AND COMMAND that the English Church shall&#xD;&#xA;be free, and that men in our kingdom shall have and keep all these&#xD;&#xA;liberties, rights, and concessions, well and peaceably in their&#xD;&#xA;fulness and entirety for them and their heirs, of us and our heirs, in&#xD;&#xA;all things and all places for ever.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Both we and the barons have sworn that all this shall be observed in&#xD;&#xA;good faith and without deceit. Witness the above mentioned people and&#xD;&#xA;many others.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Given by our hand in the meadow that is called Runnymede, between&#xD;&#xA;Windsor and Staines, on the fifteenth day of June in the seventeenth&#xD;&#xA;year of our reign.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;[There were many missing spaces in this one, not sure I got them all]&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Magna Carta 1215&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;John, by the grace of God, king of England, lord of Ireland, duke of&#xD;&#xA;Normandy and Aquitaine, and count of Anjou, to the archbishops,&#xD;&#xA;bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justiciars, foresters, sheriffs,&#xD;&#xA;stewards, servants, and to all his bailiffs and liege subjects,&#xD;&#xA;greeting. Know that, having regard to God and for the salvation of our&#xD;&#xA;soul, and those of all our ancestors and heirs, and unto the honor of&#xD;&#xA;God and the advancement of holy church, and for the reform of&#xD;&#xA;our realm, by advice of our venerable fathers, Stephen archbishop of&#xD;&#xA;Canterbury, primate of all England and cardinal of the holy Roman&#xD;&#xA;Church, Henry archbishop of Dublin, William of London, Peter of&#xD;&#xA;Winchester, Jocelyn of Bath and Glastonbury, Hugh of Lincoln, Walter of&#xD;&#xA;Worcester, William of Coventry, Benedict of Rochester, bishops; of&#xD;&#xA;master Pandulf, subdeacon and member of the household of our lord the&#xD;&#xA;Pope, of brother Aymeric (master of the Knights of the Temple in&#xD;&#xA;England), and of the illustrious men William Marshall earl of Pembroke,&#xD;&#xA;William earl of Salisbury, William earl of Warenne, William earl&#xD;&#xA;of Arundel, Alan of Galloway (constable of Scotland), Waren Fitz&#xD;&#xA;Gerald, Peter Fits Herbert, Hubert de Burgh (seneschal of Poitou), Hugh&#xD;&#xA;de Neville, Matthew Fitz Herbert, Thomas Basset, Alan Basset, Philip&#xD;&#xA;d&#39;Aubigny, Robert of Roppesley, John Marshall, John Fitz Hugh, and&#xD;&#xA;others, our liegemen.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1. In the first place we have granted to God, and by this our present&#xD;&#xA;charter confirmed for us and our heirs for ever that the English church&#xD;&#xA;shall be free, and shall have her rights entire, and her liberties&#xD;&#xA;inviolate; and we will that it be thus observed; which is apparent from&#xD;&#xA;this that the freedom of elections, which is reckoned most important&#xD;&#xA;and very essential to the English church, we, of our pure and&#xD;&#xA;unconstrained will, did grant, and did by our charter confirm and did&#xD;&#xA;obtain the ratification of the same from our lord, Pope Innocent&#xD;&#xA;III., before the quarrel arose between us and our barons: and this we&#xD;&#xA;will observe, and our will is that it be observed in good faith by our&#xD;&#xA;heirs for ever. We have also granted to all freemen of our kingdom, for&#xD;&#xA;us and our heirs for ever, all the underwritten liberties, to be had&#xD;&#xA;and held by them and their heirs, of us and our heirs for ever.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;2. If any of our earls or barons, or others holding of us in chief by&#xD;&#xA;military service shall have died, and at the time of his death his heir&#xD;&#xA;shall be of full age and owe &#34;relief&#34; he shall have his inheritance on&#xD;&#xA;payment of the ancient relief, namely the heir or heirs of an earl, 100&#xD;&#xA;pounds for a whole earl&#39;s barony; the heir or heirs of a baron, 100&#xD;&#xA;pounds for a whole barony; the heir or heirs of a knight, 100 shillings&#xD;&#xA;at most for a whole knight&#39;s fee; and whoever owes less let him give&#xD;&#xA;less, according to the ancient custom officers.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;3. If, however, the heir of any of the aforesaid has been under age&#xD;&#xA;and in wardship, let him have his inheritance without relief and&#xD;&#xA;without fine when he comes of age.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;4. The guardian of the land of an heir who is thus under age, shall&#xD;&#xA;take from the land of the heir nothing but reasonably produce,&#xD;&#xA;reasonable customs, and reasonable services, and that without&#xD;&#xA;destruction or waste of men or goods; and if we have committed the&#xD;&#xA;wardship of the lands of any such minor to the sheriff, or to any other&#xD;&#xA;who is responsible to us for its issues, and he has made destruction or&#xD;&#xA;waste of what he holds in wardship, we will take of him amends, and the&#xD;&#xA;land shall be committed to two lawful and discreet men of that fee, who&#xD;&#xA;shall be responsible for the issues to us or to him to whom we&#xD;&#xA;shall assign them; and if we have given or sold the wardship of any&#xD;&#xA;such land to anyone and he has there in made destruction or waste, he&#xD;&#xA;shall lose that wardship, and it shall be transferred to two lawful and&#xD;&#xA;discreet men of that fief, who shall be responsible to us in like&#xD;&#xA;manner as aforesaid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;5. The guardian, moreover, so long as he has the wardship of the land,&#xD;&#xA;shall keep up the houses, parks, fishponds, stanks, mills, and other&#xD;&#xA;things pertaining to the land, out of the issues of the same land; and&#xD;&#xA;he shall restore to the heir, when he has come to full age, all his&#xD;&#xA;land, stocked with ploughs and &#34;waynage,&#34; according as the season of&#xD;&#xA;husbandry shall require, and the issues of the land can reasonably bear.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;6. Heirs shall be married without disparagement, yet so that before the&#xD;&#xA;marriage takes place the nearest in blood to that heir shall have notice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;7. A widow, after the death of her husband, shall forthwith and&#xD;&#xA;without difficulty have her marriage portion and inheritance; nor shall&#xD;&#xA;she give anything for her dower, or for her marriage portion, or for&#xD;&#xA;the inheritance which her husband and she held on the day of the death&#xD;&#xA;of that husband; and she may remain in the house of her husband for&#xD;&#xA;fourty days after his death, within which time her dower shall be&#xD;&#xA;assigned to her.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;8. No widow shall be compelled to marry, so long as she prefers to&#xD;&#xA;live without a husband; provided always that she gives security not to&#xD;&#xA;marry without our consent, if she holds of us, or without the consent&#xD;&#xA;of the lord of whom she holds, if she holds of another.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;9. Neither we nor our bailiffs shall seize any land or rent for any&#xD;&#xA;debt, so long as the chattels of the debtor are sufficient to repay the&#xD;&#xA;debt; nor shall the sureties of the debtor be distrained so long as the&#xD;&#xA;principal debtor is able to satisfy the debt; and if the principal&#xD;&#xA;debtor shall fail to pay the debt, having nothing wherewith to pay it,&#xD;&#xA;then the sureties shall answer for the debt; and let them have the&#xD;&#xA;lands and rents of the debtor, if they desire them, until they are&#xD;&#xA;indemnified for the debt which they have paid for him, unless the&#xD;&#xA;principal debtor can show proof that he is discharged thereof as&#xD;&#xA;against the said sureties.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;10. If one who has borrowed from the Jews any sum, great or small, die&#xD;&#xA;before that loan can be repaid, the debt shall not bear interest while&#xD;&#xA;the heir is under age, of whomsoever he may hold; and if the debt fall&#xD;&#xA;into our hands, we will not take anything except the principal sum&#xD;&#xA;contained in the bond.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;11. And if any one die indebted to the Jews, his wife shall have her&#xD;&#xA;dower and pay nothing of that debt; and if any children of the deceased&#xD;&#xA;are left underage, necessaries shall be provided for them in keeping&#xD;&#xA;with the holding of the deceased; and out of the residue the debt shall&#xD;&#xA;be paid, reserving, however, service due to feudal lords; in like&#xD;&#xA;manner let it be done touching debts due to others than Jews.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;12. No scutage nor aid shall be imposed on our kingdom, unless by&#xD;&#xA;common counsel of our kingdom, except for ransoming our person, for&#xD;&#xA;making our eldest son a knight, and for once marrying our eldest&#xD;&#xA;daughter; and for these there shall not be levied more than a&#xD;&#xA;reasonable aid. In like manner it shall be done concerning aids from&#xD;&#xA;the city of London.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;13. And the city of London shall have all its ancient liberties and&#xD;&#xA;free customs, as well by land as by water; furthermore, we decree and&#xD;&#xA;grant that all other cities, boroughs, towns, and ports shall have all&#xD;&#xA;their liberties and free customs.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;14. And for obtaining the common counsel of the kingdom anent the&#xD;&#xA;assessing of an aid (except in the three cases aforesaid) or of a&#xD;&#xA;scutage, we will cause to be summoned the archbishops, bishops, abbots,&#xD;&#xA;earls, and greater barons, severally by our letters; and we will&#xD;&#xA;moreover cause to be summoned generally, through our sheriffs and&#xD;&#xA;bailiffs, all others who hold of us in chief, for a fixed date, namely,&#xD;&#xA;after the expiry of at least forty days, and at a fixed place; and in&#xD;&#xA;all letters of such summons we will specify the reason of the summons.&#xD;&#xA;And when the summons has thus been made, the business shall proceed on&#xD;&#xA;the day appointed, according to the counsel of such as are present,&#xD;&#xA;although not all who were summoned have come.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;15. We will not for the future grant to any one license to take an aid&#xD;&#xA;from his own free tenants, except to ransom his body, to make his&#xD;&#xA;eldest son a knight, and once to marry his eldest daughter; and on&#xD;&#xA;each of these occasions there shall be levied only a reasonable aid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;16. No one shall be distrained for performance of greater service for&#xD;&#xA;a knight&#39;s fee, or for any other free tenement, than is due therefrom.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;17. Common pleas shall not follow our court, but shall be held in some&#xD;&#xA;fixed place.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;18. Inquests of novel disseisin, of mort d&#39;ancester, and of darrein&#xD;&#xA;presentment, shall not be held elsewhere than in their own county&#xD;&#xA;courts and that in manner following,--We, or, if we should be out of&#xD;&#xA;the realm, our chief justiciar, will send two justiciars through&#xD;&#xA;every county four times a year, who shall, along with four knights of&#xD;&#xA;the county chosen by the county, hold the said assize in the county&#xD;&#xA;court, on the day and in the place of meeting of that court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;19. And if any of the said assizes cannot be taken on the day of the&#xD;&#xA;county court, let there remain of the knights and freeholders, who were&#xD;&#xA;present at the county court on that day, as many as may be required for&#xD;&#xA;the efficient making of judgments, according as the business be more or&#xD;&#xA;less.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;20. A freeman shall not be amerced for a slight offense, except in&#xD;&#xA;accordance with the degree of the offense; and for a grave offense he&#xD;&#xA;shall be amerced in accordance with the gravity of the offense, yet&#xD;&#xA;saving always his &#34;contentment;&#34; and a merchant in the same way, saving&#xD;&#xA;his &#34;merchandise;&#34; and a villein shall be amerced in the same way,&#xD;&#xA;saving his &#34;wainage&#34;--if they have fallen into our mercy: and none of&#xD;&#xA;the aforesaid amercements shall be impsed except by the oath of honest&#xD;&#xA;men of the neighborhood.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;21. Earls and barons shall not be amerced except through their peers,&#xD;&#xA;and only in accordance with the degree of the offense.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;22. A clerk shall not be amerced in respect of his lay holding except&#xD;&#xA;after the manner of the others aforesaid; further, he shall not be&#xD;&#xA;amerced in accordance with the extent of his ecclesiastical benefice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;23. No village or individual shall be compelled to make bridges at&#xD;&#xA;river-banks, except those who from of old were legally bound to do so.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;24. No sheriff, constable, coroners, or others of our bailiffs, shall&#xD;&#xA;hold pleas of our Crown.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;25. All counties, hundreds, wapentakes, and trithings (except our&#xD;&#xA;demesne manors) shall remain at old rents, and without any additional&#xD;&#xA;payment.***here may be an error&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;26. If any one holding of us a lay fief shall die, and our sheriff or&#xD;&#xA;bailiff shall exhibit our letters patent of summons for a debt which&#xD;&#xA;the deceased owed to us, it shall be lawful for our sheriff or bailiff&#xD;&#xA;to attach and catalogue chattels of the deceased, found upon the lay&#xD;&#xA;fief, to the value of that debt, at the sight of law-worthy men,&#xD;&#xA;provided always that nothing whatever be then be removed until the debt&#xD;&#xA;which is evident shall be fully paid to us; and the residue shall be&#xD;&#xA;left to the executors to fulfil the will of the deceased; and if there&#xD;&#xA;be nothing due from him to us, all the chattels shall go to&#xD;&#xA;the deceased, saving to his wife and children their reasonable shares.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;27. If any freeman shall die intestate, his chattels shall be&#xD;&#xA;distributed by the hands of his nearest kinsfolk and friends, under&#xD;&#xA;supervision of the church, saving to every one the debts which the&#xD;&#xA;deceased owed to him.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;28. No constable or other bailiff of ours shall take corn or other&#xD;&#xA;provisions from any one without immediately tendering money therefor,&#xD;&#xA;unless he can have postponement thereof by permission of the seller.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;29. No constable shall compel any knight to give money in lieu&#xD;&#xA;of castle-guard, when he is willing to perform it in his own person, or&#xD;&#xA;(if he cannot do it from any reasonable cause) then by another&#xD;&#xA;responsible man. Further, if we have led or sent him upon military&#xD;&#xA;service, he shall be relieved from guard in proportion to the time&#xD;&#xA;during which he has been on service because of us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;30. No sheriff or bailiff of ours, or other person, shall take the&#xD;&#xA;horses or carts of any freeman for transport duty, against the will of&#xD;&#xA;the said freeman.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;31. Neither we nor our bailiffs shall take, for our castles or for any&#xD;&#xA;other work of ours, wood which is not ours, against the will of the&#xD;&#xA;owner of that wood.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;32. We will not retain beyond one year and one day, the lands of those&#xD;&#xA;who have been convicted of felony, and the lands shall thereafter be&#xD;&#xA;handed over to the lords of the fiefs.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;33. All kiddles for the future shall be removed altogether from Thames&#xD;&#xA;and Medway, and throughout all England, except upon the seashore.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;34. The writ which is called praecipe shall not for the future&#xD;&#xA;be issued to any one, regarding any tenement whereby a freeman may lose&#xD;&#xA;his court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;35. Let there be one measure of wine throughout our whole realm; and&#xD;&#xA;one measure of ale; and one measure of corn, to wit, &#34;the London&#xD;&#xA;quarter;&#34; and one width of cloth (whether dyed, or russet, or&#xD;&#xA;&#34;halberget&#34;), to wit, two ells within the selvages; of weights also let&#xD;&#xA;it be as of measures.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;36. Nothing in future shall be given or taken for a writ of inquisition&#xD;&#xA;of life or limbs, but freely it shall be granted, and never denied.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;37. If any one holds of us by fee-farm, by socage, or by burgage,&#xD;&#xA;and holds also land of another lord by knight&#39;s service, we will&#xD;&#xA;not (by reason of that fee-farm, socage, or burgage) have the wardship&#xD;&#xA;of the heir, or of such land of his as is of the fief of that other;&#xD;&#xA;nor shall we have wardship of that fee-farm, socage, or burgage,&#xD;&#xA;unless such fee-farm owes knight&#39;s service. We will not by reason of&#xD;&#xA;any small serjeanty which any one may hold of us by the service of&#xD;&#xA;rendering to us knives, arrows, or the like, have wardship of his heir&#xD;&#xA;of the land which he holds of another lord by knight&#39;s service.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;38. No bailiff for the future shall, upon his own unsupported&#xD;&#xA;complaint, put any one to his &#34;law,&#34; without credible witnesses brought&#xD;&#xA;for this purpose.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;39. No freeman shall be taken or imprisoned or disseised or exiled or&#xD;&#xA;in anyway destroyed, nor will we go upon him nor send upon him, except&#xD;&#xA;by the lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of the land.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;40. To no one will we sell, to no one will we refuse or delay, right&#xD;&#xA;or justice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;41. All merchants shall have safe and secure exit from England, and&#xD;&#xA;entry to England, with the right to tarry there and to move about as&#xD;&#xA;well by land as by water, for buying and selling by the ancient and&#xD;&#xA;right customs, quit from all evil tolls, except (in time of war) such&#xD;&#xA;merchants as are of the land at war with us. And if such are found in&#xD;&#xA;our land at the beginning of the war, they shall be detained, without&#xD;&#xA;injury to their bodies or goods, until information be received by us,&#xD;&#xA;or by our chief justiciar, how the merchants of our land found in the&#xD;&#xA;land at war with us are treated; and if our men are safe there, the&#xD;&#xA;others shall be safe in our land.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;42. It shall be lawful in future for any one (excepting always&#xD;&#xA;those imprisoned or outlawed in accordance with the law of the kingdom,&#xD;&#xA;and natives of any country at war with us, and merchants, who shall be&#xD;&#xA;treated as is above provided) to leave our kingdom and to return, safe&#xD;&#xA;and secure by land and water, except for a short period in time of war,&#xD;&#xA;on grounds of public policy--reserving always the allegiance due to us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;43. If any one holding of some escheat (such as the honor of&#xD;&#xA;Wallingford, Nottingham, Boulogne, Lancaster, or of other escheats&#xD;&#xA;which are in our hands and are baronies) shall die, his heir shall give&#xD;&#xA;no other relief, and perform no other service to us than he would have&#xD;&#xA;done to the baron, if that barony had been in the baron&#39;s hand; and we&#xD;&#xA;shall hold it in the same manner in which the baron held it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;44. Men who dwell without the forest need not henceforth come before&#xD;&#xA;our justiciars of the forest upon a general summons, except those who&#xD;&#xA;are impleaded, or who have become sureties for any person or persons&#xD;&#xA;attached for forest offenses.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;45. We will appoint as justices, constables, sheriffs, or bailiffs&#xD;&#xA;only such as know the law of the realm and mean to observe it well.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;46. All barons who have founded abbeys, concerning which they hold&#xD;&#xA;charters from the kings of England, or of which they have&#xD;&#xA;long-continued possession, shall have the wardship of them, when&#xD;&#xA;vacant, as they ought to have.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;47. All forests that have been made such in our time shall forthwith&#xD;&#xA;be disafforested; and a similar course shall be followed with regard&#xD;&#xA;to river-banks that have been placed &#34;in defense&#34; by us in our time.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;48. All evil customs connected with forests and warrens, foresters&#xD;&#xA;and warreners, sheriffs and their officers, river-banks and their&#xD;&#xA;wardens, shall immediately be inquired into in each county by twelve&#xD;&#xA;sworn knights of the same county chosen by the honest men of the same&#xD;&#xA;county, and shall, within forty days of the said inquest, be utterly&#xD;&#xA;abolished, so as never to be restored, provided always that we&#xD;&#xA;previously have intimation thereof, or our justiciar, if we should not&#xD;&#xA;be in England.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;49. We will immediately restore all hostages and charters delivered to&#xD;&#xA;us by Englishmen, as sureties of the peace or of faithful service.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;50. We will entirely remove from their bailiwicks, the relations of&#xD;&#xA;Gerard Athee (so that in future they shall have no bailiwick in&#xD;&#xA;England); namely, Engelard of Cigogne, Peter, Guy, and Andrew of&#xD;&#xA;Chanceaux, Guy of Cigogne, Geofrrey of Martigny with his brothers,&#xD;&#xA;Philip Mark with his brothers and his nephew Geoffrey, and the whole&#xD;&#xA;brood of the same.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;51. As soon as peace is restored, we will banish from the kingdom&#xD;&#xA;all foreign-born knights, cross-bowmen, serjeants, and mercenary&#xD;&#xA;soldiers, who have come with horses and arms to the kingdom&#39;s hurt.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;52. If any one has been dispossessed or removed by us, without the&#xD;&#xA;legal judgment of his peers, from his lands, castles, franchises, or&#xD;&#xA;from his right, we will immediately restore them to him; and if a&#xD;&#xA;dispute arise over this, then let it be decided by the five-and-twenty&#xD;&#xA;barons of whom mention is made below in the clause for securing the&#xD;&#xA;peace. Moreover, for all those possessions, from which any one has,&#xD;&#xA;without the lawful judgment of his peers, be endisseised or removed, by&#xD;&#xA;our father, King Henry, or by our brother, King Richard, and which we&#xD;&#xA;retain in our hand (or which are possessed by others, to whom we are&#xD;&#xA;bound to warrant them) we shall have respite until the usual term of&#xD;&#xA;crusaders; excepting those things about which a plea has been raised,&#xD;&#xA;or an inquest made by our order, before our taking of the cross; but as&#xD;&#xA;soon as were turn from our expedition (or if perchance we desist from&#xD;&#xA;the expedition) we will immediately grant full justice therein.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;53. We shall have, moreover, the same respite and in the same manner&#xD;&#xA;in rendering justice concerning the disafforestation or retention of&#xD;&#xA;those forests which Henry our father and Richard our brother&#xD;&#xA;afforested, and concerning wardship of lands which are of the fief of&#xD;&#xA;another (namely, such wardships as we have hitherto had by reason of a&#xD;&#xA;fief which any one held of us by knight&#39;s service), and concerning&#xD;&#xA;abbeys founded on other fiefs than our own, in which the lord of the&#xD;&#xA;fief claims to have right; and when we have returned, or if we desist&#xD;&#xA;from our expedition, we will immediately grant full justice to all&#xD;&#xA;who complain of such things.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;54. No one shall be arrested or imprisoned upon the appeal of a woman,&#xD;&#xA;for the death of any other than her husband.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;55. All fines made with us unjustly and against the law of the land,&#xD;&#xA;and all amercements imposed unjustly and against the law of the land,&#xD;&#xA;shall be entirely remitted, or else it shall be done concerning them&#xD;&#xA;according to the decision of the five-and-twenty barons of whom mention&#xD;&#xA;is made below in the clause for securing the peace, or according to the&#xD;&#xA;judgment of the majority of the same, along with the aforesaid Stephen,&#xD;&#xA;archbishop of Canterbury, if he can be present, and such others as he&#xD;&#xA;may wish to bring with him for this purpose, and if he cannot be&#xD;&#xA;present the business shall nevertheless proceed without him, provided&#xD;&#xA;always that if any one or more of the aforesaid five-and-twenty&#xD;&#xA;barons are in a similar suit, they shall be removed as far as concerns&#xD;&#xA;this particular judgment, others being substituted in their places&#xD;&#xA;after having been selected by the rest of the same five-and-twenty for&#xD;&#xA;this purpose only, and after having been sworn.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;56. If we have disseised or removed Welshmen from lands or liberties,&#xD;&#xA;or other things, without the legal judgment of their peers in England&#xD;&#xA;or in Wales, they shall be immediately restored to them; and if a&#xD;&#xA;dispute arise over this, then let it be decided in the marches by the&#xD;&#xA;judgment of their peers; for tenements in England according to the law&#xD;&#xA;of England, for tenements in Wales according to the law of Wales, and&#xD;&#xA;for tenements in the marches according to the law of the marches.&#xD;&#xA;Welshmen shall do the same to us and ours.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;57. Further, for all those possessions from which any Welshman has,&#xD;&#xA;without the lawful judgment of his peers, been disseised or removed by&#xD;&#xA;King Henry our father or King Richard our brother, and which we retain&#xD;&#xA;in our hand (or which are possessed by others, to whom we are bound to&#xD;&#xA;warrant them) we shall have respite until the usual term of crusaders;&#xD;&#xA;excepting those things about which a plea has been raised or an inquest&#xD;&#xA;made by our order before we took the cross; but as soon as we return&#xD;&#xA;(or if perchance we desist from our expedition), we will immediately&#xD;&#xA;grant full justice in accordance with the laws of the Welsh and in&#xD;&#xA;relation to the foresaid regions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;58. We will immediately give up the son of Llywelyn and all the&#xD;&#xA;hostages of Wales, and the charters delivered to us as security for the&#xD;&#xA;peace.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;59. We will do toward Alexander, King of Scots, concerning the return&#xD;&#xA;of his sisters and his hostages, and concerning his franchises, and his&#xD;&#xA;right, in the same manner as we shall do toward our other barons of&#xD;&#xA;England, unless it ought to be otherwise according to the charters&#xD;&#xA;which we hold from William his father, formerly King of Scots; and this&#xD;&#xA;shall be according to the judgment of his peers in our court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;60. Moreover, all these aforesaid customs and liberties, the&#xD;&#xA;observance of which we have granted in our kingdom as far as pertains&#xD;&#xA;to us toward our men, shall be observed by all of our kingdom, as well&#xD;&#xA;clergy as laymen, as far as pertains to them toward their men.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;61. Since, moreover, for God and the amendment of our kingdom and for&#xD;&#xA;the better allaying of the quarrel that has arisen between us and our&#xD;&#xA;barons, we have granted all these concessions, desirous that they&#xD;&#xA;should enjoy them in complete and firm endurance for ever, we give and&#xD;&#xA;grant to them the underwritten security, namely, that the barons choose&#xD;&#xA;five-and-twenty barons of the kingdom, whomsoever they will, who shall&#xD;&#xA;be bound with all their might, to observe and hold, and cause to be&#xD;&#xA;observed, the peace and liberties we have granted and confirmed to them&#xD;&#xA;by this our present Charter, so that if we, or our justiciar, or our&#xD;&#xA;bailiffs or any one of our officers, shall in anything be at fault&#xD;&#xA;toward any one, or shall have broken any one of the articles of&#xD;&#xA;the peace or of this security, and the offense be notified to four&#xD;&#xA;barons of the foresaid five-and-twenty, the said four barons shall&#xD;&#xA;repair to us (or our justiciar, if we are out of the realm) and, laying&#xD;&#xA;the transgression before us, petition to have that transgression&#xD;&#xA;redressed without delay. And if we shall not have corrected the&#xD;&#xA;transgression (or, in the event of our being out of the realm, if our&#xD;&#xA;justiciar shall not have corrected it) within forty days, reckoning&#xD;&#xA;from the time it has been intimated to us (or to our justiciar, if&#xD;&#xA;we should be out of the realm), the four barons aforesaid shall refer&#xD;&#xA;that matter to the rest of the five-and-twenty barons, and those&#xD;&#xA;five-and-twenty barons shall, together with the community of the whole&#xD;&#xA;land, distrain and distress us in all possible ways, namely, by seizing&#xD;&#xA;our castles, lands, possessions, and in any other way they can, until&#xD;&#xA;redress has been obtained as they deem fit, saving harmless our own&#xD;&#xA;person, and the persons of our queen and children; and when redress has&#xD;&#xA;been obtained, they shall resume their old relations toward us. And let&#xD;&#xA;whoever in the country desires it, swear to obey the orders of the said&#xD;&#xA;five-and-twenty barons for the execution of all the aforesaid matters,&#xD;&#xA;and along with them, to molest us to the utmost of his power; and we&#xD;&#xA;publicly and freely grant leave to every one who wishes to swear, and&#xD;&#xA;we shall never forbid any one to swear. All those, moreover, in the&#xD;&#xA;land who of themselves and of their own accord are unwilling to swear&#xD;&#xA;to the twenty-five to help them in constraining and molesting us, we&#xD;&#xA;shall by our command compel the same to swear to the effect aforesaid.&#xD;&#xA;And if any one of the five-and-twenty barons shall have died or&#xD;&#xA;departed from the land, or be incapacitated in any other manner which&#xD;&#xA;would prevent the foresaid provisions being carried out, those of&#xD;&#xA;the said twenty-five barons who are left shall choose another in his&#xD;&#xA;place according to their own judgment, and he shall be sworn in the&#xD;&#xA;same way as the others. Further, in all matters, the execution of which&#xD;&#xA;is intrusted to these twenty-five barons, if perchance these&#xD;&#xA;twenty-five are present, that which the majority of those present&#xD;&#xA;ordain or command shall be held as fixed and established, exactly as if&#xD;&#xA;the whole twenty-five had concurred in this; and the said twenty-five&#xD;&#xA;shall swear that they will faithfully observe all that is aforesaid,&#xD;&#xA;and cause it to be observed with all their might. And we shall procure&#xD;&#xA;nothing from any one, directly or indirectly, whereby any part of&#xD;&#xA;these concessions and liberties might be revoked or diminished; and if&#xD;&#xA;any such thing has been procured, let it be void and null, and we shall&#xD;&#xA;never use it personally or by another.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;62. And all the ill-will, hatreds, and bitterness that have arisen&#xD;&#xA;between us and our men, clergy and lay, from the date of the quarrel,&#xD;&#xA;we have completely remitted and pardoned every one. Moreover, all&#xD;&#xA;trespasses occasioned by the said quarrel, from Easter in the sixteenth&#xD;&#xA;year of our reign till the restoration of peace, we have fully remitted&#xD;&#xA;to all, both clergy and laymen, and completely forgiven, as far as&#xD;&#xA;pertains to us. And, on this head, we have caused to be made for them&#xD;&#xA;letters testimonial patent of the lord Stephen, archbishop of&#xD;&#xA;Canterbury, of the lord Henry, archbishop of Dublin, of the bishops&#xD;&#xA;aforesaid, and of Master Pandulf as touching this security and&#xD;&#xA;the concessions aforesaid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;63. Wherefore it is our will, and we firmly enjoin, that the English&#xD;&#xA;Church be free, and that the men in our kingdom have and hold all the&#xD;&#xA;aforesaid liberties, rights, and concessions, well and peaceably,&#xD;&#xA;freely and quietly, fully and wholly, for themselves and their heirs,&#xD;&#xA;of us and our heirs, in all respects and in all places for ever, as is&#xD;&#xA;aforesaid. An oath, moreover, has been taken, as well on our part as on&#xD;&#xA;the part of the barons, that all these conditions aforesaid shall be&#xD;&#xA;kept in good faith and without evil intent. Given under our hand--the&#xD;&#xA;above-named and many others being witnesses--in the meadow which is&#xD;&#xA;called Runnymede, between Windsor and Staines, on the fifteenth day of&#xD;&#xA;June, in the seventeenth year of our reign.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The text of THE MAGNA CARTA&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Magna Carta (The Great Charter):&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Preamble:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;John, by the grace of God, king of England, lord of Ireland, duke of&#xD;&#xA;Normandy and Aquitaine, and count of Anjou, to the archbishop,&#xD;&#xA;bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justiciaries, foresters, sheriffs,&#xD;&#xA;stewards, servants, and to all his bailiffs and liege subjects,&#xD;&#xA;greetings.  Know that, having regard to God and for the salvation of&#xD;&#xA;our soul, and those of all our ancestors and heirs, and unto the honor&#xD;&#xA;of God and the advancement of his holy Church and for the rectifying&#xD;&#xA;of our realm, we have granted as underwritten by advice of our&#xD;&#xA;venerable fathers, Stephen, archbishop of Canterbury, primate of all&#xD;&#xA;England and cardinal of the holy Roman Church, Henry, archbishop of&#xD;&#xA;Dublin, William of London, Peter of Winchester, Jocelyn of Bath and&#xD;&#xA;Glastonbury, Hugh of Lincoln, Walter of Worcester, William of&#xD;&#xA;Coventry, Benedict of Rochester, bishops; of Master Pandulf, subdeacon&#xD;&#xA;and member of the household of our lord the Pope, of brother Aymeric&#xD;&#xA;(master of the Knights of the Temple in England), and of the&#xD;&#xA;illustrious men William Marshal, earl of Pembroke, William, earl of&#xD;&#xA;Salisbury, William, earl of Warenne, William, earl of Arundel, Alan of&#xD;&#xA;Galloway (constable of Scotland), Waren Fitz Gerold, Peter Fitz&#xD;&#xA;Herbert, Hubert De Burgh (seneschal of Poitou), Hugh de Neville,&#xD;&#xA;Matthew Fitz Herbert, Thomas Basset, Alan Basset, Philip d&#39;Aubigny,&#xD;&#xA;Robert of Roppesley, John Marshal, John Fitz Hugh, and others, our&#xD;&#xA;liegemen.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1. In the first place we have granted to God, and by this our present&#xD;&#xA;charter confirmed for us and our heirs forever that the English Church&#xD;&#xA;shall be free, and shall have her rights entire, and her liberties&#xD;&#xA;inviolate; and we will that it be thus observed; which is apparent&#xD;&#xA;from this that the freedom of elections, which is reckoned most&#xD;&#xA;important and very essential to the English Church, we, of our pure&#xD;&#xA;and unconstrained will, did grant, and did by our charter confirm and&#xD;&#xA;did obtain the ratification of the same from our lord, Pope Innocent&#xD;&#xA;III, before the quarrel arose between us and our barons: and this we&#xD;&#xA;will observe, and our will is that it be observed in good faith by our&#xD;&#xA;heirs forever.  We have also granted to all freemen of our kingdom,&#xD;&#xA;for us and our heirs forever, all the underwritten liberties, to be&#xD;&#xA;had and held by them and their heirs, of us and our heirs forever.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;2. If any of our earls or barons, or others holding of us in chief by&#xD;&#xA;military service shall have died, and at the time of his death his&#xD;&#xA;heir shall be full of age and owe &#34;relief&#34;, he shall have his&#xD;&#xA;inheritance by the old relief, to wit, the heir or heirs of an earl,&#xD;&#xA;for the whole baroncy of an earl by L100; the heir or heirs of a&#xD;&#xA;baron, L100 for a whole barony; the heir or heirs of a knight, 100s,&#xD;&#xA;at most, and whoever owes less let him give less, according to the&#xD;&#xA;ancient custom of fees.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;3. If, however, the heir of any one of the aforesaid has been under&#xD;&#xA;age and in wardship, let him have his inheritance without relief and&#xD;&#xA;without fine when he comes of age.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;4. The guardian of the land of an heir who is thus under age, shall&#xD;&#xA;take from the land of the heir nothing but reasonable produce,&#xD;&#xA;reasonable customs, and reasonable services, and that without&#xD;&#xA;destruction or waste of men or goods; and if we have committed the&#xD;&#xA;wardship of the lands of any such minor to the sheriff, or to any&#xD;&#xA;other who is responsible to us for its issues, and he has made&#xD;&#xA;destruction or waster of what he holds in wardship, we will take of&#xD;&#xA;him amends, and the land shall be committed to two lawful and discreet&#xD;&#xA;men of that fee, who shall be responsible for the issues to us or to&#xD;&#xA;him to whom we shall assign them; and if we have given or sold the&#xD;&#xA;wardship of any such land to anyone and he has therein made&#xD;&#xA;destruction or waste, he shall lose that wardship, and it shall be&#xD;&#xA;transferred to two lawful and discreet men of that fief, who shall be&#xD;&#xA;responsible to us in like manner as aforesaid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;5. The guardian, moreover, so long as he has the wardship of the land,&#xD;&#xA;shall keep up the houses, parks, fishponds, stanks, mills, and other&#xD;&#xA;things pertaining to the land, out of the issues of the same land; and&#xD;&#xA;he shall restore to the heir, when he has come to full age, all his&#xD;&#xA;land, stocked with ploughs and wainage, according as the season of&#xD;&#xA;husbandry shall require, and the issues of the land can reasonable&#xD;&#xA;bear.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;6. Heirs shall be married without disparagement, yet so that before&#xD;&#xA;the marriage takes place the nearest in blood to that heir shall have&#xD;&#xA;notice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;7. A widow, after the death of her husband, shall forthwith and&#xD;&#xA;without difficulty have her marriage portion and inheritance; nor&#xD;&#xA;shall she give anything for her dower, or for her marriage portion, or&#xD;&#xA;for the inheritance which her husband and she held on the day of the&#xD;&#xA;death of that husband; and she may remain in the house of her husband&#xD;&#xA;for forty days after his death, within which time her dower shall be&#xD;&#xA;assigned to her.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;8. No widow shall be compelled to marry, so long as she prefers to&#xD;&#xA;live without a husband; provided always that she gives security not to&#xD;&#xA;marry without our consent, if she holds of us, or without the consent&#xD;&#xA;of the lord of whom she holds, if she holds of another.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;9. Neither we nor our bailiffs will seize any land or rent for any&#xD;&#xA;debt, as long as the chattels of the debtor are sufficient to repay&#xD;&#xA;the debt; nor shall the sureties of the debtor be distrained so long&#xD;&#xA;as the principal debtor is able to satisfy the debt; and if the&#xD;&#xA;principal debtor shall fail to pay the debt, having nothing wherewith&#xD;&#xA;to pay it, then the sureties shall answer for the debt; and let them&#xD;&#xA;have the lands and rents of the debtor, if they desire them, until&#xD;&#xA;they are indemnified for the debt which they have paid for him, unless&#xD;&#xA;the principal debtor can show proof that he is discharged thereof as&#xD;&#xA;against the said sureties.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;10. If one who has borrowed from the Jews any sum, great or small, die&#xD;&#xA;before that loan be repaid, the debt shall not bear interest while the&#xD;&#xA;heir is under age, of whomsoever he may hold; and if the debt fall&#xD;&#xA;into our hands, we will not take anything except the principal sum&#xD;&#xA;contained in the bond.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;11. And if anyone die indebted to the Jews, his wife shall have her&#xD;&#xA;dower and pay nothing of that debt; and if any children of the&#xD;&#xA;deceased are left under age, necessaries shall be provided for them in&#xD;&#xA;keeping with the holding of the deceased; and out of the residue the&#xD;&#xA;debt shall be paid, reserving, however, service due to feudal lords;&#xD;&#xA;in like manner let it be done touching debts due to others than Jews.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;12. No scutage not aid shall be imposed on our kingdom, unless by&#xD;&#xA;common counsel of our kingdom, except for ransoming our person, for&#xD;&#xA;making our eldest son a knight, and for once marrying our eldest&#xD;&#xA;daughter; and for these there shall not be levied more than a&#xD;&#xA;reasonable aid.  In like manner it shall be done concerning aids from&#xD;&#xA;the city of London.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;13. And the city of London shall have all it ancient liberties and&#xD;&#xA;free customs, as well by land as by water; furthermore, we decree&#xD;&#xA;and grant that all other cities, boroughs, towns, and ports shall&#xD;&#xA;have all their liberties and free customs.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;14. And for obtaining the common counsel of the kingdom anent the&#xD;&#xA;assessing of an aid (except in the three cases aforesaid) or of a&#xD;&#xA;scutage, we will cause to be summoned the archbishops, bishops,&#xD;&#xA;abbots, earls, and greater barons, severally by our letters; and we&#xD;&#xA;will moveover cause to be summoned generally, through our sheriffs and&#xD;&#xA;bailiffs, and others who hold of us in chief, for a fixed date,&#xD;&#xA;namely, after the expiry of at least forty days, and at a fixed place;&#xD;&#xA;and in all letters of such summons we will specify the reason of the&#xD;&#xA;summons.  And when the summons has thus been made, the business shall&#xD;&#xA;proceed on the day appointed, according to the counsel of such as are&#xD;&#xA;present, although not all who were summoned have come.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;15. We will not for the future grant to anyone license to take an aid&#xD;&#xA;from his own free tenants, except to ransom his person, to make his&#xD;&#xA;eldest son a knight, and once to marry his eldest daughter; and on&#xD;&#xA;each of these occasions there shall be levied only a reasonable aid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;16. No one shall be distrained for performance of greater service for&#xD;&#xA;a knight&#39;s fee, or for any other free tenement, than is due therefrom.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;17. Common pleas shall not follow our court, but shall be held in some&#xD;&#xA;fixed place.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;18. Inquests of novel disseisin, of mort d&#39;ancestor, and of darrein&#xD;&#xA;presentment shall not be held elsewhere than in their own county&#xD;&#xA;courts, and that in manner following; We, or, if we should be out of&#xD;&#xA;the realm, our chief justiciar, will send two justiciaries through&#xD;&#xA;every county four times a year, who shall alone with four knights of&#xD;&#xA;the county chosen by the county, hold the said assizes in the county&#xD;&#xA;court, on the day and in the place of meeting of that court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;19. And if any of the said assizes cannot be taken on the day of the&#xD;&#xA;county court, let there remain of the knights and freeholders, who&#xD;&#xA;were present at the county court on that day, as many as may be&#xD;&#xA;required for the efficient making of judgments, according as the&#xD;&#xA;business be more or less.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;20. A freeman shall not be amerced for a slight offense, except in&#xD;&#xA;accordance with the degree of the offense; and for a grave offense he&#xD;&#xA;shall be amerced in accordance with the gravity of the offense, yet&#xD;&#xA;saving always his &#34;contentment&#34;; and a merchant in the same way,&#xD;&#xA;saving his &#34;merchandise&#34;; and a villein shall be amerced in the same&#xD;&#xA;way, saving his &#34;wainage&#34; if they have fallen into our mercy: and none&#xD;&#xA;of the aforesaid amercements shall be imposed except by the oath of&#xD;&#xA;honest men of the neighborhood.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;21. Earls and barons shall not be amerced except through their peers,&#xD;&#xA;and only in accordance with the degree of the offense.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;22. A clerk shall not be amerced in respect of his lay holding except&#xD;&#xA;after the manner of the others aforesaid; further, he shall not be&#xD;&#xA;amerced in accordance with the extent of his ecclesiastical benefice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;23. No village or individual shall be compelled to make bridges at&#xD;&#xA;river banks, except those who from of old were legally bound to do so.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;24. No sheriff, constable, coroners, or others of our bailiffs, shall&#xD;&#xA;hold pleas of our Crown.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;25. All counties, hundred, wapentakes, and trithings (except our&#xD;&#xA;demesne manors) shall remain at the old rents, and without any&#xD;&#xA;additional payment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;26. If anyone holding of us a lay fief shall die, and our sheriff or&#xD;&#xA;bailiff shall exhibit our letters patent of summons for a debt which&#xD;&#xA;the deceased owed us, it shall be lawful for our sheriff or bailiff to&#xD;&#xA;attach and enroll the chattels of the deceased, found upon the lay&#xD;&#xA;fief, to the value of that debt, at the sight of law worthy men,&#xD;&#xA;provided always that nothing whatever be thence removed until the debt&#xD;&#xA;which is evident shall be fully paid to us; and the residue shall be&#xD;&#xA;left to the executors to fulfill the will of the deceased; and if&#xD;&#xA;there be nothing due from him to us, all the chattels shall go to the&#xD;&#xA;deceased, saving to his wife and children their reasonable shares.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;27. If any freeman shall die intestate, his chattels shall be&#xD;&#xA;distributed by the hands of his nearest kinsfolk and friends, under&#xD;&#xA;supervision of the Church, saving to every one the debts which the&#xD;&#xA;deceased owed to him.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;28. No constable or other bailiff of ours shall take corn or other&#xD;&#xA;provisions from anyone without immediately tendering money therefor,&#xD;&#xA;unless he can have postponement thereof by permission of the seller.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;29. No constable shall compel any knight to give money in lieu of&#xD;&#xA;castle-guard, when he is willing to perform it in his own person, or&#xD;&#xA;(if he himself cannot do it from any reasonable cause) then by another&#xD;&#xA;responsible man.  Further, if we have led or sent him upon military&#xD;&#xA;service, he shall be relieved from guard in proportion to the time&#xD;&#xA;during which he has been on service because of us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;30. No sheriff or bailiff of ours, or other person, shall take the&#xD;&#xA;horses or carts of any freeman for transport duty, against the will of&#xD;&#xA;the said freeman.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;31. Neither we nor our bailiffs shall take, for our castles or for any&#xD;&#xA;other work of ours, wood which is not ours, against the will of the&#xD;&#xA;owner of that wood.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;32. We will not retain beyond one year and one day, the lands those&#xD;&#xA;who have been convicted of felony, and the lands shall thereafter be&#xD;&#xA;handed over to the lords of the fiefs.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;33. All kydells for the future shall be removed altogether from Thames&#xD;&#xA;and Medway, and throughout all England, except upon the seashore.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;34. The writ which is called praecipe shall not for the future be&#xD;&#xA;issued to anyone, regarding any tenement whereby a freeman may lose&#xD;&#xA;his court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;35. Let there be one measure of wine throughout our whole realm; and&#xD;&#xA;one measure of ale; and one measure of corn, to wit, &#34;the London&#xD;&#xA;quarter&#34;; and one width of cloth (whether dyed, or russet, or&#xD;&#xA;&#34;halberget&#34;), to wit, two ells within the selvedges; of weights also&#xD;&#xA;let it be as of measures.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;36. Nothing in future shall be given or taken for a writ of&#xD;&#xA;inquisition of life or limbs, but freely it shall be granted,&#xD;&#xA;and never denied.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;37. If anyone holds of us by fee-farm, either by socage or by burage,&#xD;&#xA;or of any other land by knight&#39;s service, we will not (by reason of&#xD;&#xA;that fee-farm, socage, or burgage), have the wardship of the heir, or&#xD;&#xA;of such land of his as if of the fief of that other; nor shall we have&#xD;&#xA;wardship of that fee-farm, socage, or burgage, unless such fee-farm&#xD;&#xA;owes knight&#39;s service.  We will not by reason of any small serjeancy&#xD;&#xA;which anyone may hold of us by the service of rendering to us knives,&#xD;&#xA;arrows, or the like, have wardship of his heir or of the land which he&#xD;&#xA;holds of another lord by knight&#39;s service.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;38. No bailiff for the future shall, upon his own unsupported&#xD;&#xA;complaint, put anyone to his &#34;law&#34;, without credible witnesses brought&#xD;&#xA;for this purposes.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;39. No freemen shall be taken or imprisoned or disseised or exiled or&#xD;&#xA;in any way destroyed, nor will we go upon him nor send upon him,&#xD;&#xA;except by the lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of the land.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;40. To no one will we sell, to no one will we refuse or delay, right&#xD;&#xA;or justice.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;41. All merchants shall have safe and secure exit from England, and&#xD;&#xA;entry to England, with the right to tarry there and to move about as&#xD;&#xA;well by land as by water, for buying and selling by the ancient and&#xD;&#xA;right customs, quit from all evil tolls, except (in time of war) such&#xD;&#xA;merchants as are of the land at war with us. And if such are found in&#xD;&#xA;our land at the beginning of the war, they shall be detained, without&#xD;&#xA;injury to their bodies or goods, until information be received by us,&#xD;&#xA;or by our chief justiciar, how the merchants of our land found in the&#xD;&#xA;land at war with us are treated; and if our men are safe there, the&#xD;&#xA;others shall be safe in our land.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;42. It shall be lawful in future for anyone (excepting always those&#xD;&#xA;imprisoned or outlawed in accordance with the law of the kingdom, and&#xD;&#xA;natives of any country at war with us, and merchants, who shall be&#xD;&#xA;treated as if above provided) to leave our kingdom and to return, safe&#xD;&#xA;and secure by land and water, except for a short period in time of&#xD;&#xA;war, on grounds of public policy- reserving always the allegiance due&#xD;&#xA;to us.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;43. If anyone holding of some escheat (such as the honor of&#xD;&#xA;Wallingford, Nottingham, Boulogne, Lancaster, or of other escheats&#xD;&#xA;which are in our hands and are baronies) shall die, his heir shall&#xD;&#xA;give no other relief, and perform no other service to us than he would&#xD;&#xA;have done to the baron if that barony had been in the baron&#39;s hand;&#xD;&#xA;and we shall hold it in the same manner in which the baron held it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;44. Men who dwell without the forest need not henceforth come before&#xD;&#xA;our justiciaries of the forest upon a general summons, unless they are&#xD;&#xA;in plea, or sureties of one or more, who are attached for the forest.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;45. We will appoint as justices, constables, sheriffs, or bailiffs&#xD;&#xA;only such as know the law of the realm and mean to observe it well.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;46. All barons who have founded abbeys, concerning which they hold&#xD;&#xA;charters from the kings of England, or of which they have long&#xD;&#xA;continued possession, shall have the wardship of them, when vacant, as&#xD;&#xA;they ought to have.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;47. All forests that have been made such in our time shall forthwith&#xD;&#xA;be disafforsted; and a similar course shall be followed with regard&#xD;&#xA;to river banks that have been placed &#34;in defense&#34; by us in our time.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;48.  All evil customs connected with forests and warrens, foresters&#xD;&#xA;and warreners, sheriffs and their officers, river banks and their&#xD;&#xA;wardens, shall immediately by inquired into in each county by twelve&#xD;&#xA;sworn knights of the same county chosen by the honest men of the same&#xD;&#xA;county, and shall, within forty days of the said inquest, be utterly&#xD;&#xA;abolished, so as never to be restored, provided always that we&#xD;&#xA;previously have intimation thereof, or our justiciar, if we should not&#xD;&#xA;be in England.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;49. We will immediately restore all hostages and charters delivered to&#xD;&#xA;us by Englishmen, as sureties of the peace of faithful service.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;50. We will entirely remove from their bailiwicks, the relations of&#xD;&#xA;Gerard of Athee (so that in future they shall have no bailiwick in&#xD;&#xA;England); namely, Engelard of Cigogne, Peter, Guy, and Andrew of&#xD;&#xA;Chanceaux, Guy of Cigogne, Geoffrey of Martigny with his brothers,&#xD;&#xA;Philip Mark with his brothers and his nephew Geoffrey, and the whole&#xD;&#xA;brood of the same.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;51. As soon as peace is restored, we will banish from the kingdom all&#xD;&#xA;foreign born knights, crossbowmen, serjeants, and mercenary soldiers&#xD;&#xA;who have come with horses and arms to the kingdom&#39;s hurt.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;52. If anyone has been dispossessed or removed by us, without the&#xD;&#xA;legal judgment of his peers, from his lands, castles, franchises, or&#xD;&#xA;from his right, we will immediately restore them to him; and if a&#xD;&#xA;dispute arise over this, then let it be decided by the five and twenty&#xD;&#xA;barons of whom mention is made below in the clause for securing the&#xD;&#xA;peace.  Moreover, for all those possessions, from which anyone has,&#xD;&#xA;without the lawful judgment of his peers, been disseised or removed,&#xD;&#xA;by our father, King Henry, or by our brother, King Richard, and which&#xD;&#xA;we retain in our hand (or which as possessed by others, to whom we are&#xD;&#xA;bound to warrant them) we shall have respite until the usual term of&#xD;&#xA;crusaders; excepting those things about which a plea has been raised,&#xD;&#xA;or an inquest made by our order, before our taking of the cross; but&#xD;&#xA;as soon as we return from the expedition, we will immediately grant&#xD;&#xA;full justice therein.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;53. We shall have, moreover, the same respite and in the same manner&#xD;&#xA;in rendering justice concerning the disafforestation or retention of&#xD;&#xA;those forests which Henry our father and Richard our brother&#xD;&#xA;afforested, and concerning the wardship of lands which are of the fief&#xD;&#xA;of another (namely, such wardships as we have hitherto had by reason&#xD;&#xA;of a fief which anyone held of us by knight&#39;s service), and concerning&#xD;&#xA;abbeys founded on other fiefs than our own, in which the lord of the&#xD;&#xA;fee claims to have right; and when we have returned, or if we desist&#xD;&#xA;from our expedition, we will immediately grant full justice to all who&#xD;&#xA;complain of such things.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;54. No one shall be arrested or imprisoned upon the appeal of a woman,&#xD;&#xA;for the death of any other than her husband.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;55. All fines made with us unjustly and against the law of the land,&#xD;&#xA;and all amercements, imposed unjustly and against the law of the land,&#xD;&#xA;shall be entirely remitted, or else it shall be done concerning them&#xD;&#xA;according to the decision of the five and twenty barons whom mention&#xD;&#xA;is made below in the clause for securing the pease, or according to&#xD;&#xA;the judgment of the majority of the same, along with the aforesaid&#xD;&#xA;Stephen, archbishop of Canterbury, if he can be present, and such&#xD;&#xA;others as he may wish to bring with him for this purpose, and if he&#xD;&#xA;cannot be present the business shall nevertheless proceed without him,&#xD;&#xA;provided always that if any one or more of the aforesaid five and&#xD;&#xA;twenty barons are in a similar suit, they shall be removed as far as&#xD;&#xA;concerns this particular judgment, others being substituted in their&#xD;&#xA;places after having been selected by the rest of the same five and&#xD;&#xA;twenty for this purpose only, and after having been sworn.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;56. If we have disseised or removed Welshmen from lands or liberties,&#xD;&#xA;or other things, without the legal judgment of their peers in England&#xD;&#xA;or in Wales, they shall be immediately restored to them; and if a&#xD;&#xA;dispute arise over this, then let it be decided in the marches by the&#xD;&#xA;judgment of their peers; for the tenements in England according to the&#xD;&#xA;law of England, for tenements in Wales according to the law of Wales,&#xD;&#xA;and for tenements in the marches according to the law of the marches.&#xD;&#xA;Welshmen shall do the same to us and ours.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;57. Further, for all those possessions from which any Welshman has,&#xD;&#xA;without the lawful judgment of his peers, been disseised or removed by&#xD;&#xA;King Henry our father, or King Richard our brother, and which we&#xD;&#xA;retain in our hand (or which are possessed by others, and which we&#xD;&#xA;ought to warrant), we will have respite until the usual term of&#xD;&#xA;crusaders; excepting those things about which a plea has been raised&#xD;&#xA;or an inquest made by our order before we took the cross; but as soon&#xD;&#xA;as we return (or if perchance we desist from our expedition), we will&#xD;&#xA;immediately grant full justice in accordance with the laws of the&#xD;&#xA;Welsh and in relation to the foresaid regions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;58. We will immediately give up the son of Llywelyn and all the&#xD;&#xA;hostages of Wales, and the charters delivered to us as security for&#xD;&#xA;the peace.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;59. We will do towards Alexander, king of Scots, concerning the return&#xD;&#xA;of his sisters and his hostages, and concerning his franchises, and&#xD;&#xA;his right, in the same manner as we shall do towards our other barons&#xD;&#xA;of England, unless it ought to be otherwise according to the charters&#xD;&#xA;which we hold from William his father, formerly king of Scots; and&#xD;&#xA;this shall be according to the judgment of his peers in our court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;60. Moreover, all these aforesaid customs and liberties, the&#xD;&#xA;observances of which we have granted in our kingdom as far as pertains&#xD;&#xA;to us towards our men, shall be observed b all of our kingdom, as well&#xD;&#xA;clergy as laymen, as far as pertains to them towards their men.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;61. Since, moveover, for God and the amendment of our kingdom and for&#xD;&#xA;the better allaying of the quarrel that has arisen between us and our&#xD;&#xA;barons, we have granted all these concessions, desirous that they&#xD;&#xA;should enjoy them in complete and firm endurance forever, we give and&#xD;&#xA;grant to them the underwritten security, namely, that the barons&#xD;&#xA;choose five and twenty barons of the kingdom, whomsoever they will,&#xD;&#xA;who shall be bound with all their might, to observe and hold, and&#xD;&#xA;cause to be observed, the peace and liberties we have granted and&#xD;&#xA;confirmed to them by this our present Charter, so that if we, or our&#xD;&#xA;justiciar, or our bailiffs or any one of our officers, shall in&#xD;&#xA;anything be at fault towards anyone, or shall have broken any one of&#xD;&#xA;the articles of this peace or of this security, and the offense be&#xD;&#xA;notified to four barons of the foresaid five and twenty, the said four&#xD;&#xA;barons shall repair to us (or our justiciar, if we are out of the&#xD;&#xA;realm) and, laying the transgression before us, petition to have that&#xD;&#xA;transgression redressed without delay.  And if we shall not have&#xD;&#xA;corrected the transgression (or, in the event of our being out of the&#xD;&#xA;realm, if our justiciar shall not have corrected it) within forty&#xD;&#xA;days, reckoning from the time it has been intimated to us (or to our&#xD;&#xA;justiciar, if we should be out of the realm), the four barons&#xD;&#xA;aforesaid shall refer that matter to the rest of the five and twenty&#xD;&#xA;barons, and those five and twenty barons shall, together with the&#xD;&#xA;community of the whole realm, distrain and distress us in all possible&#xD;&#xA;ways, namely, by seizing our castles, lands, possessions, and in any&#xD;&#xA;other way they can, until redress has been obtained as they deem fit,&#xD;&#xA;saving harmless our own person, and the persons of our queen and&#xD;&#xA;children; and when redress has been obtained, they shall resume their&#xD;&#xA;old relations towards us.  And let whoever in the country desires it,&#xD;&#xA;swear to obey the orders of the said five and twenty barons for the&#xD;&#xA;execution of all the aforesaid matters, and along with them, to molest&#xD;&#xA;us to the utmost of his power; and we publicly and freely grant leave&#xD;&#xA;to everyone who wishes to swear, and we shall never forbid anyone to&#xD;&#xA;swear.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;All those, moveover, in the land who of themselves and of their own&#xD;&#xA;accord are unwilling to swear to the twenty five to help them in&#xD;&#xA;constraining and molesting us, we shall by our command compel the same&#xD;&#xA;to swear to the effect foresaid.  And if any one of the five and&#xD;&#xA;twenty barons shall have died or departed from the land, or be&#xD;&#xA;incapacitated in any other manner which would prevent the foresaid&#xD;&#xA;provisions being carried out, those of the said twenty five barons who&#xD;&#xA;are left shall choose another in his place according to their own&#xD;&#xA;judgment, and he shall be sworn in the same way as the others.&#xD;&#xA;Further, in all matters, the execution of which is entrusted to these&#xD;&#xA;twenty five barons, if perchance these twenty five are present and&#xD;&#xA;disagree about anything, or if some of them, after being summoned, are&#xD;&#xA;unwilling or unable to be present, that which the majority of those&#xD;&#xA;present ordain or command shall be held as fixed and established,&#xD;&#xA;exactly as if the whole twenty five had concurred in this; and the&#xD;&#xA;said twenty five shall swear that they will faithfully observe all&#xD;&#xA;that is aforesaid, and cause it to be observed with all their might.&#xD;&#xA;And we shall procure nothing from anyone, directly or indirectly,&#xD;&#xA;whereby any part of these concessions and liberties might be revoked&#xD;&#xA;or diminished; and if any such things has been procured, let it be&#xD;&#xA;void and null, and we shall never use it personally or by another.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;62. And all the will, hatreds, and bitterness that have arisen between&#xD;&#xA;us and our men, clergy and lay, from the date of the quarrel, we have&#xD;&#xA;completely remitted and pardoned to everyone.  Moreover, all&#xD;&#xA;trespasses occasioned by the said quarrel, from Easter in the&#xD;&#xA;sixteenth year of our reign till the restoration of peace, we have&#xD;&#xA;fully remitted to all, both clergy and laymen, and completely&#xD;&#xA;forgiven, as far as pertains to us.  And on this head, we have caused&#xD;&#xA;to be made for them letters testimonial patent of the lord Stephen,&#xD;&#xA;archbishop of Canterbury, of the lord Henry, archbishop of Dublin, of&#xD;&#xA;the bishops aforesaid, and of Master Pandulf as touching this security&#xD;&#xA;and the concessions aforesaid.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;63. Wherefore we will and firmly order that the English Church be&#xD;&#xA;free, and that the men in our kingdom have and hold all the aforesaid&#xD;&#xA;liberties, rights, and concessions, well and peaceably, freely and&#xD;&#xA;quietly, fully and wholly, for themselves and their heirs, of us and&#xD;&#xA;our heirs, in all respects and in all places forever, as is&#xD;&#xA;aforesaid.  An oath, moreover, has been taken, as well on our part as&#xD;&#xA;on the part of the barons, that all these conditions aforesaid shall be&#xD;&#xA;kept in good faith and without evil intent.  Given under our hand -&#xD;&#xA;the above named and many others being witnesses - in the meadow which&#xD;&#xA;is called Runnymede, between Windsor and Staines, on the fifteenth day&#xD;&#xA;of June, in the seventeenth year of our reign.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;End of the Project Gutenberg EBook of The Magna Carta, by Anonymous&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*** END OF THIS PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THE MAGNA CARTA ***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***** This file should be named 10000.txt or 10000.zip *****&#xD;&#xA;This and all associated files of various formats will be found in:&#xD;&#xA;        http://www.gutenberg.org/1/0/0/0/10000/&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Produced by Michael Hart&#xD;&#xA;Updated editions will replace the previous one--the old editions will&#xD;&#xA;be renamed.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Creating the works from print editions not protected by U.S. copyright&#xD;&#xA;law means that no one owns a United States copyright in these works,&#xD;&#xA;so the Foundation (and you!) can copy and distribute it in the United&#xD;&#xA;States without permission and without paying copyright&#xD;&#xA;royalties. Special rules, set forth in the General Terms of Use part&#xD;&#xA;of this license, apply to copying and distributing Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm electronic works to protect the PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm&#xD;&#xA;concept and trademark. Project Gutenberg is a registered trademark,&#xD;&#xA;and may not be used if you charge for the eBooks, unless you receive&#xD;&#xA;specific permission. If you do not charge anything for copies of this&#xD;&#xA;eBook, complying with the rules is very easy. You may use this eBook&#xD;&#xA;for nearly any purpose such as creation of derivative works, reports,&#xD;&#xA;performances and research. They may be modified and printed and given&#xD;&#xA;away--you may do practically ANYTHING in the United States with eBooks&#xD;&#xA;not protected by U.S. copyright law. Redistribution is subject to the&#xD;&#xA;trademark license, especially commercial redistribution.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;START: FULL LICENSE&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;THE FULL PROJECT GUTENBERG LICENSE&#xD;&#xA;PLEASE READ THIS BEFORE YOU DISTRIBUTE OR USE THIS WORK&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To protect the Project Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting the free&#xD;&#xA;distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work&#xD;&#xA;(or any other work associated in any way with the phrase &#34;Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg&#34;), you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm License available with this file or online at&#xD;&#xA;www.gutenberg.org/license.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1. General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm electronic works&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.A. By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;electronic work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to&#xD;&#xA;and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property&#xD;&#xA;(trademark/copyright) agreement. If you do not agree to abide by all&#xD;&#xA;the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or&#xD;&#xA;destroy all copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in your&#xD;&#xA;possession. If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work and you do not agree to be bound&#xD;&#xA;by the terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the&#xD;&#xA;person or entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph&#xD;&#xA;1.E.8.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.B. &#34;Project Gutenberg&#34; is a registered trademark. It may only be&#xD;&#xA;used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who&#xD;&#xA;agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement. There are a few&#xD;&#xA;things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works&#xD;&#xA;even without complying with the full terms of this agreement. See&#xD;&#xA;paragraph 1.C below. There are a lot of things you can do with Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm electronic works if you follow the terms of this&#xD;&#xA;agreement and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;electronic works. See paragraph 1.E below.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.C. The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation (&#34;the&#xD;&#xA;Foundation&#34; or PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection&#xD;&#xA;of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works. Nearly all the individual&#xD;&#xA;works in the collection are in the public domain in the United&#xD;&#xA;States. If an individual work is unprotected by copyright law in the&#xD;&#xA;United States and you are located in the United States, we do not&#xD;&#xA;claim a right to prevent you from copying, distributing, performing,&#xD;&#xA;displaying or creating derivative works based on the work as long as&#xD;&#xA;all references to Project Gutenberg are removed. Of course, we hope&#xD;&#xA;that you will support the Project Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting&#xD;&#xA;free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for keeping the&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm name associated with the work. You can easily&#xD;&#xA;comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the&#xD;&#xA;same format with its attached full Project Gutenberg-tm License when&#xD;&#xA;you share it without charge with others.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.D. The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern&#xD;&#xA;what you can do with this work. Copyright laws in most countries are&#xD;&#xA;in a constant state of change. If you are outside the United States,&#xD;&#xA;check the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this&#xD;&#xA;agreement before downloading, copying, displaying, performing,&#xD;&#xA;distributing or creating derivative works based on this work or any&#xD;&#xA;other Project Gutenberg-tm work. The Foundation makes no&#xD;&#xA;representations concerning the copyright status of any work in any&#xD;&#xA;country outside the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E. Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.1. The following sentence, with active links to, or other&#xD;&#xA;immediate access to, the full Project Gutenberg-tm License must appear&#xD;&#xA;prominently whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg-tm work (any work&#xD;&#xA;on which the phrase &#34;Project Gutenberg&#34; appears, or with which the&#xD;&#xA;phrase &#34;Project Gutenberg&#34; is associated) is accessed, displayed,&#xD;&#xA;performed, viewed, copied or distributed:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;  This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and&#xD;&#xA;  most other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no&#xD;&#xA;  restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it&#xD;&#xA;  under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included with this&#xD;&#xA;  eBook or online at www.gutenberg.org. If you are not located in the&#xD;&#xA;  United States, you&#39;ll have to check the laws of the country where you&#xD;&#xA;  are located before using this ebook.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.2. If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is&#xD;&#xA;derived from texts not protected by U.S. copyright law (does not&#xD;&#xA;contain a notice indicating that it is posted with permission of the&#xD;&#xA;copyright holder), the work can be copied and distributed to anyone in&#xD;&#xA;the United States without paying any fees or charges. If you are&#xD;&#xA;redistributing or providing access to a work with the phrase &#34;Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg&#34; associated with or appearing on the work, you must comply&#xD;&#xA;either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 or&#xD;&#xA;obtain permission for the use of the work and the Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.3. If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is posted&#xD;&#xA;with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution&#xD;&#xA;must comply with both paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 and any&#xD;&#xA;additional terms imposed by the copyright holder. Additional terms&#xD;&#xA;will be linked to the Project Gutenberg-tm License for all works&#xD;&#xA;posted with the permission of the copyright holder found at the&#xD;&#xA;beginning of this work.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.4. Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;License terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this&#xD;&#xA;work or any other work associated with Project Gutenberg-tm.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.5. Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this&#xD;&#xA;electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without&#xD;&#xA;prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph 1.E.1 with&#xD;&#xA;active links or immediate access to the full terms of the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm License.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.6. You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary,&#xD;&#xA;compressed, marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including&#xD;&#xA;any word processing or hypertext form. However, if you provide access&#xD;&#xA;to or distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg-tm work in a format&#xD;&#xA;other than &#34;Plain Vanilla ASCII&#34; or other format used in the official&#xD;&#xA;version posted on the official Project Gutenberg-tm web site&#xD;&#xA;(www.gutenberg.org), you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense&#xD;&#xA;to the user, provide a copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means&#xD;&#xA;of obtaining a copy upon request, of the work in its original &#34;Plain&#xD;&#xA;Vanilla ASCII&#34; or other form. Any alternate format must include the&#xD;&#xA;full Project Gutenberg-tm License as specified in paragraph 1.E.1.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.7. Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying,&#xD;&#xA;performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg-tm works&#xD;&#xA;unless you comply with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.8. You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing&#xD;&#xA;access to or distributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works&#xD;&#xA;provided that&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from&#xD;&#xA;  the use of Project Gutenberg-tm works calculated using the method&#xD;&#xA;  you already use to calculate your applicable taxes. The fee is owed&#xD;&#xA;  to the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark, but he has&#xD;&#xA;  agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the Project&#xD;&#xA;  Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation. Royalty payments must be paid&#xD;&#xA;  within 60 days following each date on which you prepare (or are&#xD;&#xA;  legally required to prepare) your periodic tax returns. Royalty&#xD;&#xA;  payments should be clearly marked as such and sent to the Project&#xD;&#xA;  Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the address specified in&#xD;&#xA;  Section 4, &#34;Information about donations to the Project Gutenberg&#xD;&#xA;  Literary Archive Foundation.&#34;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies&#xD;&#xA;  you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he&#xD;&#xA;  does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;  License. You must require such a user to return or destroy all&#xD;&#xA;  copies of the works possessed in a physical medium and discontinue&#xD;&#xA;  all use of and all access to other copies of Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;  works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of&#xD;&#xA;  any money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the&#xD;&#xA;  electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days of&#xD;&#xA;  receipt of the work.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;* You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free&#xD;&#xA;  distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.9. If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm electronic work or group of works on different terms than&#xD;&#xA;are set forth in this agreement, you must obtain permission in writing&#xD;&#xA;from both the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and The&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg Trademark LLC, the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;trademark. Contact the Foundation as set forth in Section 3 below.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.1. Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable&#xD;&#xA;effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread&#xD;&#xA;works not protected by U.S. copyright law in creating the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm collection. Despite these efforts, Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;electronic works, and the medium on which they may be stored, may&#xD;&#xA;contain &#34;Defects,&#34; such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate&#xD;&#xA;or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other&#xD;&#xA;intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or&#xD;&#xA;other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or&#xD;&#xA;cannot be read by your equipment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.2. LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES - Except for the &#34;Right&#xD;&#xA;of Replacement or Refund&#34; described in paragraph 1.F.3, the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm trademark, and any other party distributing a Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all&#xD;&#xA;liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal&#xD;&#xA;fees. YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT&#xD;&#xA;LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE&#xD;&#xA;PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH 1.F.3. YOU AGREE THAT THE FOUNDATION, THE&#xD;&#xA;TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT WILL NOT BE&#xD;&#xA;LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE OR&#xD;&#xA;INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH&#xD;&#xA;DAMAGE.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.3. LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND - If you discover a&#xD;&#xA;defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can&#xD;&#xA;receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a&#xD;&#xA;written explanation to the person you received the work from. If you&#xD;&#xA;received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium&#xD;&#xA;with your written explanation. The person or entity that provided you&#xD;&#xA;with the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in&#xD;&#xA;lieu of a refund. If you received the work electronically, the person&#xD;&#xA;or entity providing it to you may choose to give you a second&#xD;&#xA;opportunity to receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund. If&#xD;&#xA;the second copy is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing&#xD;&#xA;without further opportunities to fix the problem.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.4. Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth&#xD;&#xA;in paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you &#39;AS-IS&#39;, WITH NO&#xD;&#xA;OTHER WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT&#xD;&#xA;LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY PURPOSE.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.5. Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied&#xD;&#xA;warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of&#xD;&#xA;damages. If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement&#xD;&#xA;violates the law of the state applicable to this agreement, the&#xD;&#xA;agreement shall be interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or&#xD;&#xA;limitation permitted by the applicable state law. The invalidity or&#xD;&#xA;unenforceability of any provision of this agreement shall not void the&#xD;&#xA;remaining provisions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.6. INDEMNITY - You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the&#xD;&#xA;trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone&#xD;&#xA;providing copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in&#xD;&#xA;accordance with this agreement, and any volunteers associated with the&#xD;&#xA;production, promotion and distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs and expenses,&#xD;&#xA;including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of&#xD;&#xA;the following which you do or cause to occur: (a) distribution of this&#xD;&#xA;or any Project Gutenberg-tm work, (b) alteration, modification, or&#xD;&#xA;additions or deletions to any Project Gutenberg-tm work, and (c) any&#xD;&#xA;Defect you cause.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 2. Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm is synonymous with the free distribution of&#xD;&#xA;electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of&#xD;&#xA;computers including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers. It&#xD;&#xA;exists because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations&#xD;&#xA;from people in all walks of life.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the&#xD;&#xA;assistance they need are critical to reaching Project Gutenberg-tm&#39;s&#xD;&#xA;goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberg-tm collection will&#xD;&#xA;remain freely available for generations to come. In 2001, the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure&#xD;&#xA;and permanent future for Project Gutenberg-tm and future&#xD;&#xA;generations. To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary&#xD;&#xA;Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations can help, see&#xD;&#xA;Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation information page at&#xD;&#xA;www.gutenberg.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3. Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non profit&#xD;&#xA;501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the&#xD;&#xA;state of Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal&#xD;&#xA;Revenue Service. The Foundation&#39;s EIN or federal tax identification&#xD;&#xA;number is 64-6221541. Contributions to the Project Gutenberg Literary&#xD;&#xA;Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full extent permitted by&#xD;&#xA;U.S. federal laws and your state&#39;s laws.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation&#39;s principal office is in Fairbanks, Alaska, with the&#xD;&#xA;mailing address: PO Box 750175, Fairbanks, AK 99775, but its&#xD;&#xA;volunteers and employees are scattered throughout numerous&#xD;&#xA;locations. Its business office is located at 809 North 1500 West, Salt&#xD;&#xA;Lake City, UT 84116, (801) 596-1887. Email contact links and up to&#xD;&#xA;date contact information can be found at the Foundation&#39;s web site and&#xD;&#xA;official page at www.gutenberg.org/contact&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;For additional contact information:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    Dr. Gregory B. Newby&#xD;&#xA;    Chief Executive and Director&#xD;&#xA;    gbnewby@pglaf.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 4. Information about Donations to the Project Gutenberg&#xD;&#xA;Literary Archive Foundation&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm depends upon and cannot survive without wide&#xD;&#xA;spread public support and donations to carry out its mission of&#xD;&#xA;increasing the number of public domain and licensed works that can be&#xD;&#xA;freely distributed in machine readable form accessible by the widest&#xD;&#xA;array of equipment including outdated equipment. Many small donations&#xD;&#xA;($1 to $5,000) are particularly important to maintaining tax exempt&#xD;&#xA;status with the IRS.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating&#xD;&#xA;charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United&#xD;&#xA;States. Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a&#xD;&#xA;considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up&#xD;&#xA;with these requirements. We do not solicit donations in locations&#xD;&#xA;where we have not received written confirmation of compliance. To SEND&#xD;&#xA;DONATIONS or determine the status of compliance for any particular&#xD;&#xA;state visit www.gutenberg.org/donate&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we&#xD;&#xA;have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition&#xD;&#xA;against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who&#xD;&#xA;approach us with offers to donate.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make&#xD;&#xA;any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from&#xD;&#xA;outside the United States. U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Please check the Project Gutenberg Web pages for current donation&#xD;&#xA;methods and addresses. Donations are accepted in a number of other&#xD;&#xA;ways including checks, online payments and credit card donations. To&#xD;&#xA;donate, please visit: www.gutenberg.org/donate&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 5. General Information About Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Professor Michael S. Hart was the originator of the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg-tm concept of a library of electronic works that could be&#xD;&#xA;freely shared with anyone. For forty years, he produced and&#xD;&#xA;distributed Project Gutenberg-tm eBooks with only a loose network of&#xD;&#xA;volunteer support.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg-tm eBooks are often created from several printed&#xD;&#xA;editions, all of which are confirmed as not protected by copyright in&#xD;&#xA;the U.S. unless a copyright notice is included. Thus, we do not&#xD;&#xA;necessarily keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper&#xD;&#xA;edition.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Most people start at our Web site which has the main PG search&#xD;&#xA;facility: www.gutenberg.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This Web site includes information about Project Gutenberg-tm,&#xD;&#xA;including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary&#xD;&#xA;Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to&#xD;&#xA;subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new eBooks. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/11/magnacarta.txt</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/11/independence.txt</link>
            <description>﻿The Project Gutenberg EBook of The Declaration of Independence of The&#xD;&#xA;United States of America by Thomas Jefferson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no&#xD;&#xA;restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under&#xD;&#xA;the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or&#xD;&#xA;online at http://www.gutenberg.org/license&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Title: The Declaration of Independence of The United States of America&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Author: Thomas Jefferson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Release Date: October 12, 2005 [Ebook #16780]&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Language: English&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Character set encoding: UTF-8&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***START OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THE DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Declaration of Independence of The United States of America&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;by Thomas Jefferson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Edition 1, (October 12, 2005)&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;THE DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;                        IN CONGRESS, July 4, 1776&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The unanimous Declaration of the thirteen united States of America&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;When in the Course of human events, it becomes necessary for one people to&#xD;&#xA;dissolve the political bands which have connected them with another, and&#xD;&#xA;to assume, among the Powers of the earth, the separate and equal station&#xD;&#xA;to which the Laws of Nature and of Nature’s God entitle them, a decent&#xD;&#xA;respect to the opinions of mankind requires that they should declare the&#xD;&#xA;causes which impel them to the separation.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal,&#xD;&#xA;that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights,&#xD;&#xA;that among these are Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness.—That to&#xD;&#xA;secure these rights, Governments are instituted among Men, deriving their&#xD;&#xA;just powers from the consent of the governed,—That whenever any Form of&#xD;&#xA;Government becomes destructive of these ends, it is the Right of the&#xD;&#xA;People to alter or to abolish it, and to institute new Government, laying&#xD;&#xA;its foundation on such principles and organizing its powers in such form,&#xD;&#xA;as to them shall seem most likely to effect their Safety and Happiness.&#xD;&#xA;Prudence, indeed, will dictate that Governments long established should&#xD;&#xA;not be changed for light and transient causes; and accordingly all&#xD;&#xA;experience hath shown, that mankind are more disposed to suffer, while&#xD;&#xA;evils are sufferable, than to right themselves by abolishing the forms to&#xD;&#xA;which they are accustomed. But when a long train of abuses and&#xD;&#xA;usurpations, pursuing invariably the same Object evinces a design to&#xD;&#xA;reduce them under absolute Despotism, it is their right, it is their duty,&#xD;&#xA;to throw off such Government, and to provide new Guards for their future&#xD;&#xA;security.—Such has been the patient sufferance of these Colonies; and such&#xD;&#xA;is now the necessity which constrains them to alter their former Systems&#xD;&#xA;of Government. The history of the present King of Great Britain is a&#xD;&#xA;history of repeated injuries and usurpations, all having in direct object&#xD;&#xA;the establishment of an absolute Tyranny over these States. To prove this,&#xD;&#xA;let Facts be submitted to a candid world.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      He has refused his Assent to Laws, the most wholesome and necessary&#xD;&#xA;      for the public good.&#xD;&#xA;      He has forbidden his Governors to pass Laws of immediate and&#xD;&#xA;      pressing importance, unless suspended in their operation till his&#xD;&#xA;      Assent should be obtained; and when so suspended, he has utterly&#xD;&#xA;      neglected to attend to them.&#xD;&#xA;      He has refused to pass other Laws for the accommodation of large&#xD;&#xA;      districts of people, unless those people would relinquish the right&#xD;&#xA;      of Representation in the Legislature, a right inestimable to them&#xD;&#xA;      and formidable to tyrants only.&#xD;&#xA;      He has called together legislative bodies at places unusual,&#xD;&#xA;      uncomfortable, and distant from the depository of their Public&#xD;&#xA;      Records, for the sole purpose of fatiguing them into compliance with&#xD;&#xA;      his measures.&#xD;&#xA;      He has dissolved Representative Houses repeatedly, for opposing with&#xD;&#xA;      manly firmness his invasions on the rights of the people.&#xD;&#xA;      He has refused for a long time, after such dissolutions, to cause&#xD;&#xA;      others to be elected; whereby the Legislative Powers, incapable of&#xD;&#xA;      Annihilation, have returned to the People at large for their&#xD;&#xA;      exercise; the State remaining in the mean time exposed to all the&#xD;&#xA;      dangers of invasion from without, and convulsions within.&#xD;&#xA;      He has endeavoured to prevent the population of these States; for&#xD;&#xA;      that purpose obstructing the Laws of Naturalization of Foreigners;&#xD;&#xA;      refusing to pass others to encourage their migration hither, and&#xD;&#xA;      raising the conditions of new Appropriations of Lands.&#xD;&#xA;      He has obstructed the Administration of Justice, by refusing his&#xD;&#xA;      Assent to Laws for establishing Judiciary Powers.&#xD;&#xA;      He has made judges dependent on his Will alone, for the tenure of&#xD;&#xA;      their offices, and the amount and payment of their salaries.&#xD;&#xA;      He has erected a multitude of New Offices, and sent hither swarms of&#xD;&#xA;      Officers to harass our People, and eat out their substance.&#xD;&#xA;      He has kept among us, in times of peace, Standing Armies without the&#xD;&#xA;      Consent of our legislatures.&#xD;&#xA;      He has affected to render the Military independent of and superior&#xD;&#xA;      to the Civil Power.&#xD;&#xA;      He has combined with others to subject us to a jurisdiction foreign&#xD;&#xA;      to our constitution, and unacknowledged by our laws; giving his&#xD;&#xA;      Assent to their Acts of pretended legislation:&#xD;&#xA;      For quartering large bodies of armed troops among us:&#xD;&#xA;      For protecting them, by a mock Trial, from Punishment for any&#xD;&#xA;      Murders which they should commit on the Inhabitants of these States:&#xD;&#xA;      For cutting off our Trade with all parts of the world:&#xD;&#xA;      For imposing taxes on us without our Consent:&#xD;&#xA;      For depriving us, in many cases, of the benefits of Trial by Jury:&#xD;&#xA;      For transporting us beyond Seas to be tried for pretended offences:&#xD;&#xA;      For abolishing the free System of English Laws in a neighbouring&#xD;&#xA;      Province, establishing therein an Arbitrary government, and&#xD;&#xA;      enlarging its Boundaries so as to render it at once an example and&#xD;&#xA;      fit instrument for introducing the same absolute rule into these&#xD;&#xA;      Colonies:&#xD;&#xA;      For taking away our Charters, abolishing our most valuable Laws, and&#xD;&#xA;      altering fundamentally the Forms of our Governments:&#xD;&#xA;      For suspending our own Legislatures, and declaring themselves&#xD;&#xA;      invested with Power to legislate for us in all cases whatsoever.&#xD;&#xA;      He has abdicated Government here, by declaring us out of his&#xD;&#xA;      Protection and waging War against us.&#xD;&#xA;      He has plundered our seas, ravaged our Coasts, burnt our towns, and&#xD;&#xA;      destroyed the lives of our people.&#xD;&#xA;      He is at this time transporting large armies of foreign mercenaries&#xD;&#xA;      to compleat the works of death, desolation and tyranny, already&#xD;&#xA;      begun with circumstances of Cruelty &amp; perfidy scarcely paralleled in&#xD;&#xA;      the most barbarous ages, and totally unworthy of the Head of a&#xD;&#xA;      civilized nation.&#xD;&#xA;      He has constrained our fellow Citizens taken Captive on the high&#xD;&#xA;      Seas to bear Arms against their Country, to become the executioners&#xD;&#xA;      of their friends and Brethren, or to fall themselves by their Hands.&#xD;&#xA;      He has excited domestic insurrections amongst us, and has&#xD;&#xA;      endeavoured to bring on the inhabitants of our frontiers, the&#xD;&#xA;      merciless Indian Savages, whose known rule of warfare, is an&#xD;&#xA;      undistinguished destruction of all ages, sexes and conditions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In every stage of these Oppressions We have Petitioned for Redress in the&#xD;&#xA;most humble terms: Our repeated Petitions have been answered only by&#xD;&#xA;repeated injury. A Prince, whose character is thus marked by every act&#xD;&#xA;which may define a Tyrant, is unfit to be the ruler of a free People.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Nor have We been wanting in attention to our Brittish brethren. We have&#xD;&#xA;warned them from time to time of attempts by their legislature to extend&#xD;&#xA;an unwarrantable jurisdiction over us. We have reminded them of the&#xD;&#xA;circumstances of our emigration and settlement here. We have appealed to&#xD;&#xA;their native justice and magnanimity, and we have conjured them by the&#xD;&#xA;ties of our common kindred to disavow these usurpations, which would&#xD;&#xA;inevitably interrupt our connections and correspondence. They too have&#xD;&#xA;been deaf to the voice of justice and of consanguinity. We must,&#xD;&#xA;therefore, acquiesce in the necessity, which denounces our Separation, and&#xD;&#xA;hold them, as we hold the rest of mankind, Enemies in War, in Peace&#xD;&#xA;Friends.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We, therefore, the Representatives of the United States of America, in&#xD;&#xA;General Congress, Assembled, appealing to the Supreme Judge of the world&#xD;&#xA;for the rectitude of our intentions, do, in the Name, and by the Authority&#xD;&#xA;of the good People of these Colonies, solemnly publish and declare, That&#xD;&#xA;these United Colonies are, and of Right ought to be Free and Independent&#xD;&#xA;States; that they are Absolved from all Allegiance to the British Crown,&#xD;&#xA;and that all political connection between them and the State of Great&#xD;&#xA;Britain, is and ought to be totally dissolved; and that as Free and&#xD;&#xA;Independent States, they have full Power to levy War, conclude Peace,&#xD;&#xA;contract Alliances, establish Commerce, and to do all other Acts and&#xD;&#xA;Things which Independent States may of right do. And for the support of&#xD;&#xA;this Declaration, with a firm reliance on the Protection of Divine&#xD;&#xA;Providence, we mutually pledge to each other our Lives, our Fortunes and&#xD;&#xA;our sacred Honor.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Button Gwinnett&#xD;&#xA;      Lyman Hall&#xD;&#xA;      George Walton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      William Hooper&#xD;&#xA;      Joseph Hewes&#xD;&#xA;      John Penn&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Edward Rutledge&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas Heyward, Jr.&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas Lunch, Jr.&#xD;&#xA;      Arthur Middleton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      John Hancock&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Samuel Chase&#xD;&#xA;      William Paca&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas Stone&#xD;&#xA;      Charles Carroll of Carrollton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      George Wythe&#xD;&#xA;      Richard Henry Lee&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas Jefferson&#xD;&#xA;      Benjamin Harrison&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas Nelson, Jr.&#xD;&#xA;      Francis Lightfoot Lee&#xD;&#xA;      Carter Braxton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Robert Morris&#xD;&#xA;      Benjamin Rush&#xD;&#xA;      Benjamin Franklin&#xD;&#xA;      John Morton&#xD;&#xA;      George Clymer&#xD;&#xA;      James Smith&#xD;&#xA;      George Taylor&#xD;&#xA;      James Wilson&#xD;&#xA;      George Ross&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Caesar Rodney&#xD;&#xA;      George Read&#xD;&#xA;      Thomas McKean&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      William Floyd&#xD;&#xA;      Philip Livingston&#xD;&#xA;      Francis Lewis&#xD;&#xA;      Lewis Morris&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Richard Stockton&#xD;&#xA;      John Witherspoon&#xD;&#xA;      Francis Hopkinson&#xD;&#xA;      John Hart&#xD;&#xA;      Abraham Clark&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Josiah Bartlett&#xD;&#xA;      William Whipple&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Samuel Adams&#xD;&#xA;      John Adams&#xD;&#xA;      Robert Treat Paine&#xD;&#xA;      Elbridge Gerry&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Stephen Hopkins&#xD;&#xA;      William Ellery&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Roger Sherman&#xD;&#xA;      Samuel Huntington&#xD;&#xA;      William Williams&#xD;&#xA;      Oliver Wolcott&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      Matthew Thornton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***END OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THE DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;CREDITS&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;October 12, 2005&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;            Created document.&#xD;&#xA;            Joshua Hutchinson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;June 2006&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;            Added PGHeader/PGFooter.&#xD;&#xA;            Joshua Hutchinson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;A WORD FROM PROJECT GUTENBERG&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This file should be named 16780-0.txt or 16780-0.zip.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This and all associated files of various formats will be found in:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/1/6/7/8/16780/&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Updated editions will replace the previous one — the old editions will be&#xD;&#xA;renamed.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Creating the works from public domain print editions means that no one&#xD;&#xA;owns a United States copyright in these works, so the Foundation (and&#xD;&#xA;you!) can copy and distribute it in the United States without permission&#xD;&#xA;and without paying copyright royalties. Special rules, set forth in the&#xD;&#xA;General Terms of Use part of this license, apply to copying and&#xD;&#xA;distributing Project Gutenberg™ electronic works to protect the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg™ concept and trademark. Project Gutenberg is a registered&#xD;&#xA;trademark, and may not be used if you charge for the eBooks, unless you&#xD;&#xA;receive specific permission. If you do not charge anything for copies of&#xD;&#xA;this eBook, complying with the rules is very easy. You may use this eBook&#xD;&#xA;for nearly any purpose such as creation of derivative works, reports,&#xD;&#xA;performances and research. They may be modified and printed and given away&#xD;&#xA;— you may do practically _anything_ with public domain eBooks.&#xD;&#xA;Redistribution is subject to the trademark license, especially commercial&#xD;&#xA;redistribution.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;THE FULL PROJECT GUTENBERG LICENSE&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;_Please read this before you distribute or use this work._&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To protect the Project Gutenberg™ mission of promoting the free&#xD;&#xA;distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work (or&#xD;&#xA;any other work associated in any way with the phrase “Project Gutenberg”),&#xD;&#xA;you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;License (available with this file or online at&#xD;&#xA;http://www.gutenberg.org/license).&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;General Terms of Use &amp; Redistributing Project Gutenberg™ electronic works&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.A.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg™ electronic work,&#xD;&#xA;you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to and accept all the&#xD;&#xA;terms of this license and intellectual property (trademark/copyright)&#xD;&#xA;agreement. If you do not agree to abide by all the terms of this&#xD;&#xA;agreement, you must cease using and return or destroy all copies of&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ electronic works in your possession. If you paid a fee&#xD;&#xA;for obtaining a copy of or access to a Project Gutenberg™ electronic work&#xD;&#xA;and you do not agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement, you may&#xD;&#xA;obtain a refund from the person or entity to whom you paid the fee as set&#xD;&#xA;forth in paragraph 1.E.8.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.B.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;“Project Gutenberg” is a registered trademark. It may only be used on or&#xD;&#xA;associated in any way with an electronic work by people who agree to be&#xD;&#xA;bound by the terms of this agreement. There are a few things that you can&#xD;&#xA;do with most Project Gutenberg™ electronic works even without complying&#xD;&#xA;with the full terms of this agreement. See paragraph 1.C below. There are&#xD;&#xA;a lot of things you can do with Project Gutenberg™ electronic works if you&#xD;&#xA;follow the terms of this agreement and help preserve free future access to&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ electronic works. See paragraph 1.E below.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.C.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation (“the Foundation” or&#xD;&#xA;PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection of Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg™ electronic works. Nearly all the individual works in the&#xD;&#xA;collection are in the public domain in the United States. If an individual&#xD;&#xA;work is in the public domain in the United States and you are located in&#xD;&#xA;the United States, we do not claim a right to prevent you from copying,&#xD;&#xA;distributing, performing, displaying or creating derivative works based on&#xD;&#xA;the work as long as all references to Project Gutenberg are removed. Of&#xD;&#xA;course, we hope that you will support the Project Gutenberg™ mission of&#xD;&#xA;promoting free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg™ works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for&#xD;&#xA;keeping the Project Gutenberg™ name associated with the work. You can&#xD;&#xA;easily comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the&#xD;&#xA;same format with its attached full Project Gutenberg™ License when you&#xD;&#xA;share it without charge with others.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.D.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern what you&#xD;&#xA;can do with this work. Copyright laws in most countries are in a constant&#xD;&#xA;state of change. If you are outside the United States, check the laws of&#xD;&#xA;your country in addition to the terms of this agreement before&#xD;&#xA;downloading, copying, displaying, performing, distributing or creating&#xD;&#xA;derivative works based on this work or any other Project Gutenberg™ work.&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation makes no representations concerning the copyright status of&#xD;&#xA;any work in any country outside the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.1.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The following sentence, with active links to, or other immediate access&#xD;&#xA;to, the full Project Gutenberg™ License must appear prominently whenever&#xD;&#xA;any copy of a Project Gutenberg™ work (any work on which the phrase&#xD;&#xA;“Project Gutenberg” appears, or with which the phrase “Project Gutenberg”&#xD;&#xA;is associated) is accessed, displayed, performed, viewed, copied or&#xD;&#xA;distributed:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with&#xD;&#xA;    almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away&#xD;&#xA;    or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License&#xD;&#xA;    included with this eBook or online at http://www.gutenberg.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.2.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If an individual Project Gutenberg™ electronic work is derived from the&#xD;&#xA;public domain (does not contain a notice indicating that it is posted with&#xD;&#xA;permission of the copyright holder), the work can be copied and&#xD;&#xA;distributed to anyone in the United States without paying any fees or&#xD;&#xA;charges. If you are redistributing or providing access to a work with the&#xD;&#xA;phrase “Project Gutenberg” associated with or appearing on the work, you&#xD;&#xA;must comply either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7&#xD;&#xA;or obtain permission for the use of the work and the Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.3.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If an individual Project Gutenberg™ electronic work is posted with the&#xD;&#xA;permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution must comply&#xD;&#xA;with both paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 and any additional terms imposed&#xD;&#xA;by the copyright holder. Additional terms will be linked to the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg™ License for all works posted with the permission of the&#xD;&#xA;copyright holder found at the beginning of this work.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.4.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberg™ License&#xD;&#xA;terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this work or any&#xD;&#xA;other work associated with Project Gutenberg™.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.5.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this electronic&#xD;&#xA;work, or any part of this electronic work, without prominently displaying&#xD;&#xA;the sentence set forth in paragraph 1.E.1 with active links or immediate&#xD;&#xA;access to the full terms of the Project Gutenberg™ License.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.6.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary, compressed,&#xD;&#xA;marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including any word&#xD;&#xA;processing or hypertext form. However, if you provide access to or&#xD;&#xA;distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg™ work in a format other than&#xD;&#xA;“Plain Vanilla ASCII” or other format used in the official version posted&#xD;&#xA;on the official Project Gutenberg™ web site (http://www.gutenberg.org),&#xD;&#xA;you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense to the user, provide a&#xD;&#xA;copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means of obtaining a copy upon&#xD;&#xA;request, of the work in its original “Plain Vanilla ASCII” or other form.&#xD;&#xA;Any alternate format must include the full Project Gutenberg™ License as&#xD;&#xA;specified in paragraph 1.E.1.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.7.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying, performing,&#xD;&#xA;copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg™ works unless you comply&#xD;&#xA;with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.8.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing access to or&#xD;&#xA;distributing Project Gutenberg™ electronic works provided that&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    - You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from&#xD;&#xA;      the use of Project Gutenberg™ works calculated using the method you&#xD;&#xA;      already use to calculate your applicable taxes. The fee is owed to&#xD;&#xA;      the owner of the Project Gutenberg™ trademark, but he has agreed to&#xD;&#xA;      donate royalties under this paragraph to the Project Gutenberg&#xD;&#xA;      Literary Archive Foundation. Royalty payments must be paid within 60&#xD;&#xA;      days following each date on which you prepare (or are legally&#xD;&#xA;      required to prepare) your periodic tax returns. Royalty payments&#xD;&#xA;      should be clearly marked as such and sent to the Project Gutenberg&#xD;&#xA;      Literary Archive Foundation at the address specified in Section 4,&#xD;&#xA;      “Information about donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary&#xD;&#xA;      Archive Foundation.”&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    - You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies&#xD;&#xA;      you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he&#xD;&#xA;      does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg™ License.&#xD;&#xA;      You must require such a user to return or destroy all copies of the&#xD;&#xA;      works possessed in a physical medium and discontinue all use of and&#xD;&#xA;      all access to other copies of Project Gutenberg™ works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    - You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of&#xD;&#xA;      any money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the&#xD;&#xA;      electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days of&#xD;&#xA;      receipt of the work.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    - You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free&#xD;&#xA;      distribution of Project Gutenberg™ works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.E.9.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project Gutenberg™ electronic&#xD;&#xA;work or group of works on different terms than are set forth in this&#xD;&#xA;agreement, you must obtain permission in writing from both the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and Michael Hart, the owner of the&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ trademark. Contact the Foundation as set forth in&#xD;&#xA;Section 3 below.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.1.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable effort to&#xD;&#xA;identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread public domain&#xD;&#xA;works in creating the Project Gutenberg™ collection. Despite these&#xD;&#xA;efforts, Project Gutenberg™ electronic works, and the medium on which they&#xD;&#xA;may be stored, may contain “Defects,” such as, but not limited to,&#xD;&#xA;incomplete, inaccurate or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright&#xD;&#xA;or other intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk&#xD;&#xA;or other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot&#xD;&#xA;be read by your equipment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.2.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES — Except for the “Right of&#xD;&#xA;Replacement or Refund” described in paragraph 1.F.3, the Project Gutenberg&#xD;&#xA;Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;trademark, and any other party distributing a Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all liability to you for&#xD;&#xA;damages, costs and expenses, including legal fees. YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE&#xD;&#xA;NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH&#xD;&#xA;OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH F3. YOU AGREE THAT THE&#xD;&#xA;FOUNDATION, THE TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT&#xD;&#xA;WILL NOT BE LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL,&#xD;&#xA;PUNITIVE OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY&#xD;&#xA;OF SUCH DAMAGE.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.3.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND — If you discover a defect in this&#xD;&#xA;electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can receive a refund&#xD;&#xA;of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a written explanation to&#xD;&#xA;the person you received the work from. If you received the work on a&#xD;&#xA;physical medium, you must return the medium with your written explanation.&#xD;&#xA;The person or entity that provided you with the defective work may elect&#xD;&#xA;to provide a replacement copy in lieu of a refund. If you received the&#xD;&#xA;work electronically, the person or entity providing it to you may choose&#xD;&#xA;to give you a second opportunity to receive the work electronically in&#xD;&#xA;lieu of a refund. If the second copy is also defective, you may demand a&#xD;&#xA;refund in writing without further opportunities to fix the problem.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.4.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth in&#xD;&#xA;paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you ’AS-IS,’ WITH NO OTHER&#xD;&#xA;WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO&#xD;&#xA;WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTIBILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY PURPOSE.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.5.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied warranties or the&#xD;&#xA;exclusion or limitation of certain types of damages. If any disclaimer or&#xD;&#xA;limitation set forth in this agreement violates the law of the state&#xD;&#xA;applicable to this agreement, the agreement shall be interpreted to make&#xD;&#xA;the maximum disclaimer or limitation permitted by the applicable state&#xD;&#xA;law. The invalidity or unenforceability of any provision of this agreement&#xD;&#xA;shall not void the remaining provisions.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;1.F.6.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;INDEMNITY — You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the trademark&#xD;&#xA;owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone providing copies of&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ electronic works in accordance with this agreement, and&#xD;&#xA;any volunteers associated with the production, promotion and distribution&#xD;&#xA;of Project Gutenberg™ electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs&#xD;&#xA;and expenses, including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from&#xD;&#xA;any of the following which you do or cause to occur: (a) distribution of&#xD;&#xA;this or any Project Gutenberg™ work, (b) alteration, modification, or&#xD;&#xA;additions or deletions to any Project Gutenberg™ work, and (c) any Defect&#xD;&#xA;you cause.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section  2.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;           Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ is synonymous with the free distribution of electronic&#xD;&#xA;works in formats readable by the widest variety of computers including&#xD;&#xA;obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers. It exists because of the&#xD;&#xA;efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations from people in all walks&#xD;&#xA;of life.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the assistance&#xD;&#xA;they need, is critical to reaching Project Gutenberg™’s goals and ensuring&#xD;&#xA;that the Project Gutenberg™ collection will remain freely available for&#xD;&#xA;generations to come. In 2001, the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive&#xD;&#xA;Foundation was created to provide a secure and permanent future for&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ and future generations. To learn more about the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations&#xD;&#xA;can help, see Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation web page at&#xD;&#xA;http://www.pglaf.org.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;   Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non profit&#xD;&#xA;501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the state of&#xD;&#xA;Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal Revenue Service.&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation’s EIN or federal tax identification number is 64-6221541.&#xD;&#xA;Its 501(c)(3) letter is posted at&#xD;&#xA;http://www.gutenberg.org/fundraising/pglaf. Contributions to the Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full&#xD;&#xA;extent permitted by U.S. federal laws and your state’s laws.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation’s principal office is located at 4557 Melan Dr.&#xD;&#xA;S. Fairbanks, AK, 99712., but its volunteers and employees are scattered&#xD;&#xA;throughout numerous locations. Its business office is located at 809 North&#xD;&#xA;1500 West, Salt Lake City, UT 84116, (801) 596-1887, email&#xD;&#xA;business@pglaf.org. Email contact links and up to date contact information&#xD;&#xA;can be found at the Foundation’s web site and official page at&#xD;&#xA;http://www.pglaf.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;For additional contact information:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    Dr. Gregory B. Newby&#xD;&#xA;    Chief Executive and Director&#xD;&#xA;    gbnewby@pglaf.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 4.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;  Information about Donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive&#xD;&#xA;                                Foundation&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ depends upon and cannot survive without wide spread&#xD;&#xA;public support and donations to carry out its mission of increasing the&#xD;&#xA;number of public domain and licensed works that can be freely distributed&#xD;&#xA;in machine readable form accessible by the widest array of equipment&#xD;&#xA;including outdated equipment. Many small donations ($1 to $5,000) are&#xD;&#xA;particularly important to maintaining tax exempt status with the IRS.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating&#xD;&#xA;charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United States.&#xD;&#xA;Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a considerable&#xD;&#xA;effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up with these&#xD;&#xA;requirements. We do not solicit donations in locations where we have not&#xD;&#xA;received written confirmation of compliance. To SEND DONATIONS or&#xD;&#xA;determine the status of compliance for any particular state visit&#xD;&#xA;http://www.gutenberg.org/fundraising/donate&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we have&#xD;&#xA;not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition against&#xD;&#xA;accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who approach us&#xD;&#xA;with offers to donate.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make any&#xD;&#xA;statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from outside the&#xD;&#xA;United States. U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Please check the Project Gutenberg Web pages for current donation methods&#xD;&#xA;and addresses. Donations are accepted in a number of other ways including&#xD;&#xA;checks, online payments and credit card donations. To donate, please&#xD;&#xA;visit: http://www.gutenberg.org/fundraising/donate&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 5.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;      General Information About Project Gutenberg™ electronic works.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Professor Michael S. Hart is the originator of the Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;concept of a library of electronic works that could be freely shared with&#xD;&#xA;anyone. For thirty years, he produced and distributed Project Gutenberg™&#xD;&#xA;eBooks with only a loose network of volunteer support.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg™ eBooks are often created from several printed editions,&#xD;&#xA;all of which are confirmed as Public Domain in the U.S. unless a copyright&#xD;&#xA;notice is included. Thus, we do not necessarily keep eBooks in compliance&#xD;&#xA;with any particular paper edition.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Each eBook is in a subdirectory of the same number as the eBook’s eBook&#xD;&#xA;number, often in several formats including plain vanilla ASCII, compressed&#xD;&#xA;(zipped), HTML and others.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Corrected _editions_ of our eBooks replace the old file and take over the&#xD;&#xA;old filename and etext number. The replaced older file is renamed.&#xD;&#xA;_Versions_ based on separate sources are treated as new eBooks receiving&#xD;&#xA;new filenames and etext numbers.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Most people start at our Web site which has the main PG search facility:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    http://www.gutenberg.org&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This Web site includes information about Project Gutenberg™, including how&#xD;&#xA;to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation,&#xD;&#xA;how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to subscribe to our email&#xD;&#xA;newsletter to hear about new eBooks.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***FINIS*** ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/11/independence.txt</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/11/constitution.txt</link>
            <description>﻿The Project Gutenberg EBook of The United States&#39; Constitution&#xD;&#xA;by  Founding Fathers&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Copyright laws are changing all over the world. Be sure to check the&#xD;&#xA;copyright laws for your country before downloading or redistributing&#xD;&#xA;this or any other Project Gutenberg eBook.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This header should be the first thing seen when viewing this Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg file.  Please do not remove it.  Do not change or edit the&#xD;&#xA;header without written permission.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Please read the &#34;legal small print,&#34; and other information about the&#xD;&#xA;eBook and Project Gutenberg at the bottom of this file.  Included is&#xD;&#xA;important information about your specific rights and restrictions in&#xD;&#xA;how the file may be used.  You can also find out about how to make a&#xD;&#xA;donation to Project Gutenberg, and how to get involved.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;**Welcome To The World of Free Plain Vanilla Electronic Texts**&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;**eBooks Readable By Both Humans and By Computers, Since 1971**&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*****These eBooks Were Prepared By Thousands of Volunteers!*****&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Title: The United States&#39; Constitution&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Author:  Founding Fathers&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Release Date: December, 1975  [EBook #5]&#xD;&#xA;[This file was first posted on August 19, 2003]&#xD;&#xA;[Previous update: April 14, 2006]&#xD;&#xA;[Last updated: April 1, 2015]&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Edition: 11&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Language: English&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*** START OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK, THE UNITED STATES&#39; CONSTITUTION ***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;All of the original Project Gutenberg Etexts from the&#xD;&#xA;1970&#39;s were produced in ALL CAPS, no lower case.  The&#xD;&#xA;computers we used then didn&#39;t have lower case at all.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;These original Project Gutenberg Etexts will be compiled into a file&#xD;&#xA;containing them all, in order to improve the content ratios of Etext&#xD;&#xA;to header material.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The following edition of The Consitution of the United States of America&#xD;&#xA;has been based on many hours of study of a variety of editions, and will&#xD;&#xA;include certain variant spellings, punctuation, and captialization as we&#xD;&#xA;have been able to reasonable ascertain belonged to the orginal.  In case&#xD;&#xA;of internal discrepancies in these matters, most or all have been left.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In our orginal editions the letters were all CAPITALS, and we did not do&#xD;&#xA;anything about capitalization, consistent or otherwise, nor with most of&#xD;&#xA;the punctuation, since we had limited punctionation in those days.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This document does NOT include the amendments, as the Bill of Rights was&#xD;&#xA;one of our earlier Project Gutenberg Etexts, and the others will be sent&#xD;&#xA;in a separate posting.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We would ask that any Consitutional scholars would please take a minute,&#xD;&#xA;or longer, to send us a note concerning possible corrections.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;THE CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, 1787&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We the people of the United States, in Order to form a more perfect Union,&#xD;&#xA;establish Justice, insure domestic Tranquility, provide for the common defence,&#xD;&#xA;promote the general Welfare, and secure the Blessings of Liberty to ourselves&#xD;&#xA;and our Posterity, do ordain and establish this Constitution for the&#xD;&#xA;United States of America.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Article 1&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1.  All legislative Powers herein granted shall be vested in a&#xD;&#xA;Congress of the United States, which shall consist of a Senate and&#xD;&#xA;House of Representatives.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 2.  The House of Representatives shall be composed of Members&#xD;&#xA;chosen every second Year by the People of the several States,&#xD;&#xA;and the electors in each State shall have the qualifications requisite&#xD;&#xA;for electors of the most numerous branch of the State legislature.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Person shall be a Representative who shall not have attained to the&#xD;&#xA;Age of twenty five Years, and been seven Years a citizen of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;and who shall not, when elected, be an Inhabitant of that State in which&#xD;&#xA;he shall be chosen.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Representatives and direct Taxes shall be apportioned among&#xD;&#xA;the several States which may be included within this Union,&#xD;&#xA;according to their respective Numbers, which shall be determined&#xD;&#xA;by adding to the whole number of free Persons, including those&#xD;&#xA;bound to Service for a Term of Years, and excluding Indians not taxed,&#xD;&#xA;three fifths of all other Persons.  The actual Enumeration shall be made&#xD;&#xA;within three Years after the first Meeting of the Congress of the&#xD;&#xA;United States, and within every subsequent Term of ten Years,&#xD;&#xA;in such Manner as they shall by law Direct.  The number of&#xD;&#xA;Representatives shall not exceed one for every thirty Thousand,&#xD;&#xA;but each State shall have at least one Representative;&#xD;&#xA;and until such enumeration shall be made, the State of New Hampshire&#xD;&#xA;shall be entitled to chuse three, Massachusetts eight, Rhode Island&#xD;&#xA;and Providence Plantations one, Connecticut five, New York six,&#xD;&#xA;New Jersey four, Pennsylvania eight, Delaware one, Maryland six,&#xD;&#xA;Virginia ten, North Carolina five, South Carolina five, and Georgia three.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;When vacancies happen in the Representation from any State, the Executive&#xD;&#xA;Authority thereof shall issue Writs of Election to fill such Vacancies.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The House of Representatives shall chuse their Speaker and other Officers;&#xD;&#xA;and shall have the sole Power of Impeachment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3.  The Senate of the United States shall be composed of&#xD;&#xA;two Senators from each State, chosen by the legislature thereof,&#xD;&#xA;for six Years; and each Senator shall have one Vote.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Immediately after they shall be assembled in Consequence of the first Election,&#xD;&#xA;they shall be divided as equally as may be into three Classes.  The Seats of&#xD;&#xA;the Senators of the first Class shall be vacated at the expiration of the&#xD;&#xA;second Year, of the second Class at the expiration of the fourth Year,&#xD;&#xA;and of the third Class at the expiration of the sixth Year, so that one third&#xD;&#xA;may be chosen every second Year; and if vacancies happen by Resignation,&#xD;&#xA;or otherwise, during the recess of the Legislature of any State,&#xD;&#xA;the Executive thereof may make temporary Appointments until the&#xD;&#xA;next meeting of the Legislature, which shall then fill such Vacancies.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No person shall be a Senator who shall not have attained to the Age of&#xD;&#xA;thirty Years, and been nine Years a Citizen of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;and who shall not, when elected, be an Inhabitant of that State&#xD;&#xA;for which he shall be chosen.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Vice-President of the United States shall be President of the Senate,&#xD;&#xA;but shall have no Vote, unless they be equally divided.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Senate shall choose their other Officers, and also a President&#xD;&#xA;pro tempore, in the Absence of the Vice-President, or when he shall&#xD;&#xA;exercise the Office of President of the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Senate shall have the sole Power to try all Impeachments.&#xD;&#xA;When sitting for that Purpose, they shall be on Oath or Affirmation.&#xD;&#xA;When the President of the United States is tried, the Chief Justice&#xD;&#xA;shall preside: And no Person shall be convicted without the Concurrence&#xD;&#xA;of two thirds of the Members present.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Judgment in cases of Impeachment shall not extend further than to removal&#xD;&#xA;from Office, and disqualification to hold and enjoy any Office of honor,&#xD;&#xA;Trust or Profit under the United States:  but the Party convicted shall&#xD;&#xA;nevertheless be liable and subject to Indictment, Trial, Judgment and&#xD;&#xA;Punishment, according to Law.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 4.  The Times, Places and Manner of holding Elections for Senators and&#xD;&#xA;Representatives, shall be prescribed in each State by the Legislature thereof;&#xD;&#xA;but the Congress may at any time by Law make or alter such Regulations,&#xD;&#xA;except as to the Places of chusing Senators.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Congress shall assemble at least once in every Year,&#xD;&#xA;and such Meeting shall be on the first Monday in December,&#xD;&#xA;unless they shall by law appoint a different Day.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 5.  Each House shall be the Judge of the Elections,&#xD;&#xA;Returns and Qualifications of its own Members, and a&#xD;&#xA;Majority of each shall constitute a Quorum to do Business;&#xD;&#xA;but a smaller Number may adjourn from day to day,&#xD;&#xA;and may be authorized to compel the Attendance of absent Members,&#xD;&#xA;in such Manner, and under such Penalties as each House may provide.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Each house may determine the Rules of its Proceedings,&#xD;&#xA;punish its Members for disorderly Behavior, and, with the&#xD;&#xA;Concurrence of two-thirds, expel a Member.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Each house shall keep a Journal of its Proceedings,&#xD;&#xA;and from time to time publish the same, excepting such Parts as may&#xD;&#xA;in their Judgment require Secrecy; and the Yeas and Nays of the&#xD;&#xA;Members of either House on any question shall, at the Desire of&#xD;&#xA;one fifth of those Present, be entered on the Journal.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Neither House, during the Session of Congress, shall, without the&#xD;&#xA;Consent of the other, adjourn for more than three days, nor to&#xD;&#xA;any other Place than that in which the two Houses shall be sitting.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 6.  The Senators and Representatives shall receive a Compensation&#xD;&#xA;for their Services, to be ascertained by Law, and paid out of the Treasury&#xD;&#xA;of the United States.  They shall in all Cases, except Treason, Felony and&#xD;&#xA;Breach of the Peace, be privileged from Arrest during their Attendance&#xD;&#xA;at the Session of their respective Houses, and in going to and returning&#xD;&#xA;from the same; and for any Speech or Debate in either House,&#xD;&#xA;they shall not be questioned in any other Place.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Senator or Representative shall, during the Time for which he was elected,&#xD;&#xA;be appointed to any civil Office under the authority of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;which shall have been created, or the Emoluments whereof shall have been&#xD;&#xA;increased during such time; and no Person holding any Office under the&#xD;&#xA;United States, shall be a Member of either House during his Continuance&#xD;&#xA;in Office.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 7.  All Bills for raising Revenue shall originate in the&#xD;&#xA;House of Representatives; but the Senate may propose or concur with&#xD;&#xA;Amendments as on other Bills.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Every Bill which shall have passed the House of Representatives and&#xD;&#xA;the Senate, shall, before it become a Law, be presented to the&#xD;&#xA;President of the United States; If he approve he shall sign it,&#xD;&#xA;but if not he shall return it, with his Objections to that House&#xD;&#xA;in which it shall have originated, who shall enter the Objections&#xD;&#xA;at large on their Journal, and proceed to reconsider it.&#xD;&#xA;If after such Reconsideration two thirds of that house&#xD;&#xA;shall agree to pass the Bill, it shall be sent,&#xD;&#xA;together with the Objections, to the other House, by which&#xD;&#xA;it shall likewise be reconsidered, and if approved by two thirds&#xD;&#xA;of that House, it shall become a law.  But in all such Cases&#xD;&#xA;the Votes of both Houses shall be determined by Yeas and Nays,&#xD;&#xA;and the Names of the Persons voting for and against the Bill shall be&#xD;&#xA;entered on the Journal of each House respectively.  If any Bill&#xD;&#xA;shall not be returned by the President within ten Days (Sundays excepted)&#xD;&#xA;after it shall have been presented to him, the Same shall be a Law,&#xD;&#xA;in like Manner as if he had signed it, unless the Congress by their&#xD;&#xA;Adjournment prevent its Return, in which case it shall not be a Law.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Every Order, Resolution, or Vote to which the Concurrence of the Senate&#xD;&#xA;and House of Representatives may be necessary (except on a question&#xD;&#xA;of Adjournment) shall be presented to the President of the United States;&#xD;&#xA;and before the Same shall take Effect, shall be approved by him,&#xD;&#xA;or being disapproved by him, shall be repassed by two thirds of&#xD;&#xA;the Senate and House of Representatives, according to the Rules&#xD;&#xA;and Limitations prescribed in the Case of a Bill.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 8.  The Congress shall have Power to lay and collect Taxes, Duties,&#xD;&#xA;Imposts and Excises, to pay the Debts and provide for the common Defence&#xD;&#xA;and general Welfare of the United States; but all Duties, Imposts and Excises&#xD;&#xA;shall be uniform throughout the United States;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To borrow Money on the credit of the United States;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To regulate Commerce with foreign Nations, and among the several States,&#xD;&#xA;and with the Indian Tribes;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To establish an uniform Rule of Naturalization, and uniform Laws&#xD;&#xA;on the subject of Bankruptcies throughout the United States;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To coin Money, regulate the Value thereof, and of foreign Coin,&#xD;&#xA;and fix the Standard of Weights and Measures;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To provide for the Punishment of counterfeiting the Securities&#xD;&#xA;and current Coin of the United States;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To establish Post Offices and Post Roads;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To promote the Progress of Science and useful Arts, by securing&#xD;&#xA;for limited Times to Authors and Inventors the exclusive Right&#xD;&#xA;to their respective Writings and Discoveries;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To constitute Tribunals inferior to the supreme Court;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To define and punish Piracies and Felonies committed on the high Seas,&#xD;&#xA;and Offenses against the Law of Nations;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To declare War, grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal,&#xD;&#xA;and make Rules concerning Captures on Land and Water;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To raise and support Armies, but no Appropriation of Money to that Use&#xD;&#xA;shall be for a longer term than two Years;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To provide and maintain a Navy;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To make Rules for the Government and Regulation of the land and naval Forces;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To provide for calling forth the Militia to execute the Laws of the Union,&#xD;&#xA;suppress Insurrections and repel Invasions;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To provide for organizing, arming, and disciplining, the Militia, and for&#xD;&#xA;governing such Part of them as may be employed in the Service of the&#xD;&#xA;United States, reserving to the States respectively, the Appointment&#xD;&#xA;of the Officers, and the Authority of training the militia according&#xD;&#xA;to the discipline prescribed by Congress;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To exercise exclusive Legislation in all Cases whatsoever,&#xD;&#xA;over such District (not exceeding ten Miles square) as may,&#xD;&#xA;by Cession of particular States, and the Acceptance of Congress,&#xD;&#xA;become the Seat of the Government of the United States, and to&#xD;&#xA;exercise like Authority over all Places purchased by the Consent&#xD;&#xA;of the Legislature of the State in which the Same shall be,&#xD;&#xA;for the Erection of Forts, Magazines, Arsenals, Dockyards,&#xD;&#xA;and other needful Buildings;--And&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To make all Laws which shall be necessary and proper for carrying&#xD;&#xA;into Execution the foregoing Powers, and all other Powers vested&#xD;&#xA;by this Constitution in the Government of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;or in any Department or Officer thereof.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 9.  The Migration or Importation of such Persons as any&#xD;&#xA;of the States now existing shall think proper to admit, shall not&#xD;&#xA;be prohibited by the Congress prior to the Year one thousand eight&#xD;&#xA;hundred and eight, but a Tax or Duty may be imposed on such Importation,&#xD;&#xA;not exceeding ten dollars for each Person.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Privilege of the Writ of Habeas Corpus shall not be suspended, unless&#xD;&#xA;when in Cases of Rebellion or Invasion the public Safety may require it.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Bill of Attainder or ex post facto Law shall be passed.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Capitation, or other direct, Tax shall be laid, unless in Proportion&#xD;&#xA;to the Census or Enumeration herein before directed to be taken.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Tax or Duty shall be laid on Articles exported from any State.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Preference shall be given by any Regulation of Commerce or Revenue&#xD;&#xA;to the Ports of one State over those of another: nor shall Vessels bound to,&#xD;&#xA;or from, one State, be obliged to enter, clear, or pay Duties in another.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Money shall be drawn from the Treasury, but in Consequence&#xD;&#xA;of Appropriations made by Law; and a regular Statement and Account&#xD;&#xA;of the Receipts and Expenditures of all public Money shall be&#xD;&#xA;published from time to time.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Title of Nobility shall be granted by the United States;&#xD;&#xA;and no Person holding any Office of Profit or Trust under them, shall,&#xD;&#xA;without the Consent of the Congress, accept of any present, Emolument,&#xD;&#xA;Office, or Title, of any kind whatever, from any King, Prince,&#xD;&#xA;or foreign State.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 10.  No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or&#xD;&#xA;Confederation; grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money;&#xD;&#xA;emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but gold and silver Coin a Tender&#xD;&#xA;in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law,&#xD;&#xA;or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any Title of Nobility.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No State shall, without the Consent of the Congress, lay any Imposts or Duties&#xD;&#xA;on Imports or Exports, except what may be absolutely necessary for executing&#xD;&#xA;it&#39;s inspection Laws: and the net Produce of all Duties and Imposts,&#xD;&#xA;laid by any State on Imports or Exports, shall be for the Use of the Treasury&#xD;&#xA;of the United States; and all such Laws shall be subject to the Revision&#xD;&#xA;and Controul of the Congress.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No State shall, without the Consent of Congress, lay any Duty of&#xD;&#xA;Tonnage, keep Troops, or Ships of War in time of Peace, enter into any&#xD;&#xA;Agreement or Compact with another State, or with a foreign Power, or&#xD;&#xA;engage in War, unless actually invaded, or in such imminent Danger&#xD;&#xA;as will not admit of delay.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE 2&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1.  The executive Power shall be vested in a President&#xD;&#xA;of the United States of America.  He shall hold his Office during&#xD;&#xA;the Term of four Years, and, together with the Vice President&#xD;&#xA;chosen for the same Term, be elected, as follows:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Each State shall appoint, in such Manner as the Legislature thereof may direct,&#xD;&#xA;a Number of Electors, equal to the whole Number of Senators and Representatives&#xD;&#xA;to which the State may be entitled in the Congress:  but no Senator or&#xD;&#xA;Representative, or Person holding an Office of Trust or Profit under&#xD;&#xA;the United States, shall be appointed an Elector.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Electors shall meet in their respective States, and vote by Ballot&#xD;&#xA;for two Persons, of whom one at least shall not be an Inhabitant of&#xD;&#xA;the same State with themselves.  And they shall make a List of&#xD;&#xA;all the Persons voted for, and of the Number of Votes for each;&#xD;&#xA;which List they shall sign and certify, and transmit sealed to&#xD;&#xA;the Seat of the Government of the United States, directed to the&#xD;&#xA;President of the Senate.  The President of the Senate shall,&#xD;&#xA;in the Presence of the Senate and House of Representatives,&#xD;&#xA;open all the Certificates, and the Votes shall then be counted.&#xD;&#xA;The Person having the greatest Number of Votes shall be the President,&#xD;&#xA;if such Number be a Majority of the whole Number of Electors appointed;&#xD;&#xA;and if there be more than one who have such Majority, and have an equal&#xD;&#xA;Number of votes, then the House of Representatives shall immediately&#xD;&#xA;chuse by Ballot one of them for President; and if no Person have&#xD;&#xA;a Majority, then from the five highest on the List the said House&#xD;&#xA;shall in like Manner chuse the President.  But in chusing the President,&#xD;&#xA;the Votes shall be taken by States, the Representation from each State&#xD;&#xA;having one Vote; a Quorum for this Purpose shall consist of a Member&#xD;&#xA;or Members from two thirds of the States, and a Majority of all the&#xD;&#xA;States shall be necessary to a Choice.  In every Case, after the Choice&#xD;&#xA;of the President, the Person having the greatest Number of Votes of&#xD;&#xA;the Electors shall be the Vice President.  But if there should remain&#xD;&#xA;two or more who have equal Votes, the Senate shall chuse from them&#xD;&#xA;by Ballot the Vice President.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Congress may determine the Time of chusing the Electors,&#xD;&#xA;and the Day on which they shall give their Votes; which Day&#xD;&#xA;shall be the same throughout the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No Person except a natural born Citizen, or a Citizen of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;at the time of the Adoption of this Constitution, shall be eligible to&#xD;&#xA;the Office of President; neither shall any Person be eligible to that&#xD;&#xA;Office who shall not have attained to the Age of thirty five Years,&#xD;&#xA;and been fourteen Years a Resident within the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In Case of the Removal of the President from Office, or of his Death,&#xD;&#xA;Resignation, or Inability to discharge the Powers and Duties of the&#xD;&#xA;said Office, the Same shall devolve on the Vice President, and the&#xD;&#xA;Congress may by Law provide for the Case of Removal, Death, Resignation&#xD;&#xA;or Inability, both of the President and Vice President, declaring what&#xD;&#xA;Officer shall then act as President, and such Officer shall act accordingly,&#xD;&#xA;until the Disability be removed, or a President shall be elected.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The President shall, at stated Times, receive for his Services,&#xD;&#xA;a Compensation, which shall neither be encreased nor diminished during&#xD;&#xA;the Period for which he shall have been elected, and he shall not receive&#xD;&#xA;within that Period any other Emolument from the United States, or any of them.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Before he enter on the Execution of his Office, he shall take the&#xD;&#xA;following Oath or Affirmation:--&#34;I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that&#xD;&#xA;I will faithfully execute the Office of President of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;and will to the best of my Ability, preserve, protect and defend the&#xD;&#xA;Constitution of the United States.&#34;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 2.  The President shall be Commander in Chief of the Army&#xD;&#xA;and Navy of the United States, and of the Militia of the several States,&#xD;&#xA;when called into the actual Service of the United States;&#xD;&#xA;he may require the Opinion, in writing, of the principal Officer&#xD;&#xA;in each of the executive Departments, upon any Subject relating to&#xD;&#xA;the Duties of their respective Offices, and he shall have Power&#xD;&#xA;to grant Reprieves and Pardons for Offenses against the United States,&#xD;&#xA;except in Cases of impeachment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;He shall have Power, by and with the Advice and Consent of the&#xD;&#xA;Senate, to make Treaties, provided two thirds of the Senators&#xD;&#xA;present concur; and he shall nominate, and by and with the Advice&#xD;&#xA;and Consent of the Senate, shall appoint Ambassadors, other public&#xD;&#xA;Ministers and Consuls, Judges of the supreme Court, and all other&#xD;&#xA;Officers of the United States, whose Appointments are not herein&#xD;&#xA;otherwise provided for, and which shall be established by Law:&#xD;&#xA;but the Congress may by Law vest the Appointment of such inferior Officers,&#xD;&#xA;as they think proper, in the President alone, in the Courts of Law,&#xD;&#xA;or in the Heads of Departments.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The President shall have Power to fill up all Vacancies that may happen&#xD;&#xA;during the Recess of the Senate, by granting Commissions which shall&#xD;&#xA;expire at the End of their next session.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3.  He shall from time to time give to the Congress&#xD;&#xA;Information of the State of the Union, and recommend to their&#xD;&#xA;Consideration such Measures as he shall judge necessary and expedient;&#xD;&#xA;he may, on extraordinary Occasions, convene both Houses, or either&#xD;&#xA;of them, and in Case of Disagreement between them, with Respect to&#xD;&#xA;the Time of Adjournment, he may adjourn them to such Time as he shall&#xD;&#xA;think proper; he shall receive Ambassadors and other public Ministers;&#xD;&#xA;he shall take Care that the Laws be faithfully executed, and shall&#xD;&#xA;Commission all the Officers of the United States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 4.  The President, Vice President and all civil Officers of the&#xD;&#xA;United States, shall be removed from Office on Impeachment for,&#xD;&#xA;and Conviction of, Treason, Bribery, or other high Crimes and Misdemeanors.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE THREE&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1.  The judicial Power of the United States, shall be vested&#xD;&#xA;in one supreme Court, and in such inferior Courts as the Congress may&#xD;&#xA;from time to time ordain and establish.  The Judges, both of the supreme&#xD;&#xA;and inferior Courts, shall hold their Offices during good behavior,&#xD;&#xA;and shall, at stated Times, receive for their Services, a Compensation,&#xD;&#xA;which shall not be diminished during their Continuance in Office.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 2.  The judicial Power shall extend to all Cases, in Law and Equity,&#xD;&#xA;arising under this Constitution, the Laws of the United States, and Treaties&#xD;&#xA;made, or which shall be made, under their Authority;--to all Cases affecting&#xD;&#xA;Ambassadors, other public Ministers and Consuls;--to all Cases of admiralty&#xD;&#xA;and maritime Jurisdiction;--to Controversies to which the United States&#xD;&#xA;shall be a Party;--to Controversies between two or more States;--between a&#xD;&#xA;State and Citizens of another State;--between Citizens of different States;&#xD;&#xA;--between Citizens of the same State claiming Lands under Grants of&#xD;&#xA;different States, and between a State, or the Citizens thereof,&#xD;&#xA;and foreign States, Citizens or Subjects.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In all cases affecting Ambassadors, other public Ministers and Consuls,&#xD;&#xA;and those in which a State shall be Party, the supreme Court shall have&#xD;&#xA;original Jurisdiction.  In all the other Cases before mentioned, the&#xD;&#xA;supreme Court shall have appellate Jurisdiction, both as to Law and Fact,&#xD;&#xA;with such Exceptions, and under such Regulations as the Congress shall make.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Trial of all Crimes, except in Cases of Impeachment, shall be by Jury;&#xD;&#xA;and such Trial shall be held in the State where the said Crimes shall&#xD;&#xA;have been committed; but when not committed within any State, the Trial&#xD;&#xA;shall be at such Place or Places as the Congress may by Law have directed.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3.  Treason against the United States, shall consist only in&#xD;&#xA;levying War against them, or in adhering to their Enemies, giving them&#xD;&#xA;Aid and Comfort.  No Person shall be convicted of Treason unless on&#xD;&#xA;the Testimony of two Witnesses to the same overt Act, or on Confession&#xD;&#xA;in open Court.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Congress shall have power to declare the punishment of Treason,&#xD;&#xA;but no Attainder of Treason shall work Corruption of Blood,&#xD;&#xA;or Forfeiture except during the Life of the Person attainted.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE FOUR&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 1.  Full Faith and Credit shall be given in each State to the&#xD;&#xA;public Acts, Records, and judicial Proceedings of every other State.&#xD;&#xA;And the Congress may by general Laws prescribe the Manner in which such Acts,&#xD;&#xA;Records, and Proceedings shall be proved, and the Effect thereof.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 2.  The Citizens of each State shall be entitled to all&#xD;&#xA;Privileges and Immunities of Citizens in the several States.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;A Person charged in any State with Treason, Felony, or other Crime,&#xD;&#xA;who shall flee from Justice, and be found in another State,&#xD;&#xA;shall on Demand of the executive Authority of the State from&#xD;&#xA;which he fled, be delivered up, to be removed to the State having&#xD;&#xA;Jurisdiction of the Crime.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;No person held to Service or Labor in one State, under the Laws thereof,&#xD;&#xA;escaping into another, shall, in Consequence of any Law or Regulation therein,&#xD;&#xA;be discharged from such Service or Labor, But shall be delivered up on Claim&#xD;&#xA;of the Party to whom such Service or Labor may be due.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 3.  New States may be admitted by the Congress into this Union;&#xD;&#xA;but no new States shall be formed or erected within the Jurisdiction&#xD;&#xA;of any other State; nor any State be formed by the Junction of two&#xD;&#xA;or more States, or Parts of States, without the Consent of the&#xD;&#xA;Legislatures of the States concerned as well as of the Congress.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Congress shall have Power to dispose of and make all needful Rules&#xD;&#xA;and Regulations respecting the Territory or other Property belonging&#xD;&#xA;to the United States; and nothing in this Constitution shall be so&#xD;&#xA;construed as to Prejudice any Claims of the United States,&#xD;&#xA;or of any particular State.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Section 4.  The United States shall guarantee to every State in this Union&#xD;&#xA;a Republican Form of Government, and shall protect each of them against&#xD;&#xA;Invasion; and on Application of the Legislature, or of the Executive&#xD;&#xA;(when the Legislature cannot be convened) against domestic Violence.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE FIVE&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Congress, whenever two thirds of both Houses shall deem it necessary,&#xD;&#xA;shall propose Amendments to this Constitution, or, on the Application of&#xD;&#xA;the Legislatures of two thirds of the several States, shall call a Convention&#xD;&#xA;for proposing Amendments, which, in either Case, shall be valid to all Intents&#xD;&#xA;and Purposes, as Part of this Constitution, when ratified by the Legislatures&#xD;&#xA;of three fourths of the several States, or by Conventions in three fourths&#xD;&#xA;thereof, as the one or the other Mode of Ratification may be proposed by&#xD;&#xA;the Congress; Provided that no Amendment which may be made prior to the&#xD;&#xA;Year one thousand eight hundred and eight shall in any Manner affect&#xD;&#xA;the first and fourth Clauses in the ninth Section of the first Article;&#xD;&#xA;and that no State, without its Consent, shall be deprived of it&#39;s&#xD;&#xA;equal Suffrage in the Senate.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE SIX&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;All Debts contracted and Engagements entered into, before the Adoption&#xD;&#xA;of this Constitution, shall be as valid against the United States&#xD;&#xA;under this Constitution, as under the Confederation.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This Constitution, and the Laws of the United States which shall be made&#xD;&#xA;in Pursuance thereof; and all Treaties made, or which shall be made,&#xD;&#xA;under the Authority of the United States, shall be the supreme&#xD;&#xA;Law of the Land; and the Judges in every State shall be bound thereby,&#xD;&#xA;any Thing in the Constitution or Laws of any State to the Contrary&#xD;&#xA;notwithstanding.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Senators and Representatives before mentioned, and the Members of the&#xD;&#xA;several State Legislatures, and all executive and judicial Officers,&#xD;&#xA;both of the United States and of the several States, shall be bound&#xD;&#xA;by Oath or Affirmation, to support this Constitution; but no religious&#xD;&#xA;Test shall ever be required as a Qualification to any Office or public Trust&#xD;&#xA;under the United States&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ARTICLE SEVEN&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Ratification of the Conventions of nine States, shall be sufficient for the&#xD;&#xA;Establishment of this Constitution between the States so ratifying the Same.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Done in Convention by the Unanimous Consent of the States present&#xD;&#xA;the Seventeenth Day of September in the Year of our Lord one&#xD;&#xA;thousand seven hundred and eighty seven and of the Independence of the&#xD;&#xA;United States of America the Twelfth        In Witness whereof We have&#xD;&#xA;hereunto subscribed our Names,&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Go. WASHINGTON--&#xD;&#xA;Presid. and deputy from Virginia&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;New Hampshire&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;John Langdon&#xD;&#xA;Nicholas Gilman&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Massachusetts&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Nathaniel Gorham&#xD;&#xA;Rufus King&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Connecticut&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Wm. Saml. Johnson&#xD;&#xA;Roger Sherman&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;New York&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Alexander Hamilton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;New Jersey&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Wil: Livingston&#xD;&#xA;David Brearley&#xD;&#xA;Wm. Paterson&#xD;&#xA;Jona: Dayton&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Pennsylvania&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;B Franklin&#xD;&#xA;Thomas Mifflin&#xD;&#xA;Robt Morris&#xD;&#xA;Geo. Clymer&#xD;&#xA;Thos FitzSimons&#xD;&#xA;Jared Ingersoll&#xD;&#xA;James Wilson&#xD;&#xA;Gouv Morris&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Delaware&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Geo: Read&#xD;&#xA;Gunning Bedford jun&#xD;&#xA;John Dickinson&#xD;&#xA;Richard Bassett&#xD;&#xA;Jaco: Broom&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Maryland&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;James Mchenry&#xD;&#xA;Dan of St Thos. Jenifer&#xD;&#xA;Danl Carroll&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Virginia&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;John Blair--&#xD;&#xA;James Madison Jr.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;North Carolina&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Wm. Blount&#xD;&#xA;Rich&#39;d Dobbs Spaight&#xD;&#xA;Hu Williamson&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;South Carolina&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;J. Rutledge&#xD;&#xA;Charles Cotesworth Pinckney&#xD;&#xA;Charles Pinckney&#xD;&#xA;Pierce Butler&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Georgia&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;William Few&#xD;&#xA;Abr Baldwin&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Attest:&#xD;&#xA;William Jackson, Secretary&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*** END OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK, THE UNITED STATES&#39; CONSTITUTION ***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;This file should be named 5.txt or 5.zip&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg eBooks are often created from several printed&#xD;&#xA;editions, all of which are confirmed as Public Domain in the US&#xD;&#xA;unless a copyright notice is included.  Thus, we usually do not&#xD;&#xA;keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper edition.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We are now trying to release all our eBooks one year in advance&#xD;&#xA;of the official release dates, leaving time for better editing.&#xD;&#xA;Please be encouraged to tell us about any error or corrections,&#xD;&#xA;even years after the official publication date.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Please note neither this listing nor its contents are final til&#xD;&#xA;midnight of the last day of the month of any such announcement.&#xD;&#xA;The official release date of all Project Gutenberg eBooks is at&#xD;&#xA;Midnight, Central Time, of the last day of the stated month.  A&#xD;&#xA;preliminary version may often be posted for suggestion, comment&#xD;&#xA;and editing by those who wish to do so.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Most people start at our Web sites at:&#xD;&#xA;http://gutenberg.net or&#xD;&#xA;http://promo.net/pg&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;These Web sites include award-winning information about Project&#xD;&#xA;Gutenberg, including how to donate, how to help produce our new&#xD;&#xA;eBooks, and how to subscribe to our email newsletter (free!).&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Those of you who want to download any eBook before announcement&#xD;&#xA;can get to them as follows, and just download by date.  This is&#xD;&#xA;also a good way to get them instantly upon announcement, as the&#xD;&#xA;indexes our cataloguers produce obviously take a while after an&#xD;&#xA;announcement goes out in the Project Gutenberg Newsletter.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;http://www.ibiblio.org/gutenberg/etext05 or&#xD;&#xA;ftp://ftp.ibiblio.org/pub/docs/books/gutenberg/etext05&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Or /etext04, 03, 02, 01, 00, 99, 98, 97, 96, 95, 94, 93, 92, 92,&#xD;&#xA;91 or 90&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Just search by the first five letters of the filename you want,&#xD;&#xA;as it appears in our Newsletters.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Information about Project Gutenberg (one page)&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We produce about two million dollars for each hour we work.  The&#xD;&#xA;time it takes us, a rather conservative estimate, is fifty hours&#xD;&#xA;to get any eBook selected, entered, proofread, edited, copyright&#xD;&#xA;searched and analyzed, the copyright letters written, etc.   Our&#xD;&#xA;projected audience is one hundred million readers.  If the value&#xD;&#xA;per text is nominally estimated at one dollar then we produce $2&#xD;&#xA;million dollars per hour in 2002 as we release over 100 new text&#xD;&#xA;files per month:  1240 more eBooks in 2001 for a total of 4000+&#xD;&#xA;We are already on our way to trying for 2000 more eBooks in 2002&#xD;&#xA;If they reach just 1-2% of the world&#39;s population then the total&#xD;&#xA;will reach over half a trillion eBooks given away by year&#39;s end.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Goal of Project Gutenberg is to Give Away 1 Trillion eBooks!&#xD;&#xA;This is ten thousand titles each to one hundred million readers,&#xD;&#xA;which is only about 4% of the present number of computer users.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Here is the briefest record of our progress (* means estimated):&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;eBooks Year Month&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;    1  1971 July&#xD;&#xA;   10  1991 January&#xD;&#xA;  100  1994 January&#xD;&#xA; 1000  1997 August&#xD;&#xA; 1500  1998 October&#xD;&#xA; 2000  1999 December&#xD;&#xA; 2500  2000 December&#xD;&#xA; 3000  2001 November&#xD;&#xA; 4000  2001 October/November&#xD;&#xA; 6000  2002 December*&#xD;&#xA; 9000  2003 November*&#xD;&#xA;10000  2004 January*&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation has been created&#xD;&#xA;to secure a future for Project Gutenberg into the next millennium.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We need your donations more than ever!&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;As of February, 2002, contributions are being solicited from people&#xD;&#xA;and organizations in: Alabama, Alaska, Arkansas, Connecticut,&#xD;&#xA;Delaware, District of Columbia, Florida, Georgia, Hawaii, Illinois,&#xD;&#xA;Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Massachusetts,&#xD;&#xA;Michigan, Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New&#xD;&#xA;Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, North Carolina, Ohio,&#xD;&#xA;Oklahoma, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, South Carolina, South&#xD;&#xA;Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah, Vermont, Virginia, Washington, West&#xD;&#xA;Virginia, Wisconsin, and Wyoming.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We have filed in all 50 states now, but these are the only ones&#xD;&#xA;that have responded.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;As the requirements for other states are met, additions to this list&#xD;&#xA;will be made and fund raising will begin in the additional states.&#xD;&#xA;Please feel free to ask to check the status of your state.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;In answer to various questions we have received on this:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We are constantly working on finishing the paperwork to legally&#xD;&#xA;request donations in all 50 states.  If your state is not listed and&#xD;&#xA;you would like to know if we have added it since the list you have,&#xD;&#xA;just ask.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;While we cannot solicit donations from people in states where we are&#xD;&#xA;not yet registered, we know of no prohibition against accepting&#xD;&#xA;donations from donors in these states who approach us with an offer to&#xD;&#xA;donate.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;International donations are accepted, but we don&#39;t know ANYTHING about&#xD;&#xA;how to make them tax-deductible, or even if they CAN be made&#xD;&#xA;deductible, and don&#39;t have the staff to handle it even if there are&#xD;&#xA;ways.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Donations by check or money order may be sent to:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA; PROJECT GUTENBERG LITERARY ARCHIVE FOUNDATION&#xD;&#xA; 809 North 1500 West&#xD;&#xA; Salt Lake City, UT 84116&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Contact us if you want to arrange for a wire transfer or payment&#xD;&#xA;method other than by check or money order.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation has been approved by&#xD;&#xA;the US Internal Revenue Service as a 501(c)(3) organization with EIN&#xD;&#xA;[Employee Identification Number] 64-622154.  Donations are&#xD;&#xA;tax-deductible to the maximum extent permitted by law.  As fund-raising&#xD;&#xA;requirements for other states are met, additions to this list will be&#xD;&#xA;made and fund-raising will begin in the additional states.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We need your donations more than ever!&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;You can get up to date donation information online at:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;http://www.gutenberg.net/donation.html&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If you can&#39;t reach Project Gutenberg,&#xD;&#xA;you can always email directly to:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Michael S. Hart &lt;hart@pobox.com&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Prof. Hart will answer or forward your message.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;We would prefer to send you information by email.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;**The Legal Small Print**&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;(Three Pages)&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;***START**THE SMALL PRINT!**FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN EBOOKS**START***&#xD;&#xA;Why is this &#34;Small Print!&#34; statement here? You know: lawyers.&#xD;&#xA;They tell us you might sue us if there is something wrong with&#xD;&#xA;your copy of this eBook, even if you got it for free from&#xD;&#xA;someone other than us, and even if what&#39;s wrong is not our&#xD;&#xA;fault. So, among other things, this &#34;Small Print!&#34; statement&#xD;&#xA;disclaims most of our liability to you. It also tells you how&#xD;&#xA;you may distribute copies of this eBook if you want to.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*BEFORE!* YOU USE OR READ THIS EBOOK&#xD;&#xA;By using or reading any part of this PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm&#xD;&#xA;eBook, you indicate that you understand, agree to and accept&#xD;&#xA;this &#34;Small Print!&#34; statement. If you do not, you can receive&#xD;&#xA;a refund of the money (if any) you paid for this eBook by&#xD;&#xA;sending a request within 30 days of receiving it to the person&#xD;&#xA;you got it from. If you received this eBook on a physical&#xD;&#xA;medium (such as a disk), you must return it with your request.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;ABOUT PROJECT GUTENBERG-TM EBOOKS&#xD;&#xA;This PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm eBook, like most PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm eBooks,&#xD;&#xA;is a &#34;public domain&#34; work distributed by Professor Michael S. Hart&#xD;&#xA;through the Project Gutenberg Association (the &#34;Project&#34;).&#xD;&#xA;Among other things, this means that no one owns a United States copyright&#xD;&#xA;on or for this work, so the Project (and you!) can copy and&#xD;&#xA;distribute it in the United States without permission and&#xD;&#xA;without paying copyright royalties. Special rules, set forth&#xD;&#xA;below, apply if you wish to copy and distribute this eBook&#xD;&#xA;under the &#34;PROJECT GUTENBERG&#34; trademark.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Please do not use the &#34;PROJECT GUTENBERG&#34; trademark to market&#xD;&#xA;any commercial products without permission.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;To create these eBooks, the Project expends considerable&#xD;&#xA;efforts to identify, transcribe and proofread public domain&#xD;&#xA;works. Despite these efforts, the Project&#39;s eBooks and any&#xD;&#xA;medium they may be on may contain &#34;Defects&#34;. Among other&#xD;&#xA;things, Defects may take the form of incomplete, inaccurate or&#xD;&#xA;corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other&#xD;&#xA;intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged&#xD;&#xA;disk or other eBook medium, a computer virus, or computer&#xD;&#xA;codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;LIMITED WARRANTY; DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES&#xD;&#xA;But for the &#34;Right of Replacement or Refund&#34; described below,&#xD;&#xA;[1] Michael Hart and the Foundation (and any other party you may&#xD;&#xA;receive this eBook from as a PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm eBook) disclaims&#xD;&#xA;all liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including&#xD;&#xA;legal fees, and [2] YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE OR&#xD;&#xA;UNDER STRICT LIABILITY, OR FOR BREACH OF WARRANTY OR CONTRACT,&#xD;&#xA;INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE&#xD;&#xA;OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES, EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE&#xD;&#xA;POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If you discover a Defect in this eBook within 90 days of&#xD;&#xA;receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money (if any)&#xD;&#xA;you paid for it by sending an explanatory note within that&#xD;&#xA;time to the person you received it from. If you received it&#xD;&#xA;on a physical medium, you must return it with your note, and&#xD;&#xA;such person may choose to alternatively give you a replacement&#xD;&#xA;copy. If you received it electronically, such person may&#xD;&#xA;choose to alternatively give you a second opportunity to&#xD;&#xA;receive it electronically.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;THIS EBOOK IS OTHERWISE PROVIDED TO YOU &#34;AS-IS&#34;. NO OTHER&#xD;&#xA;WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, ARE MADE TO YOU AS&#xD;&#xA;TO THE EBOOK OR ANY MEDIUM IT MAY BE ON, INCLUDING BUT NOT&#xD;&#xA;LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A&#xD;&#xA;PARTICULAR PURPOSE.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;Some states do not allow disclaimers of implied warranties or&#xD;&#xA;the exclusion or limitation of consequential damages, so the&#xD;&#xA;above disclaimers and exclusions may not apply to you, and you&#xD;&#xA;may have other legal rights.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;INDEMNITY&#xD;&#xA;You will indemnify and hold Michael Hart, the Foundation,&#xD;&#xA;and its trustees and agents, and any volunteers associated&#xD;&#xA;with the production and distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm&#xD;&#xA;texts harmless, from all liability, cost and expense, including&#xD;&#xA;legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of the&#xD;&#xA;following that you do or cause:  [1] distribution of this eBook,&#xD;&#xA;[2] alteration, modification, or addition to the eBook,&#xD;&#xA;or [3] any Defect.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;DISTRIBUTION UNDER &#34;PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm&#34;&#xD;&#xA;You may distribute copies of this eBook electronically, or by&#xD;&#xA;disk, book or any other medium if you either delete this&#xD;&#xA;&#34;Small Print!&#34; and all other references to Project Gutenberg,&#xD;&#xA;or:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;[1]  Only give exact copies of it.  Among other things, this&#xD;&#xA;     requires that you do not remove, alter or modify the&#xD;&#xA;     eBook or this &#34;small print!&#34; statement.  You may however,&#xD;&#xA;     if you wish, distribute this eBook in machine readable&#xD;&#xA;     binary, compressed, mark-up, or proprietary form,&#xD;&#xA;     including any form resulting from conversion by word&#xD;&#xA;     processing or hypertext software, but only so long as&#xD;&#xA;     *EITHER*:&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;     [*]  The eBook, when displayed, is clearly readable, and&#xD;&#xA;          does *not* contain characters other than those&#xD;&#xA;          intended by the author of the work, although tilde&#xD;&#xA;          (~), asterisk (*) and underline (_) characters may&#xD;&#xA;          be used to convey punctuation intended by the&#xD;&#xA;          author, and additional characters may be used to&#xD;&#xA;          indicate hypertext links; OR&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;     [*]  The eBook may be readily converted by the reader at&#xD;&#xA;          no expense into plain ASCII, EBCDIC or equivalent&#xD;&#xA;          form by the program that displays the eBook (as is&#xD;&#xA;          the case, for instance, with most word processors);&#xD;&#xA;          OR&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;     [*]  You provide, or agree to also provide on request at&#xD;&#xA;          no additional cost, fee or expense, a copy of the&#xD;&#xA;          eBook in its original plain ASCII form (or in EBCDIC&#xD;&#xA;          or other equivalent proprietary form).&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;[2]  Honor the eBook refund and replacement provisions of this&#xD;&#xA;     &#34;Small Print!&#34; statement.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;[3]  Pay a trademark license fee to the Foundation of 20% of the&#xD;&#xA;     gross profits you derive calculated using the method you&#xD;&#xA;     already use to calculate your applicable taxes.  If you&#xD;&#xA;     don&#39;t derive profits, no royalty is due.  Royalties are&#xD;&#xA;     payable to &#34;Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation&#34;&#xD;&#xA;     the 60 days following each date you prepare (or were&#xD;&#xA;     legally required to prepare) your annual (or equivalent&#xD;&#xA;     periodic) tax return.  Please contact us beforehand to&#xD;&#xA;     let us know your plans and to work out the details.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;WHAT IF YOU *WANT* TO SEND MONEY EVEN IF YOU DON&#39;T HAVE TO?&#xD;&#xA;Project Gutenberg is dedicated to increasing the number of&#xD;&#xA;public domain and licensed works that can be freely distributed&#xD;&#xA;in machine readable form.&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;The Project gratefully accepts contributions of money, time,&#xD;&#xA;public domain materials, or royalty free copyright licenses.&#xD;&#xA;Money should be paid to the:&#xD;&#xA;&#34;Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.&#34;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;If you are interested in contributing scanning equipment or&#xD;&#xA;software or other items, please contact Michael Hart at:&#xD;&#xA;hart@pobox.com&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;[Portions of this eBook&#39;s header and trailer may be reprinted only&#xD;&#xA;when distributed free of all fees.  Copyright (C) 2001, 2002 by&#xD;&#xA;Michael S. Hart.  Project Gutenberg is a TradeMark and may not be&#xD;&#xA;used in any sales of Project Gutenberg eBooks or other materials be&#xD;&#xA;they hardware or software or any other related product without&#xD;&#xA;express permission.]&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;*END THE SMALL PRINT! FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN EBOOKS*Ver.02/11/02*END* ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/11/constitution.txt</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Pandoc &amp; Metadata</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/11/Pandoc-Metadata.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Pandoc &amp; Metadata &#xA;=================&#xA;&#xA;Pandoc supports three ways of providing metadata to its template&#xA;engine.&#xA;&#xA;1. Front matter&#xA;2. Command line optional metadata&#xA;3. A JSON metadata file.&#xA;&#xA;Front matter&#xA;------------ ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/11/Pandoc-Metadata.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title></title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/09/Pandoc-Partials.txt</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Pandoc Partial Templates&#xA;========================&#xA;&#xA;Most people know about [Pandoc](https://pandoc.org/) from its&#xA;fantastic ability to convert various markup formats from one to&#xA;another. A little less obvious is Pandoc can be a template engine&#xA;for rendering static websites allowing you full control over the&#xA;rendered content.&#xA;&#xA;The main Pandoc documentation of the template engine can be found&#xA;in the [User Guide](https://pandoc.org/MANUAL.html#templates).&#xA;The documentation is complete in terms of describing the template&#xA;capabilities but lacks a tutorial for using as a replacement for more&#xA;ambitious rendering systems like [Jekyll](https://jekyllrb.com/) or&#xA;[Hugo](https://gohugo.io/). Pandoc takes a vary direct approach and&#xA;can be deceptively simple to implement.&#xA;&#xA;Use your own template&#xA;--------------------- ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/09/Pandoc-Partials.txt</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Software Tools, Filters</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/10/31/Filters.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Software Tools, Filters&#xA;=======================&#xA;&#xA;Overview&#xA;--------&#xA;&#xA;This post is the second in a series revisiting the programs&#xA;described in the 1981 book by Brian W. Kernighan and P. J.&#xA;Plauger&#39;s called [Software Tools in Pascal](https://archive.org/details/softwaretoolsinp00kern). The book is available from the&#xA;[Open Library](https://openlibrary.org/) and physical copies&#xA;are still (2020) commonly available from used book sellers.&#xA;The book was an late 20th century text on creating portable&#xA;command line programs using ISO standard Pascal of the era.&#xA;&#xA;In this chapter K &amp; P focuses on developing the idea of filters.&#xA;Filters are programs which typically process standard input, do&#xA;some sort of transformation or calculation and write to standard&#xA;output.  They are intended to work either standalone or in a pipeline&#xA;to solve more complex problems. I like to think of filters as&#xA;software [LEGO](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lego).&#xA;Filter programs can be &#34;snapped&#34; together creating simple shapes&#xA;data shapes or combined to for complex compositions. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/10/31/Filters.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Assembling Pages</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/10/19/Assemble-pages.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Assembling pages&#xA;================&#xA;&#xA;This is the thirteenth post in the [Mostly Oberon](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;Pandoc and JSON&#xA;---------------&#xA;&#xA;I use [Pandoc](https://pandoc.org) to process Markdown documents. I like to keep my&#xA;front matter in JSON rather than Pandoc&#39;s YAML. Fortunately Pandoc&#xA;does support working with JSON as a metadata file include. Normally I would&#xA;manually split the JSON front matter and the rest of the markup into two&#xA;separate files, then process with Pandoc and other tooling like&#xA;[LunrJS](https://lunrjs.com). [AssemblePage](AssemblePage.Mod) automates this&#xA;process. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/10/19/Assemble-pages.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Pandoc Partials</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/11/09/Pandoc-Partials.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Pandoc Partial Templates&#xA;========================&#xA;&#xA;Most people know about [Pandoc](https://pandoc.org/) from its&#xA;fantastic ability to convert various markup formats from one to&#xA;another. A little less obvious is Pandoc can be a template engine&#xA;for rendering static websites allowing you full control over the&#xA;rendered content.&#xA;&#xA;The main Pandoc documentation of the template engine can be found&#xA;in the [User Guide](https://pandoc.org/MANUAL.html#templates).&#xA;The documentation is complete in terms of describing the template&#xA;capabilities but lacks a tutorial for using as a replacement for more&#xA;ambitious rendering systems like [Jekyll](https://jekyllrb.com/) or&#xA;[Hugo](https://gohugo.io/). Pandoc takes a vary direct approach and&#xA;can be deceptively simple to implement.&#xA;&#xA;Use your own template&#xA;--------------------- ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/11/09/Pandoc-Partials.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon to Markdown</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Oberon to Markdown&#xA;==================&#xA;&#xA;This is the twelfth post in the [Mostly Oberon](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;A nice feature of Oberon&#xA;------------------------&#xA;&#xA;Oberon source code has a very nice property in that anything&#xA;after the closing end statement is ignored by the compiler.&#xA;This makes it a nice place to write documentation, program&#xA;notes and other ideas. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Software Tools, Getting Started</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/09/29/Software-Tools-1.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Software Tools, Getting Started&#xA;&#xA;## Overview&#xA;&#xA;This post is the first in a series revisiting the&#xA;programs described in the 1981 book by Brian W. Kernighan and&#xA;P. J. Plauger&#39;s called [Software Tools in Pascal](https://archive.org/details/softwaretoolsinp00kern).&#xA;The book is available from the [Open Library](https://openlibrary.org/)&#xA;and physical copies are still (2020) commonly available from used book&#xA;sellers.  The book was an early text on creating portable command&#xA;line programs.&#xA;&#xA;In this series I present the K &amp; P (i.e. Software Tools in Pascal)&#xA;programs re-implemented in Oberon-7. I have testing my implementations&#xA;using Karl Landström&#39;s [OBNC](http://miasap.se/obnc/)&#xA;compiler and his implementation of the Oakwood Guide&#39;s modules&#xA;for portable Oberon programs. Karl also provides a few additional&#xA;modules for working in a POSIX environment (e.g. BSD, macOS, Linux,&#xA;Windows 10 with Linux subsystem). I have also tested these&#xA;programs with Mike Spivey&#39;s [Oxford Oberon Compiler](http://spivey.oriel.ox.ac.uk/corner/Oxford_Oberon-2_compiler) an aside&#xA;from the differences file extensions that both compilers use&#xA;the source code works the same. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/09/29/Software-Tools-1.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon to Markdown</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Oberon to Markdown&#xA;==================&#xA;&#xA;This is the twelfth post in the [Mostly Oberon](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;A nice feature of Oberon&#xA;------------------------&#xA;&#xA;Oberon source code has a very nice property in that anything&#xA;after the closing end statement is ignored by the compiler.&#xA;This makes it a nice place to write documentation, program&#xA;notes and other ideas. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Software Tools, Getting Started</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/09/29/Software-Tools-1.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Software Tools, Getting Started&#xA;&#xA;## Overview&#xA;&#xA;This post is the first in a series revisiting the&#xA;programs described in the 1981 book by Brian W. Kernighan and&#xA;P. J. Plauger&#39;s called [Software Tools in Pascal](https://archive.org/details/softwaretoolsinp00kern).&#xA;The book is available from the [Open Library](https://openlibrary.org/)&#xA;and physical copies are still (2020) commonly available from used book&#xA;sellers.  The book was an early text on creating portable command&#xA;line programs.&#xA;&#xA;In this series I present the K &amp; P (i.e. Software Tools in Pascal)&#xA;programs re-implemented in Oberon-7. I have testing my implementations&#xA;using Karl Landström&#39;s [OBNC](http://miasap.se/obnc/)&#xA;compiler and his implementation of the Oakwood Guide&#39;s modules&#xA;for portable Oberon programs. Karl also provides a few additional&#xA;modules for working in a POSIX environment (e.g. BSD, macOS, Linux,&#xA;Windows 10 with Linux subsystem). I have also tested these&#xA;programs with Mike Spivey&#39;s [Oxford Oberon Compiler](http://spivey.oriel.ox.ac.uk/corner/Oxford_Oberon-2_compiler) an aside&#xA;from the differences file extensions that both compilers use&#xA;the source code works the same. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/09/29/Software-Tools-1.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Portable Oberon 7</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/08/15/Portable-Oberon-7.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Portable Oberon 7&#xA;&#xA;## using OBNC modules&#xA;&#xA;This is the eleventh post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the&#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;## Working with standard input ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/08/15/Portable-Oberon-7.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon to Markdown</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Oberon to Markdown&#xA;==================&#xA;&#xA;This is the twelfth post in the [Mostly Oberon](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;A nice feature of Oberon&#xA;------------------------&#xA;&#xA;Oberon source code has a very nice property in that anything&#xA;after the closing end statement is ignored by the compiler.&#xA;This makes it a nice place to write documentation, program&#xA;notes and other ideas. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/10/03/Oberon-to-markdown.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Portable Oberon 7</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/08/15/Portable-Oberon-7.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Portable Oberon 7&#xA;&#xA;## using OBNC modules&#xA;&#xA;This is the eleventh post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the&#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;## Working with standard input ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/08/15/Portable-Oberon-7.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Words Matter</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/07/08/words-matter.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Words Matter&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-07-08&#xA;&#xA;UPDATE (2020-08-15, RSD): When I added a post today I was VERY pleased to &#xA;to see that GitHub now allows me to publish my blog via the &#34;main&#34; branch.&#xA;It&#39;s nice to see the change in the words we use.&#xA;&#xA;**Why does software development use the vocabulary of slavery and&#xA;Jim Crow to describe our creations?** What we call things matters.&#xA;This is especially true of the words we use day to day without thinking. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/07/08/words-matter.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Procedures in records</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/07/07/Procedures-in-records.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Procedures in records&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-07-07&#xA;&#xA;This is the tenth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the &#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;In my last post I looked at how Oberon-7 supports the passing of procedures as parameters in a procedure. In this one I am looking at how we can&#xA;include procedures as a part of an Oberon RECORD. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/07/07/Procedures-in-records.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Procedures as parameters</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/06/20/Procedures-as-parameters.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Procedures as parameters&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-06-20&#xA;&#xA;This is the ninth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the &#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;Oberon-7 supports the passing of procedures as parameters in a procedure. &#xA;Let&#39;s create a module name [Noises.Mod](Noises.Mod) to explore this. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/06/20/Procedures-as-parameters.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Procedures in records</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/07/07/Procedures-in-records.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Procedures in records&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-07-07&#xA;&#xA;This is the tenth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the &#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;In my last post I looked at how Oberon-7 supports the passing of procedures as parameters in a procedure. In this one I am looking at how we can&#xA;include procedures as a part of an Oberon RECORD. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/07/07/Procedures-in-records.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Dynamic types</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/05/25/Dynamic-types.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Dynamic types&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-05-25&#xA;&#xA;This is the eighth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html)&#xA;series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, &#xA;Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;## Dynamic Types in Oberon ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/05/25/Dynamic-types.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Procedures as parameters</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/06/20/Procedures-as-parameters.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Procedures as parameters&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-06-20&#xA;&#xA;This is the ninth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series.&#xA;Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the &#xA;various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;Oberon-7 supports the passing of procedures as parameters in a procedure. &#xA;Let&#39;s create a module name [Noises.Mod](Noises.Mod) to explore this. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/06/20/Procedures-as-parameters.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon-7 and the file system</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/05/09/Oberon-7-and-the-filesystem.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Oberon-7 and the file system&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-05-09&#xA;&#xA;This is the seventh post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;## Working with files in Oberon-7 ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/05/09/Oberon-7-and-the-filesystem.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Compiling OBNC on macOS</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/05/06/Compiling-OBNC-on-macOS.md</link>
            <description>Compiling OBNC on macOS &#xA;=======================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-05-06&#xA;&#xA;This is the sixth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;Compiling OBNC v0.16.1 on macOS (10.13.6) using MacPorts (2.6.2) &#xA;is straight forward if you have the required dependencies and &#xA;environment setup up. Below are my notes to get everything working.&#xA;&#xA;## Prerequisites ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/05/06/Compiling-OBNC-on-macOS.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Combining Oberon-7 and C with OBNC</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/05/01/Combining-Oberon-and-C.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Combining Oberon-7 and C with OBNC&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-05-01&#xA;&#xA;This is the fifth post in the [Mostly Oberon](../../04/11/Mostly-Oberon.html)&#xA;series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon&#xA;Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will&#xA;inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;In my day job I write allot of code in Go and&#xA;orchestration code in Python.  It&#39;s nice having&#xA;the convenience of combining code written one&#xA;language with an another.  You can do the same&#xA;with [OBNC](https://miasap.se/obnc/).  The OBNC&#xA;compiler supports inclusion of C code in a&#xA;straight forward manner. In fact Karl&#39;s compiler&#xA;will generate the C file for you! ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/05/01/Combining-Oberon-and-C.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon Loops and Conditions</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/04/19/Mostly-Oberon-Loops-and-Conditions.md</link>
            <description>Oberon Loops and Conditions&#xA;===========================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-04-19&#xA;&#xA;This is the four post in the [Mostly Oberon](../11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit holes I will inevitably fall into.&#xA;&#xA;## Data Flow&#xA;&#xA;Oberon is a small systems language and while it is minimalist.&#xA;It provides you with the necessary primitives to get things done.&#xA;I&#39;ve touched on code organization, basic types and basic type&#xA;extensions in the previous articles.  I have shown the basic&#xA;control statements but have not talked about them yet. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/04/19/Mostly-Oberon-Loops-and-Conditions.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon Basic Types</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/04/18/Mostly-Oberon-Basic-Types.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Oberon Basic Types&#xA;==================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-04-18&#xA;&#xA;This is the third post in the [Mostly Oberon](../11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit wholes I inevitably fell into.&#xA;&#xA;## Simple Types ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/04/18/Mostly-Oberon-Basic-Types.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Oberon Modules and Procedures</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/04/12/Mostly-Oberon-Modules.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Oberon Modules and Procedures&#xA;=============================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-04-12&#xA;&#xA;This is the second post in the [Mostly Oberon](../11/Mostly-Oberon.html) series. Mostly Oberon documents my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit wholes I inevitably fell into.&#xA;&#xA;## Modules ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/04/12/Mostly-Oberon-Modules.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Mostly Oberon</title>
            <link>/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;Mostly Oberon&#xA;=============&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2020-04-11&#xA;&#xA;**Mostly Oberon** is a series of blog posts documenting my exploration of the Oberon Language, Oberon System and the various rabbit wholes I inevitably fell into.&#xA;&#xA;## Overview ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2020/04/11/Mostly-Oberon.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>FreeDOS 1.2 to Oberon System 3</title>
            <link>/blog/2019/07/28/freedos-to-oberon-system-3.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;FreeDOS to Oberon System 3&#xA;==========================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2019-07-28&#xA;&#xA;&gt;    UPDATE: (2021-02-19, RSD) Under VirtualBox 6.1 these&#xA;&gt;    instructions fail. For VirtualBox I&#39;ve used FreeDOS 1.3rc3&#xA;&gt;    Live CD installing the &#34;Plain DOS&#34; without problems.&#xA;&#xA;What follows are notes on getting a FreeDOS 1.2[^1] and &#xA;then Native Oberon[^2] running under VirtualBox 6.0. You might &#xA;wonder why these two are together. While it was&#xA;easy to run the Native Oberon installation process that process&#xA;assumes you have a properly partitioned hard disk and VirtualBox&#xA;seems to skip that process. I found taking advantage of FreeDOS&#xA;simplified things for me. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2019/07/28/freedos-to-oberon-system-3.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Review: Software Tools in Pascal</title>
            <link>/blog/2018/07/22/software-tools-in-pascal.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Review: Software Tools in Pascal&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2018-07-22&#xA;(updated: 2018-07-22, 1:39 pm, PDT)&#xA;&#xA;This book is by Brian W. Kernighan and P. J. Plauger. It is an&#xA;example of the type of books I find I re-read and want in my&#xA;personal library. The book covers software construction through &#xA;a series of programs written in pascal. It is about how these &#xA;programs work, how to approach problems and write sound software.&#xA;I was surprised I did not know about this book when I was browsing &#xA;the [Open Library](https://openlibrary.org) this weekend.  While &#xA;Pascal was a popular in the 1980&#39;s it has faded for most people in the &#xA;early 21st century.  This review maybe a small bit of nostalgia. &#xA;On the other hand I suspect &#xA;[&#34;Software Tools in Pascal&#34;](https://openlibrary.org/books/OL4258115M/Software_tools_in_Pascal)&#xA;is one of the short list of computer books that will remain useful&#xA;over the long run.&#xA;&#xA;## What&#39;s covered ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2018/07/22/software-tools-in-pascal.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Accessing Go from Julia</title>
            <link>/blog/2018/03/11/accessing-go-from-julia.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Accessing Go from Julia&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2018-03-11&#xA;&#xA;The problem: I&#39;ve started exploring Julia and I would like to leverage existing&#xA;code I&#39;ve written in Go. Essentially this is a revisit to the problem in my&#xA;last post [Go based Python Modules](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2018/02/24/go-based-python-modules.html) &#xA;but with the language pairing of Go and Julia.&#xA;&#xA;## Example 1, libtwice.go, libtwice.jl and libtwice_test.jl ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2018/03/11/accessing-go-from-julia.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Go based Python modules</title>
            <link>/blog/2018/02/24/go-based-python-modules.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Go based Python modules&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2018-02-24&#xA;&#xA;The problem: I have written a number of Go packages at work.&#xA;My colleagues know Python and I&#39;d like them to be able to use the&#xA;packages without resorting to system calls from Python to the&#xA;command line implementations. The solution is create a C-Shared&#xA;library from my Go packages, using Go&#39;s _C_ package and combine it&#xA;with Python&#39;s _ctypes_ package.  What follows is a series of &#xA;simple recipes I used to understand the details of how that worked.&#xA;&#xA;## Example 1, libtwice.go and twice.py ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2018/02/24/go-based-python-modules.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Go, Bleve and Library oriented software</title>
            <link>/blog/2018/02/19/go-bleve-and-libraries.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Go, Bleve and Library oriented software&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2018-02-19&#xA;(updated: 2018-02-22)&#xA;&#xA;In 2016, Stephen Davison, asked me, &#34;Why use Go and Blevesearch for&#xA;our library projects?&#34; After our conversation I wrote up some notes so&#xA;I would remember. It is now 2018 and I am revising these notes. I&#xA;think our choice paid off.  What follows is the current state of my&#xA;reflection on the background, rational, concerns, and risk mitigation&#xA;strategies so far for using [Go](https://golang.org) and&#xA;[Blevesearch](https://blevesearch.com) for Caltech Library projects.&#xA;&#xA;## Background ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2018/02/19/go-bleve-and-libraries.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Accessing Go from Julia</title>
            <link>/blog/2018/03/11/accessing-go-from-julia.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Accessing Go from Julia&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel, 2018-03-11&#xA;&#xA;The problem: I&#39;ve started exploring Julia and I would like to leverage existing&#xA;code I&#39;ve written in Go. Essentially this is a revisit to the problem in my&#xA;last post [Go based Python Modules](https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2018/02/24/go-based-python-modules.html) &#xA;but with the language pairing of Go and Julia.&#xA;&#xA;## Example 1, libtwice.go, libtwice.jl and libtwice_test.jl ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2018/03/11/accessing-go-from-julia.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Raspbian Stretch on DELL E4310 Laptop</title>
            <link>/blog/2017/12/18/raspbian-stretch-on-amd64.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Raspbian Stretch on DELL E4310 Laptop&#xA;&#xA;by R. S. Doiel 2017-12-18&#xA;&#xA;Today I bought a used Dell E4310 laptop. The E4310 is an &#34;old model&#34; now&#xA;but certainly not vintage yet.  It has a nice keyboard and reasonable &#xA;screen size and resolution. I bought it as a writing machine. I mostly&#xA;write in Markdown or Fountain depending on what I am writing these days.&#xA;&#xA;## Getting the laptop setup ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2017/12/18/raspbian-stretch-on-amd64.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Harvesting my Gists from GitHub</title>
            <link>/blog/2017/12/10/harvesting-my-gists-from-github.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Harvesting my Gists from GitHub&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2017-12-10&#xA;&#xA;This is a just quick set of notes on harvesting my Gists on GitHub so I&#xA;have an independent copy for my own website.&#xA;&#xA;## Assumptions ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2017/12/10/harvesting-my-gists-from-github.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>NodeJS, NPM, Electron</title>
            <link>/blog/2017/10/20/node-npm-electron.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# NodeJS, NPM, Electron&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2017-10-20&#xA;&#xA;Electron is an app platform leveraging web technologies. Conceptually it is a&#xA;mashup of NodeJS and Chrome browser. [Electron](https://electron.atom.io/) site&#xA;has a nice starter app. It displays a window with Electron version info and&#xA;&#39;hello world&#39;.&#xA;&#xA;Before you can get going with _Electron_ you need to have a&#xA;working _NodeJS_ and _NPM_. I usually compile from source and this&#xA;was my old recipe (adjusted for v8.7.0). ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2017/10/20/node-npm-electron.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Cross compiling Go 1.8.3 for Pine64 Pinebook</title>
            <link>/blog/2017/06/16/cross-compiling-go.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Cross compiling Go 1.8.3 for Pine64 Pinebook&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2017-06-16&#xA;&#xA;Pine64&#39;s Pinebook has a 64-bit Quad-Core ARM Cortex A53 which is &#xA;not the same ARM processor found on a Raspberry Pi 3. As a &#xA;result it needs its own compiled version of Go. Fortunately cross &#xA;compiling Go is very straight forward. I found two helpful Gists&#xA;on GitHub discussing compiling Go for a 64-Bit ARM processor.&#xA;&#xA;+ [conoro&#39;s gist](https://gist.github.com/conoro/4fca191fad018b6e47922a21fab499ca)&#xA;+ [truedat101&#39;s gist](https://gist.github.com/truedat101/5898604b1f7a1ec42d65a75fa6a0b802) ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2017/06/16/cross-compiling-go.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Android, Termux and Dev Environment</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/09/20/Android-Termux-Dev-environment.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Android, Termux and Dev Environment&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-09-20&#xA;&#xA;Recently I got a new Android 6 tablet. I got a case with a tiny Bluetooth keyboard. I started wondering if I could use it as a development device when on the road. So this is my diary of that test.&#xA;&#xA;## Challenges ...</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/09/20/Android-Termux-Dev-environment.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>From Markdown and Bash to mkpage</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/08/16/From-Markdown-and-Bash-to-mkpage.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;From Markdown and Bash to mkpage&#xA;================================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-08-16&#xA;&#xA;When I started maintaining a website on GitHub a few years ago my needs&#xA;were so simple I hand coded the HTML.  Eventually I adopted &#xA;a markdown processor for maintaining the prose. My &#34;theme&#34; was a&#xA;CSS file and some HTML fragments to wrap the markdown output. If I needed &#xA;interactivity I used JavaScript to access content via a web API. &#xA;Life was simple, all I had to learn to get started was Git and how to&#xA;populate a branch called &#34;gh-pages&#34;.&#xA;&#xA;## Deconstructing Content Management Systems ...</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/08/16/From-Markdown-and-Bash-to-mkpage.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Exploring Bash for Windows 10 Pro</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/08/15/Setting-up-Go-under-Bash-for-Windows-10.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Exploring Bash for Windows 10 Pro&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-08-15&#xA;&#xA;UPDATE (2016-10-27, RSD): Today trying to compile Go 1.7.3 under &#xA;    Windows 10 Pro I&#39;ve am getting compile errors when the &#xA;    assembler is being built.  I can compile go1.4.3 but see errors &#xA;    in some of the tests results.&#xA;&#xA;## Initial Setup and configuration ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/08/15/Setting-up-Go-under-Bash-for-Windows-10.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How to make a Pi-Top more Raspbian</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/07/04/How-To-Make-A-PiTop-More-Raspbian.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;How to make a Pi-Top more Raspbian&#xA;==================================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-07-04&#xA;&#xA;I have a first generation Pi-Top.  I like the idea but found I didn&#39;t use it much due to a preference for&#xA;basic Raspbian. With the recent Pi-TopOS upgrades I realized getting back to basic Raspbian was relatively&#xA;straight forward.&#xA;&#xA;## The recipe ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/07/04/How-To-Make-A-PiTop-More-Raspbian.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Instant Articles, Accelerated Mobile Pages, Twitter Cards and Open Graph</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/05/30/amp-cards-and-open-graph.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;# Instant Articles, Accelerated Mobile Pages, Twitter Cards and Open Graph&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-05-30&#xA;&#xA;## The problem&#xA;&#xA;The web has gotten slow. In [2016](http://httparchive.org/trends.php) the &#xA;average page weight is in multi-megabytes and the average number of network &#xA;requests needed to deliver the content is counted in &#xA;the hundreds. In the mix are saturated networks and a continued public &#xA;expectation of responsiveness (web wisdom suggests you have about 3 seconds &#xA;before people give up).  The odd thing is we&#39;ve known how to build fast &#xA;websites for a [decade](https://www.stevesouders.com/) or so.  &#xA;Collectively we don&#39;t build them [fast](https://www.sitepoint.com/average-page-weight-increased-another-16-2015/). ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/05/30/amp-cards-and-open-graph.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>OPML to Markdown and back</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/05/28/OPML-to-Markdown-and-back.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;OPML to Markdown and back&#xA;=========================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-05-28&#xA;&#xA;## Overview&#xA;&#xA;I wrote a Go language package to sort [OPML](http://dev.opml.org/spec2.html) outlines. &#xA;I wrote this because my preferred [feed reader ](http://goread.io) supports manual &#xA;sorting but not automatic alpha sorting by the _outline_ element&#39;s _text_ attribute. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/05/28/OPML-to-Markdown-and-back.md</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How to make a Pi-Top more Raspbian</title>
            <link>/blog/2016/07/04/How-To-Make-A-PiTop-More-Raspbian.md</link>
            <description>&#xA;&#xA;How to make a Pi-Top more Raspbian&#xA;==================================&#xA;&#xA;By R. S. Doiel 2016-07-04&#xA;&#xA;I have a first generation Pi-Top.  I like the idea but found I didn&#39;t use it much due to a preference for&#xA;basic Raspbian. With the recent Pi-TopOS upgrades I realized getting back to basic Raspbian was relatively&#xA;straight forward.&#xA;&#xA;## The recipe ...</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
            <guid>/blog/2016/07/04/How-To-Make-A-PiTop-More-Raspbian.md</guid>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>