<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <atom:link href="https://rsdoiel.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <title>Robert&#39;s ramblings and wonderig</title>
        <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io</link>
        <description>Robert&#39;s ramblings and wonderigs</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>pdtk rss 0.0.3</generator>
        <item>
            <title>11:30 AM, SQL: Postgres</title>
            <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/22/rosette-notes-2022-08-22_111130.html</link>
            <description>Post: Monday, August 22, 2022, 11:30 AM&#xA;&#xA;Two things have turned out to be challenges in the SQL I write, first back ticks is a MySQL-ism for literal quoting of table and column names, causes problems in Postgres. Second issue is &#34;REPLACE&#34; is a none standard extension I picked up from MySQL [it wraps a DELETE and INSERT together](https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/extensions-to-ansi.html), should be using UPDATE more than I have done in the past.&#xA;&#xA; ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/22/rosette-notes-2022-08-22_111130.html</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Rosette Notes: Postgres and MySQL</title>
            <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/19/rosette-notes.html</link>
            <description>&gt; A dance around two relational databases, piecing together similarities as with the tiny mosaic tiles of a guitar&#39;s rosette&#xA;&#xA;What follows are my preliminary notes learning Postgres 12 and 14.&#xA;&#xA;This is a short comparison of some administrative commands I commonly use. The first column describes the task followed by the SQL to execute for Postgres 14.5 and then MySQL 8. The presumption is you&#39;re using `psql` to access Postgres and `mysql` to  access MySQL. Values between `&lt;` and `&gt;` should be replaced with an appropriate value.&#xA;&#xA;| Task                    | Postgres 14.5                     | MySQL 8           |&#xA;|-------------------------|------------------------------------|-------------------|&#xA;| show all databases      | `SELECT datname FROM pg_database;` | `SHOW DATABASES;` |&#xA;| select a database       | `\c &lt;dbname&gt;`                      | `USE &lt;dbname&gt;`    |&#xA;| show tables in database | `\dt`                              | `SHOW TABLES;`    |&#xA;| show columns in table   | `SELECT column_name, data_type FROM information_schema.columns WHERE table_name = &#39;&lt;table_name&gt;&#39;;` | `SHOW COLUMNS IN &lt;table_name&gt;` |&#xA;&#xA;The Postgres shell, `psql`, provides the functionality of showing a list of tables via a short cut while MySQL choose to add the `SHOW TABLES` query. For me `SHOW ...` feels like SQL where as `\d` or `\dt` takes me out of SQL space. On the other hand given Postgres metadata structure the shortcut is appreciated and I often query for table names as I forget them. `\dt` quickly becomes second nature and is shorter to type than `SHOW TABLES`. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/19/rosette-notes.html</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Pdtk and STN</title>
            <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/golang-development.html</link>
            <description>This log is a proof of concept in using [simple timesheet notation](https://rsdoiel.github.io/stngo/docs/stn.html) as a source for very short blog posts. The tooling is written in Golang (though eventually I hope to port it to Oberon-07).  The implementation combines two of my personal projects, [stngo](https://github.com/rsdoiel/stngo) and my experimental writing tool [pdtk](https://github.com/rsdoiel/pdtk). Updating the __pdtk__ cli I added a function to the &#34;blogit&#34; action that will translates the simple timesheet notation (aka STN) to a short blog post.  My &#34;short post&#34; interest is a response to my limited writing time. What follows is the STN markup. See the [Markdown](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rsdoiel/rsdoiel.github.io/main/blog/2022/08/15/golang-development.md) source for the unprocessed text.&#xA;&#xA;2022-08-15&#xA;&#xA;16:45 - 17:45; Golang; ptdk, stngo; Thinking through what a &#34;post&#34; from an simple timesheet notation file should look like. One thing occurred to me is that the entry&#39;s &#34;end&#34; time is the publication date, not the start time. That way the post is based on when it was completed not when it was started. There is an edge case of where two entries end at the same time on the same date. The calculated filename will collide. In the `BlogSTN()` function I could check for potential file collision and either issue a warning or append. Not sure of the right action. Since I write sequentially this might not be a big problem, not sure yet. Still playing with formatting before I add this type of post to my blog. Still not settled on the title question but I need something to link to from my blog&#39;s homepage and that &#34;title&#34; is what I use for other posts. Maybe I should just use a command line option to provide a title?&#xA;&#xA;2022-08-14&#xA;&#xA;14:00 - 17:00; Golang; pdtk, stngo; Today I started an experiment. I cleaned up stngo a little today, still need to implement a general `Parse()` method that works on a `io.Reader`. After a few initial false starts I realized the &#34;right&#34; place for rendering simple timesheet notation as blog posts is in the the &#34;blogit&#34; action of [pdtk](https://rsdoiel.github.io/pdtk). I think this form might be useful for both release notes in projects as well as a series aggregated from single paragraphs. The limitation of the single paragraph used in simple timesheet notation is intriguing. Proof of concept is working in v0.0.3 of pdtk. Still sorting out if I need a title and if so what it should be. ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/golang-development.html</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>5:45 PM, Golang: ptdk,  stngo</title>
            <link>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/golang-development-2022-08-15_170545.html</link>
            <description>By R. S. Doiel, Monday, August 15, 2022 17:05 PDT&#xA;&#xA;Thinking through what a &#34;post&#34; from an simple timesheet notation file should look like. One thing occurred to me is that the entry&#39;s &#34;end&#34; time is the publication date, not the start time. That way the post is based on when it was completed not when it was started. There is an edge case of where two entries end at the same time on the same date. The calculated filename will collide. In the `BlogSTN()` function I could check for potential file collision and either issue a warning or append. Not sure of the right action. Since I write sequentially this might not be a big problem, not sure yet. Still playing with formatting before I add this type of post to my blog. Still not settled on the title question but I need something to link to from my blog&#39;s homepage and that &#34;title&#34; is what I use for other posts. Maybe I should just use a command line option to provide a title?&#xA;&#xA; ...</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid>https://rsdoiel.github.io/blog/2022/08/15/golang-development-2022-08-15_170545.html</guid>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
